<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Bay Area Metropolitan Observer</title>
  <id>urn:uuid:52c4ddef-40d4-3bc8-bbd3-d91037b58706</id>
  <updated>2016-12-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/" />
  <link href="http://sfbamo.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <author>
    <name></name>
  </author>
  <generator uri="https://github.com/ajdavis/lektor-atom" version="0.2">Lektor Atom Plugin</generator>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/in-memoriam-micah-danemayer/">
    <title type="text">In Memoriam: Micah Danemayer</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:6005b4b9-2719-3139-a8dd-fa6503be4cf2</id>
    <updated>2016-12-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/in-memoriam-micah-danemayer/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Micah Danemayer, 28, channeled a life force that even death could not extinguish. Indeed, the Ghost Ship tragedy that claimed his terrestrial existence along with 35 others seems to only have brought me closer to the community Micah himself introduced me to, just a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Micah was one of the first people to introduce themselves to me after I moved to the East Bay in 2014 and started attending local concerts. Between acts at the closing party for Downtown Oakland’s Moco Gallery, Micah simply passed me his bottle of bourbon and started talking to me about music, as though we’d known each other for decades. The feeling persisted, even after his passing, when he appeared to me in a dream this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Micah,” I said, “there are tributes to you all over town. So many good shows—I wish you could be there, man!”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Micah smiled and responded in his habitually cheeky way, sticking his tongue out and flashing the devil-horns hand gesture, shouting &lt;em&gt;slayyy it duder!&lt;/em&gt; I woke from my dream with the image of him smiling and winking, very much in the style of his idol, David Bowie.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At the Ghost Ship, Micah was manning the projector during various performances, conjuring masterful avant-garde splashes of light and color under the moniker Visual Aids, just as he had been last year, during my only visit to the ill-fated venue. I feel immensely fortunate to have experienced his multisensory art firsthand.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It’s impossible to overstate what a pillar Micah was in the local arts community. Last performing under the name &lt;a href=&quot;https://discardedrecords.bandcamp.com/album/paralycyst-damage-done-discarded-007&quot;&gt;Paralycyst&lt;/a&gt;, he combined a penchant for densely-textured industrial sounds with an unabashed love of pure, decadent acid techno. &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/redcellaroakland&quot;&gt;Red Cellar&lt;/a&gt;, his new duo with another local techno master &lt;a href=&quot;https://discardedrecords.bandcamp.com/album/regretamine-headcave-microrave-006&quot;&gt;Regretamine&lt;/a&gt;, was slated to make its live debut next month at Obscura Machina, Micah’s monthly series of curated “micro-rave” concerts. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/1150785288339183/&quot;&gt;The show will go on&lt;/a&gt; in his honor.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Micah’s personal warmth and open heart brought him to introduce me to many other heroes in the Bay Area’s incendiary techno scene including &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/countervulture&quot;&gt;Countervulture&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://discardedrecords.bandcamp.com/album/type-b-discarded-008&quot;&gt;Type B&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://discardedrecords.bandcamp.com/album/forbidden-colors-discarded-004&quot;&gt;Forbidden Colors&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/heartworm&quot;&gt;Heartworm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/hom&quot;&gt;HOM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/404-not-found-4&quot;&gt;404 Not Found&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://discardedrecords.bandcamp.com/album/bonus-beast-discarded-005&quot;&gt;Bonus Beast&lt;/a&gt;, to name but a few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/277770433&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/291549147&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;He was the glue that held us together and continues to inspire us. We love you, Micah.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-francisco-approves-200-units-with-state-density-bonus/">
    <title type="text">San Francisco Approves 200 Units with State Density Bonus</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:87cf3fe1-4905-36a9-a8de-796815141ab6</id>
    <updated>2016-12-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-francisco-approves-200-units-with-state-density-bonus/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a landmark decision last Thursday, the San Francisco Planning Commission voted 5-1 to approve a project with 200 dwelling units at 333 12th Street in the South of Market (SoMa) District. Spearheaded by local developer Panoramic Interests, the project makes local history by being the first development in San Francisco to invoke the State Density Bonus law to add more units to the project.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Dubbed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panoramic.com/cityspaces-location/cityspaces-333-12th-st/&quot;&gt;“CitySpaces 333,”&lt;/a&gt; the six-story building will contain 200 “micro-unit” apartments, some with up to four bedrooms, with bike storage and two car-sharing spots instead of private parking.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Initially planned solely for student housing, the project would have qualified under the city’s Student Housing Ordinance exempting the developer from including any on-site Below Market Rate (BMR) units. San Francisco recently raised those requirements to 25% BMR for new rental housing under June’s Proposition C, though CitySpaces 333 was grandfathered in under earlier, lower requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It’s a huge step forward,” said Zac Shore of Panoramic Interests. “The State Density Bonus dovetails nicely with our student housing application, enabling us to keep the subsidized units on-site while building 52 additional units of much needed student housing for nonprofit schools.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;CitySpaces 333 qualified for a 35% increase in density in exchange for providing 11% of its units—16 total—at rents permanently affordable to Very Low-Income households, defined as earning up to 50% of the Area Median Income. Should Panoramic end a leasing agreement with a 501(c)(3) educational nonprofit, the building would be required to provide an additional 7% BMR under the Western SoMa neighborhood plan.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In other words, this landmark project will combine student dormitories with subsidized housing for any low-income household that completes the lottery application process through the Mayor’s Office of Housing. Should the project cease to include dorms, more subsidized housing will take their place.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Shore also noted that the two additional floors would change the construction from a wood-frame building  to concrete. “The additional units granted under the state density bonus allow us to make that construction cost increase work financially, while keeping the subsidized units on site,” he said. “The state density bonus seems to be one of the only ways to work with the inclusionary housing requirements brought on by Prop C.” (Earlier this year, a &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/&quot;&gt;investigation&lt;/a&gt; found that fewer residential units had been proposed after the passage of Proposition C.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The state density bonus has been a hot-button issue in San Francisco politics: up throughout this year,  legislators and stakeholders were bitterly divided over the proposed &lt;a href=&quot;http://hoodline.com/2016/06/votes-on-dueling-plans-reveal-what-sf-supervisors-really-believe-about-housing-solutions&quot;&gt;Affordable Housing Bonus Program (AHBP)&lt;/a&gt;, a local implementation of the state density bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Planning Commissioner Dennis Richards voted in favor of the project, but also stated in an interview that he was open-minded to the opponents’ concerns that the density bonus did not adequately maximize affordability. “What we have is a policy issue, and you don’t evaluate policy over a specific project—you make policy to apply to many projects. So I think they got that backwards,” he said. “Now, what do you do to get the maximum number of affordable units you can? That’s what we have to figure out. That’s the policy issue.” Aside from their deliberations on specific projects, Commissioner Richards noted that the Planning Commission is able to send communications to the Board of Supervisors urging any number of policy reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The developer has the law on their side,” Richards added. “We sat there with the seven pages of the law printed out in front of us.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In late September, Governor Jerry Brown approved &lt;a href=&quot;https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billHistoryClient.xhtml?bill_id=201520160AB2501&quot;&gt;AB 2501&lt;/a&gt; a bill proposed by State Assemblymember Richard Bloom (Santa Monica) requiring local municipalities to enact their own standards of compliance to the State Density Bonus. In part, the bill reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&quot;All cities, counties, or cities and counties shall adopt an ordinance that specifies how compliance with this section will be implemented. Failure to adopt an ordinance shall not relieve a city, county, or city and county from complying with this section.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;… &quot;A local government shall not condition the submission, review, or approval of an application pursuant to this chapter on the preparation of an additional report or study that is not otherwise required by state law, including this section.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/in-loving-memory/">
    <title type="text">In Loving Memory</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:018dd771-7335-3a2f-8e74-2e1741b0f53f</id>
    <updated>2016-12-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/in-loving-memory/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Please donate to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youcaring.com/firevictimsofoaklandfiredec232016-706684&quot;&gt;relief fund&lt;/a&gt; for victims of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbaytimes.com/2016/12/03/oakland-massive-fire-at-live-work-space-in-fruitvale-district/&quot;&gt;Ghost Ship&lt;/a&gt; fire in Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Words cannot describe the devastation we feel at the loss of many beloved friends. I personally have lost heroes, mentors, incomparable kindred spirits. While I will remain offline for a few days to process this grief, readers should be aware of many &lt;a href=&quot;https://helpghostship.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;relief efforts&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/1200018936718540/&quot;&gt;benefit concerts&lt;/a&gt;, and other &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/174030323063264/&quot;&gt;fundraisers&lt;/a&gt; to aid those affected and, hopefully, prevent future tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On behalf of those who didn't, we owe it to each other to rise from the ashes. We need each other now more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/planning-commission-approves-senior-housing-in-mission-district/">
    <title type="text">Planning Commission Approves Senior Housing in Mission District</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:20e138a5-2410-3804-9f6a-0bd80a9a09e1</id>
    <updated>2016-12-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/planning-commission-approves-senior-housing-in-mission-district/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After a marathon hearing at the San Francisco Planning Commission, the 9-story apartment project proposed at 1296 Shotwell Street for low-income seniors in the Mission District received its permit approvals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The non-profit developers building the 94-unit project, the Mission Economic Development Agency (MEDA) and the Chinatown Community Development Center, have held community meetings for &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/05/neighbors-of-mission-district-affordable-housing-cry-too-tall/&quot;&gt;over six months&lt;/a&gt; to interface with concerned neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Units in the building will be reserved for senior citizens early 50% of the Area Median Income, with one-fifth further earmarked for formerly homeless seniors.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Craig Weber, an accountant and nearby landlord, objected to the total lack of parking and increased density on a residential street. Weber’s mother, Connie Weber, was the only other speaker testifying against the project. “We have enough big buildings,” she said, adding that she had lived on Shotwell Street for 85 years.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sam Moss, director of the Mission Housing Development Company, testified in response to fears that parking was a serious issue. “We know senior projects work well without parking,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many local Mission District activists, noted in &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/12/senior-housing-on-shotwell-brings-foes-together/&quot;&gt;Mission Local&lt;/a&gt; as more frequently mobilizing to speak against market-rate developments, rallied to support the development. A variety of elderly Latino residents gave supporting testimony in Spanish, through an interpreter. San Francisco, one speaker insisted, “a beautiful city if it had buildings for all these people.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Laura Clark, founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.growsanfrancisco.org/&quot;&gt;Grow San Francisco&lt;/a&gt;, was pleased with the outcome, but qualified her optimism: “If a perfect project like this, that everyone loves, with 100% affordable housing, still has to go through a five-hour hearing like this and face neighborhood opposition, what hope do we have of fixing the city’s raw housing shortage? I hope this sends a clear message that everyone stands to benefit from serious process reform.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/">
    <title type="text">Editorial: Prop 13, or, California's Progressive Blindspot Illuminated</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:b8a7955f-e081-3b8c-bcf0-7596f08a8da4</id>
    <updated>2016-12-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In 1979, California voters passed Proposition 13. This locked in property tax rates at a maximum rate of 1% of its assessed value, which can change at most 2% per year. Most voters (in the counties labeled green above) hoped to protect homeowners from the market volatility of their own equity values, preventing foreclosures that could occur if tax assessments became more than their incomes could bear. Sounds good, right?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, the ballot measure legislated a de facto caste system benefiting legacy landowners. Ralph McLaughlin, Chief Economist at the real estate website Trulia has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trulia.com/blog/trends/prop-13/&quot;&gt;recently published data to illustrate this&lt;/a&gt;: by comparing current assessments to market values, McLaughlin calculated “effective” property tax rates, essentially the difference between what an established owner pays, and what a new buyer would pay today.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Revolt” sounds too noble to me, even “populist.” I prefer to call it feudalism.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/prop13fig2lao.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: Legislative Analyst's Office)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Prop 13 had further consequences: tax rates could only be reassessed upon sale of the property, whereas before, homes could be reassessed if anyone in the neighborhood sold for a higher price. Additionally, taxes in general became much more difficult to change. The state of California controls all property tax policy, and can only raise taxes with a 2/3 vote from the legislature. Municipalities could only introduce new taxes by referendum, also with a 2/3 margin if they intend to spend revenue for a specific purpose. Schools, infrastructure, and all sorts of public services have since relied on much less stable revenue streams, namely income and sales taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Like most policies enacted in response to fear, Prop 13 has demonstrably done more harm than good. The Legislative Analyst’s Office &lt;a href=&quot;http://lao.ca.gov/Publications/Report/3497&quot;&gt;also reported&lt;/a&gt; what everyone has known for years: the tax burden has inordinately shifted to newer residents. Even within the same neighborhood, owners pay wildly diverging tax rates.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;More damningly, McLaughlin reports: “In 2015 alone, California homeowners received over $12.5 billion in savings from Prop 13, while local governments lost that same amount.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/prop13fig4lao.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: LAO)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, since higher-earning households are more likely to own higher-value properties, the tax break inordinately benefits the wealthiest Californians. Palo Alto, one of the state’s most expensive towns, has the lowest effective rate. Mercifully, Palo Altans do not live in fear of underwater equity.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lucky children who inherit valuable property also inherit their parent’s Prop 13-based tax assessments. Not only does the policy establish a sort of feudalism via subsidy, it also encourages the consolidation of dynastic wealth. New, young computer programmers with six-figure salaries may easy to scapegoat as the emblem of the Bay Area’s 21st Century inequality, but even if they can afford real estate, their privilege is chump change compared to that of pre-1979 homebuyers and their descendants.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/prop13_supportinggraphic_v07-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: Trulia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, renters &lt;em&gt;qua&lt;/em&gt; renters do not get tax benefits for renting a place to sleep, only a place to work. While the state codified price controls for property owners, many renters were stripped of similar protections in 1995 when the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/its-time-to-overturn-the-state-ban-on-rent-control/Content?oid=4229744&quot;&gt;Costa Hawkins Act&lt;/a&gt; banned rent control in dwelling units built after 1977.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Let’s be clear: if your landlord raises your rent, and they’ve owned the building since before either tech boom, they are literally the landed gentry profiting off your serfdom. If that rent increase isn’t limited by rent control, you are being denied a privilege your landlord enjoys.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;You may assume that given this bleak picture, California lawmakers must be scrambling to make fundamental changes to the state’s tax structure, and you would not be wholly incorrect. State Senator Loni Hancock (SD09) has recently proposed a “split-roll” tax reform, which would gradually decouple Prop 13 caps on commercial real estate from those on residential property.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Split-roll reform has its own problems. Skeptics fear that only assessing commercial property at market rates would exacerbate imbalances between jobs and housing by further incentivizing commercial development over residential. But the logic in support is that it’s fairer to raise taxes on Disneyland than grandmothers living on Social Security checks. The cynical logic is that it’s the only politically palatable reform—but even current Governor Jerry Brown has said he won’t touch it.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Before you close out of this article and curse Jerry’s obstinate, some would say overzealous pragmatism, let’s take a look at where the conversation on housing costs &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; gone. Like a feeble stream trickling through a rocky mountainside, the “third rail” of Prop 13 reform keeps the debate over housing reforms locked into tragicomic and ineffective limits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco projects a culture that is, shall we say, not fond of capitalism, and the so-called “progressive” faction has seized on this image, while the ostensible “moderates” remain largely agnostic, or at least anemic. The progressive faction’s rhetorically compassionate, class-warrior-tinged proposals to solve the region’s crippling housing crisis tend to follow this basic narrative:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yes, there is a shortage of housing supply. Yes, more must be built. But without strong protections for incumbent residents, and aggressive price controls to protect everyone without exorbitant incomes, all new privately financed market-rate development must be treated as guilty before proven innocent. New construction, lacking drastic state-wide rent control reform and ever-higher ratios of Below Market Rate units, will be guilty of gentrification and displacement. A shiny new mid-rise in the Mission District will not only fail to fully alleviate a supply shortage on its own, it will also raise median rents in the area such that vulnerable lower-income residents will be forced out. New development is bad until proven good. We need more housing, but let’s not be careless here.*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Reasonable enough, no? No.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I’ll point to the more obvious holes first. Most demand for new construction has concentrated in the Mission District because San Francisco has lower-density zoning in wealthier neighborhoods once explicitly segregated for “whites-only.” When activists rally to protect the Mission, the elephant in the room is that nobody is wringing their hands about gentrification in North Beach, Pac Heights, Bernal Heights, Russian Hill, Forest Hill, and so on—because those neighborhoods &lt;em&gt;are already rich&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;they will be fine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Marina Dwellers will be fine. Telegraph Hill Dwellers will be fine. Developers are not frothing at the mouth to build tall residences all over there for the influx of new workers coming to the city, except, notably, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/designs-released-for-affordable-housing-in-telegraph-hill/&quot;&gt;some low- and middle-income housing planned near the port&lt;/a&gt;. They should be.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In my paraphrase above, did you notice something missing? I used the term “Below Market Rate” (BMR) for what is often called “affordable housing,” but I did not use the term “subsidy.” This is because inclusionary zoning requirements do not provide price-indexed dwelling units with public money. Private development pays for it with a cut on investment returns—a cut that is passed on to market-rate renters.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;How curious, then, that the proposed “progressive” solutions to our housing affordability crisis contain many caveats that may end up being &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/&quot;&gt;a detriment&lt;/a&gt; to longer-term affordability goals. In the context of Proposition 13, this is relevant because inclusionary zoning (or fees paid “in-lieu” of “affordable” units) are a tax, but are much easier to codify, because they are not called a tax. Affordable housing is largely not funded by actual taxes because the vast majority of real estate equity gains are left untouched.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I’m going to shoot the messengers now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Aaron Peskin, who &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/Prop-C-would-raise-new-housing-s-below-market-7388907.php&quot;&gt;coauthored&lt;/a&gt; the new 25% Below Market Rate requirements and &lt;a href=&quot;http://hoodline.com/2015/04/major-8-washington-opponent-backs-peskin-s-d3-supervisor-bid&quot;&gt;opposed development on the city’s waterfront&lt;/a&gt;, was given a duplex in Telegraph Hill by his parents, purchased for $800,000, which was since converted to a single-family residence. Sale prices in that neighborhood often hit the $2 million mark now, but Peskin pays taxes on an assessed value of $1 million. Though also a realtor and landlord, Peskin magnanimously lacks a profit-seeking talent, at least in his role as a public official. During negotiations to sell city-owned real estate, Peskin demanded $7 million higher than the highest bid of $80 million, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/aaron-peskins-art-of-no-deal/&quot;&gt;the deal fell through&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Dean Preston, a tenant defense attorney, recently ran an unsuccessful campaign to replace London Breed as Supervisor for District 5. He has regularly called for restricting density along the transit-rich corridor of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?hl=en&amp;amp;q=http://hoodline.com/2015/10/affordable-divis-group-defines-goals&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1480730509962000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNFPhv5XnzAFsiATQ0Bbfi3dxPfUbQ&quot;&gt;Divisadero Street&lt;/a&gt;, building less housing at the site of a former gas station, and has often &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/London-Breed-Dean-Preston-argue-personal-9283790.php&quot;&gt;condescended&lt;/a&gt; to Breed, a lifelong renter, during the campaign. Preston has admirably called for &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@DeanPreston/rent-control-for-midtown-2dfc435b971c#.db8z27fye&quot;&gt;expanded rent control&lt;/a&gt;, which is particularly admirable given the price controls he enjoys. About that: his home on Alamo Square, purchased by his wife’s parents, is assessed at just under $1.2 million. Homes around Alamo Square regularly fetch between $2-2.5 million sale prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Calvin Welch, who sits on the board of the Haight-Ashbury Neighborhood Council (HANC), recently described the Affordable Housing Bonus Program (AHBP), a density bonus allowing additional floors in new buildings in exchange for higher BMR percentages, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/01/sf-delays-controversial-housing-law-amidst-opposition-cries-of-ethnic-cleansing/&quot;&gt;“ethnic cleansing.”&lt;/a&gt; For &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/video-san-franciscos-pony-tailed-godfather-of-white-paternalism/&quot;&gt;a variety of reasons&lt;/a&gt;, he has been called the “godfather of white paternalism in San Francisco”—for example, after dismissing homeownership as a “bankrupt dream” in the early 1970s, he bought a duplex in the Haight. Its net taxable value hovers around $65,000 in a neighborhood with a median home price of $1.3 million (and that’s for single-family residences).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Zelda Bronstein, an allegedly socialist firebrand, has written at length about &lt;a href=&quot;http://48hills.org/2016/11/28/17209/&quot;&gt;the indignation&lt;/a&gt; she feels about San Francisco’s projected population growth reaching 1 million people without anyone personally requesting her permission. She pays property taxes on an assessed value of $467,790 in a neighborhood where homes regularly fetch $1 million. Her most lauded accomplishment as chair of Berkeley’s Planning Commission is the approval of a park across the street from her house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Becky O’Malley, editor of the &lt;em&gt;Berkeley Daily Planet&lt;/em&gt;, is fond of writing screeds against new development and newer, younger residents in Berkeley. In one editorial, she &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleydailyplanet.com/issue/2016-06-10/article/44573?headline=Keeping-on-Keepin-On-even-in-the-summertime--Becky-O-Malley&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; a planned 7-story apartment building near the UC Berkeley campus as “the kind designed for cramming in as many students who want to party it up without dorm rules as possible.” (The project will be replacing a 2-story commercial building that does not meet seismic safety requirements.) Mr. and Mrs. O’Malley, who founded the &lt;em&gt;Planet&lt;/em&gt; as a retirement project after selling a successful software company for millions, pay taxes on an assessed value of $116,440. Homes regularly surpass the $2 million price in their neighborhood, though the median is closer to $1.5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Joe Bravo, a lawyer and landlord residing in Forest Hills, has publicly opposed a proposal for a five-story housing project for low-income senior citizens. In an &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/11/18/13681294/forest-hill-sf-senior-housing-joe-bravo&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with Curbed SF, Bravo said he objected to the height of the project, and feared that allowing development above zoned height limits would only benefit “high tech” people. Bravo’s home in Forest Hill is assessed at a $1.1 million net taxable value. Homes of a similar size sell for up to $3 million in that neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I made a handy graphic to illustrate this coalition’s approach to housing affordability:&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/malthus-lol.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A funny joke inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malthusian_growth_model&quot;&gt;Thomas Malthus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It is a given that the Bay Area does not have enough housing to accommodate population growth. Few deny this. It is also a given that land is finite in coastal cities, and new rental properties so prohibitively expensive, so privately-financed development alone will not ease this crisis for the state’s lesser-privileged residents (or, for that matter, lesser-privileged hopeful migrants).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What is not as commonly agreed upon is who should pay more to bridge that gap between what the market will bear and what people need &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;. Who is holding out on us?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A friend once told me, only halfway joking, that “if you want to eat the rich, it helps to have them living nearby.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Proposition 13, Old Money doesn’t want New Money living nearby. The rest of us are left to pick up the pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/menlo-park-approves-fivefold-increase-in-housing-near-facebook/">
    <title type="text">Menlo Park Approves Fivefold Increase in Housing Near Facebook</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:55a86e1a-7676-3d0b-97ec-d0f89badbbc4</id>
    <updated>2016-11-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/menlo-park-approves-fivefold-increase-in-housing-near-facebook/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At a special meeting last night, Menlo Park’s City Council approved an upgrade to the city’s General Plan by a 4-1 vote, a significant reform to local land-use regulations that have been largely untouched since 1994. After weathering mild controversies over Facebook’s proposal to build workforce housing near their corporate campus, Menlo Park has essentially quintupled its allowable residential capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Known as ConnectMenlo, the plan to encourage mixed-use development in Menlo Park has been a top priority on the City Council’s Work Plan for 2016. These efforts include rezonings that will allow for more “vibrant” uses of land, including entertainment and retail where such establishments were previously not allowed. Crucially, the plan rezones the Bayside area, home to Facebook’s global headquarters, to include 5,500 dwelling units—a net increase of 4,500 units. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.menlopark.org/DocumentCenter/View/12418&quot;&gt;staff report&lt;/a&gt; delivered to the Council, city staff “anticipates working with property owners to aggressively recruit new retail and entertainment uses as soon as the zoning allows.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The plan also includes goals for 20% Below Market Rate units in all new residential developments.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/menlo-park-approves-fivefold-increase-in-housing-near-facebook/g1-connectmenlo_201611231212296985.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: ConnectMenlo)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This update is the culmination of over 60 community meetings, in which neighbors and commercial stakeholders met to discuss a “live/work/play” neighborhood plan to revitalize a mostly industrial area. “Transportation was an important concern,” said Adina Levin, a Menlo Park resident and board member of Friends Of Caltrain who attended many meetings. “One of the motivations to approve the plan is that housing is an important transportation solution to help people commute and run errands without driving.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Under new Green and Sustainable Building Standards in the General Plan upgrade, future development will have to conform to requirements for water efficiency and recycling, including dual plumbing and water budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/menlo-park-approves-fivefold-increase-in-housing-near-facebook/mp-far.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In anticipation of an argument that arises time and again in San Francisco’s contentious land-use battles, the rezonings will also require a diversity of units, both for single occupants and families. One of the new districts will implement a “sliding scale” for the Floor Area Ratio (FAR) of units, which staff writes “would help create a mix of appropriately sized units instead of a few units that are very large.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/">
    <title type="text">Tiny Houses, Huge Hurdles: Panoramic and the Future of Supportive Housing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:2bd97aa1-69d1-36cc-9e73-a5e37a407e06</id>
    <updated>2016-11-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Imagine having no place to live in one of the planet’s most expensive metropolitan areas. For many residents of San Francisco, this is a daily reality. Yet while labor and investment capital pours in, the region’s culture of technological “innovation” has failed to improve the livelihoods of our most vulnerable neighbors. Patrick Kennedy wants to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On a rainy Sunday afternoon, the developer at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panoramic.com/cityspaces-location/cityspaces-micropad/&quot;&gt;Panoramic Interests&lt;/a&gt; welcomed us into his MicroPAD™, a prefabricated “micro-unit” dwelling designed to lower the cost of housing the city’s homeless. Panoramic advertises that construction costs are just 40% of conventional costs. He is visibly beaming as he shows us every miniscule feature, an effortless grin glowing brighter than his neon-yellow raincoat.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/pano2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diagram of the MicroPAD (courtesy: Panoramic Interests)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In general, it is striking how modern such cozy accommodations can appear without looking garishly futuristic. The wooden kitchen cabinets and countertop, the latter painted a gentle cream color, could be from any decade. The bathroom, Kennedy’s favorite feature, is far more welcoming than my own: illuminated by a warm blue light, it features two drains, a slip-resistant floor, and is bounded by shatterproof glass.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/micropad_looking-in.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interior view from the entrance, on a sunny day (courtesy: Panoramic)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The microwave doubles as an oven; the closet could fit twice as much clothes as my walk-in closet. I count at least four electrical outlets, each equipped with additional USB ports. Underneath the bed, you can turn on a blue light that kills bedbugs.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kennedy even has me step outside of the unit and scream at the top of my lungs into the closed window. Inside, the group can scarcely hear a mutter—a useful design feature to have on 9th &amp;amp; Mission, the bustling intersection where Panoramic’s sample MicroPAD now sits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/pano1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yours truly, shouting at the window&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kennedy overhears me praise many features in comparison to my own apartment, and immediately discourages me from doing so. “The point is not to compare this to your own home,.” adds Laura Clark, housing advocate and founder of the nonprofit group &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.growsanfrancisco.org/&quot;&gt;Grow San Francisco&lt;/a&gt;. “Compare this to living on the street. Otherwise, many people get turned off.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The 160-square foot units aim to maximize livability and dignity for the city’s nearly 7,000 homeless residents (at the lowest estimate) while minimizing overhead costs. They’re larger than a typical Single-Room Occupancy (SRO) unit, which are operated like hotels and typically have shared facilities rather than private ones.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://modernluxury.com/san-francisco/story/think-small&quot;&gt;Politically, there’s only one problem:&lt;/a&gt; Mr. Kennedy wants to be a landlord.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Panoramic hopes to stack their prefab modular units, manufactured at Chinese steel plants, in structures up to 8 stories high on city-owned land. (Build any higher, says Kennedy, and costs increase dramatically due to necessary fire codes and other structural costs.) Kennedy hopes to finance this by leasing the units out to the city for $1000 per unit per month. Essentially, the City &amp;amp; County of San Francisco would be a master tenant for the thousands of housing-insecure and homeless residents Panoramic hopes to help.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco is both too dogmatically leftist and too old-school industrialist for this to sit well with the political establishment. The city’s so-called “progressive” faction—whose standard-bearers on the Board of Supervisors, David Campos and Aaron Peskin, both own increasingly valuable homes in upscale neighborhoods—are skeptical that investment capital can have any positive impact in such a crisis of inequality. Meanwhile, the so-called “moderate” faction, beholden to many labor unions as a driving force of their threadbare coalition, is hesitant to support anything without generous local-hire guarantees.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The rents he’s proposing, furthermore, have drawn the ire of the nonprofit development community, who are accustomed to remaining in everyone’s good graces by asking for lower prices from the public sector. Kennedy, for his part, was quick to dismiss this faction as “vigilantes” and a “cartel” &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/the-kennedy-touch-one-case-study-in-berkeley-development/Content?oid=1065637&quot;&gt;fifteen years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/micropad_looking-towards-door.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interior view from the window, facing the door (courtesy: Panoramic)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Our conversation turns to the looming federal tyranny many San Franciscans fear, a fear that nearly drained this author of all physical energy that very morning.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think Trump has his sights set on us,” Kennedy tells me. “Even if there’s a trade war with China, there’s no domestic industry to protect, as far as our work is concerned.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This is because Panoramic deals with Chinese manufacturers that sweat every detail. “Our manufacturers install everything in the factory. There’s very little you have to do after delivery, but usually with domestic modular construction, a lot of prep work has to be done anyway. Here, they include the coffeemaker and the mugs. The closet came with coat hangers.” But worse case scenario, if a trade war got seriously ugly? “If an American manufacturer were to offer this, we’d be first in line.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite the ossified political gridlock, Panoramic’s idea is gaining traction. Recently, Planning Commissioners Kathryn Moore and Dennis Richards visited the MicroPAD and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfhac.org/san-francisco-planning-commissioners-impressed-micropad/&quot;&gt;spoke at length about its merits at a public hearing&lt;/a&gt;. Kennedy also says Berkeley City Councilmember Kriss Worthington was impressed after his visit.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But the pride Kennedy takes in his work can’t lift the grimness that hangs heavy over our hearts. What does, for the time being, is a piping hot cappuccino at the café next door, which Kennedy treats us to after the tour.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I stare into an ornate leaf pattern drawn into the milk foam. Outside, the haggard figure of a homeless human being pushes a shopping cart past the corner of my eye. What good is wealth if it doesn’t improve human welfare? What good are ideals if they don't proffer real hope?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We’re in this for the money, among other things,” Kennedy says to us before we part ways. (He loves to cheekily confess to that motive quite often.) “You guys,” he says, nodding at Clark, “are in this for the good of it. Because housing is a good thing.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“See you soon,” everyone says to each other, almost at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/open-letter-forest-hill-affordable-housing/">
    <title type="text">Open Letter: Forest Hill Affordable Housing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:cdb18f90-b68c-31d1-ba13-f05946c1028c</id>
    <updated>2016-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/open-letter-forest-hill-affordable-housing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Concerned Citizens</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor's Note: this letter was sent to District 7 Supervisor Norman Yee by constituents who have agreed to publish its contents under the condition of anonymity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Yee,&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As 40+ year residents of San Francisco now living in Parkmerced, we are seniors without a personal need for affordable housing, but there are thousands of people in this city NOT so lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We urge you to support, and allow the other supervisors to support,  the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/forest-hill-neighbors-oppose-150-unit-senior-housing-proposal/&quot;&gt;affordable senior housing development&lt;/a&gt; proposed for the Christian Church site in Forest Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We were homeowners in Forest Hill for 15 years, living near the Forest Hill Clubhouse.  We would support the development if we lived there still.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We understand that the leader of the opposition to the development is an attorney whose property apparently lies on the hillside above the proposed site.  Thus, the development IS more or less in his back yard....and all the arguments he advances in opposition to the development are classic NIMBY arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;You are aware as we are that there is a housing crisis in this city.  That crisis can only be resolved by construction of more housing for the people coming to San Francisco, as we came before the Summer of Love.  The City is never going to be restored to what it was then, regardless of the activities of the faux progressives like Aaron Peskin, who, with his allies, operates an elaborate pay 4 play form of crony capitalism favoring those developers who contribute largely to the campaign funds he favors. Nor should our political leadership support activities that try to restore it to that state.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We encourage you to rise above the narrow political program of those who came to SF years ago and now are primarily interested in preserving the advantages they gained by being early arrivals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In the US, which has free immigration among the States, it is the responsible thing for cities and States to which people migrate to make reasonable efforts to permit enough housing to be built to accommodate everyone... immigrants as well as seniors and lower-income current residents.  Such building, of course, must comply with local zoning and affordability requirements, as, we think,  does the proposed Forest Hill development.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Thank you for rejecting the NIMBY arguments and for your support of a sensible project for a forward-looking San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Concerned Citizens]&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/review-arrival-is-here-but-can-it-please-leave-now/">
    <title type="text">Review: &quot;Arrival&quot; Is Here But Can It Please Leave Now?</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a0aad841-fc84-3b3a-a377-0feb9f5554cf</id>
    <updated>2016-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/review-arrival-is-here-but-can-it-please-leave-now/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For this year’s holiday sendoff, &lt;em&gt;BAMO&lt;/em&gt; reviews &lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt;, Denis Vellevue’s latest dreamy sci-fi flick starring Amy Adams and Jeremy Renner’s biceps.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Arrival” is an interesting word choice for this film title. It is mysterious, vague, and relatively neutral in tone – we don’t have any indication if what happens after the “arrival” will be good or bad. At some level, there is a looming, ominous feeling, just from the sheer scale of the vessels shown in the movie posters and trailer, but little to suggest that sweeping destruction of mankind is imminent.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What we do know, from the trailer at least, is that an extraterrestrial presence has arrived on Earth, in the form of gargantuan metalloid shells floating above the planet’s surface. We know Amy Adams is the protagonist linguistics professor tasked with communicating with the visitors; we know Jeremy Renner will be somehow involved, and it appears Forest Whitaker will take on the role of the irrationally inflexible government/army supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On the last one: I won’t harp on this too much, but if you’ve heard any reviews of &lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt; you have probably heard about the atrocious accent Whitaker adopts for the character – sort of a choppy New Englander/townie inflection, but with 10% commitment and 90% disorientation. Forget interpreting the aliens, can someone please tell me &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tFMo3UJ4B4g#t=00m15s&quot;&gt;what the hell Forrest Whitaker is doing here&lt;/a&gt;? Ok, we can move on.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ineffective accents are a minor failure, but the overall direction and thematic messaging represent the bigger miss. That was especially disappointing because of the promising cast, and the undeniable talent of director Denis Villeneuve. Villeneuve’s &lt;em&gt;Sicario&lt;/em&gt; was one of my favorite movies of last year, a film that confronts its audience with both the expected – humanity at its worst, entangled in drug cartels, violence, greed, power – and the less obvious –  a revolving point of view that casts doubt on our collective, often simplistic judgments about morality. There’s a lot to unpack, and closure remains elusive.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt; offers none of this mystery, ambiguity, or moral digging – it simply slaps a humanist message on a sci-fi-lite plot and calls it a day. We get a very clear point of view; we get closure; we get Jeremy Renner’s biceps. This whole sappy package is force fed to the audience through twinkling, gentle vignettes that leave nothing thematic to the imagination, and a painfully overt motif about “what really matters in life.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/review-arrival-is-here-but-can-it-please-leave-now/amy-adams-arrival.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amy Adams is also tired of this film by this point, but look how pretty the lighting is. Oh, and look who is in the foreground and look what is in the background. Hmm, what might the real focus of this film be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I can’t believe I’m saying this, but M. Night Shyamalan’s 2002 &lt;em&gt;Signs&lt;/em&gt; actually did a far superior job at weaving the human story into the UFO plot. &lt;em&gt;Signs&lt;/em&gt; drops clues throughout the film, and while it is understood how important family is to Mel Gibson’s protagonist in the midst of an alien invasion, there is still a real element of uncertainty regarding the convergence of the two until the very end. The point is, there is a way to intertwine human themes in a science fiction story without rubbing the audience’s face in it like a misbehaved puppy.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Alas, most reviewers are falling over themselves about &lt;em&gt;Arrival.&lt;/em&gt; The main crux of the plot, an academic using linguistics to approach extraterrestrial beings, has delighted critics, in contrast to the more destructive and explosive greeting we generally expect from Hollywood. The government employs Adams to decrypt the language of the alien “heptapods,” creatures which sort of resemble giant elephant squid knuckles, an assignment she performs thoughtfully, gradually, and peacefully. Meanwhile, the army seems to hover on razor’s edge, blistering for a change in tone and more aggressive strategy. So, yes, this was a nice contrast, and a novel offering to an “OMG ALIENS NOW WHAT” plot.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The real essence of the story, while I do not want to give too much away of it, is the artful and complex treatment of time and language revealed through Adams interactions with the heptapods. In case you’ve never read Kurt Vonnegut, time can be non-linear, except that humans perceive time linearly, which means that if you want to imagine a twist to &lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt; you now have all the tools you need.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In fairness, this film is an adaptation of a short story, so my criticisms of the narrative itself can’t be entirely targeted at the direction or cast portrayal. That aside, the direction could have been more subtle, and ultimately rewarding, had the message of the story not been so incessantly pushed at the viewer.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The pros: the film is beautifully shot, and the communicative journey undertaken by Adams and Renner is both creative and realistic. The score is powerful, intense, and thunderous, although like many epic sci-fi films seems to have borrowed heavily from the &lt;em&gt;Inception&lt;/em&gt; theme (BA-WAHHHHH tones. Like that.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Editor's note: Jóhann Jóhannsson is not our preferred film composer, though it is notable that, unlike many contemporaries, his score is bequeathed with approval from the world of Classical Music with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Arrival-Johann-Johannsson/dp/B01LZ4WK2S&quot;&gt;vinyl release&lt;/a&gt; by the&lt;/em&gt; Deutsche Grammophon &lt;em&gt;imprint.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Other, more trivial cons: Jeremy Renner was an odd casting choice. There was no chemistry between him and Adams, and his plucky optimism seemed starkly out of place in a predominantly grey, gloomy piece. Also, pacing. Time is a crucial element of this film, so perhaps this was a very meta-choice, but the film seriously and unnecessarily drags in tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Finally, the hokey conclusion manages to bundle both an unexpected reveal and the most predictable trope storytelling knows.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt; disappoints if you are looking for a planet-smashing sci-fi film, and equally disappoints if you are looking for artistic depth. We award this film a two-story rating.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/review-arrival-is-here-but-can-it-please-leave-now/story.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/trauss-sfbarf-v-city-of-lafayette-petitioners-brief/">
    <title type="text">Trauss, SFBARF v. City of Lafayette: Petitioners' Brief</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:9c3931b5-9102-3519-8d90-4cbcd8659065</id>
    <updated>2016-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/trauss-sfbarf-v-city-of-lafayette-petitioners-brief/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last year, our webmaster Sonja Trauss filed a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carlaef.org/s/FINAL-Second-Amended-Petition-with-exhibits.pdf&quot;&gt;lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; against the City of Lafayette, a wealthy East Bay suburb, for violating state housing law. The suit concerns Homes at Deer Hill, a development of 44 single-family homes estimated to sell for $1.2 million. The developer, O'Brien Homes, had previously proposed a 315-unit apartment complex at the same site, but was met with stiff local opposition. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.modernluxury.com/san-francisco/story/city-housing-activists-test-out-brazen-new-battle-cry-sue-the-suburbs&quot;&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;em&gt;San Francisco Magazine&lt;/em&gt; provides ample background, and the recently filed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carlaef.org/s/Petitioners-Memorandum-of-Points-and-Authorities-in-Support-of-Petition-for-Writ-of-Administrative-M.pdf&quot;&gt;petitioners' brief&lt;/a&gt; is below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;embed src=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/55dbb5e9e4b0703ec759c956/t/583b992cb8a79b774fbdee71/1480300858030/Petitioners%27+Memorandum+of+Points+and+Authorities+in+Support+of+Petition+for+Writ+of+Administrative+Manduamus.pdf&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; height=&quot;2100px&quot; /&gt;
    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/state-and-local-officials-double-down-on-immigrant-protections/">
    <title type="text">State and Local Officials Double Down on Immigrant Protections</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:53e9de37-5fb4-3860-bb32-dbfc538a58d0</id>
    <updated>2016-11-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/state-and-local-officials-double-down-on-immigrant-protections/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In the wake of a perceived federal mandate for legislated xenophobia after the 2016 Election, politicians both in San Francisco and the state of California have begun further publicizing their support for undocumented migrants.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco’s Public Defender Jeff Adachi has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/sf-may-create-legal-team-fight-upcoming-trump-deportations/&quot;&gt;proposed&lt;/a&gt; a “universal representation” program to defend the rights of an estimated 30,000 undocumented immigrants living in the city. Adachi plants to request 30 or 40 attorneys on retainer to represent noncitizens facing deportation, a program modeled after a New York City program implemented in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The City Attorney’s Office has also stated that San Francisco stands by its legal obligation to protect the private information of undocumented residents holding &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/sf-promises-keep-city-ids-undocumented-immigrants-private/?utm_campaign=magnet&amp;amp;utm_source=article_page&amp;amp;utm_medium=recommended_articles&quot;&gt;City ID cards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On the statewide front, Lt. Governor Gavin Newsom has penned an open letter to Chancellors of the University of California, California State University, and California Community College systems urging them to affirm the status of their universities as sanctuary campuses. Newsom advocated for these institutions to protect the information of their students from the federal government, particularly of students with an undocumented immigration status.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last week, the former Mayor of San Francisco gave a rousing press conference on the steps of city hall. Though nominally a celebration of Propositions 63 and 64 passing, Newsom turned to the post-election fears expressed in subsequent protests throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“If we can practice the politics of inclusion,” Newsom said, “if we can try to build bridges and bring people together...we have unlimited potential.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&quot;I think what makes California great…we don’t tolerate our diversity, we celebrate our diversity,” Newsom added. &quot;We believe that inclusive societies are adaptable societies. We believe that adaptability and flexibility are what will allow us not just to survive the 21st century, but to thrive.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At a press conference yesterday in the UCSF Mission Bay Campus, Newsom noted that the country has far fewer than 3 million undocumented immigrants reside in the country, and that the President-elect would likely have to deport non-felons if his stated goals remain in place.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Newsom is widely regarded as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/Gavin-Newsom-leading-candidate-in-18-10614220.php?t=e6e830851a&amp;amp;cmpid=email-premium&quot;&gt;top contender&lt;/a&gt; for Governor in the 2018 race.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/caltrain-begins-construction-to-prepare-for-electrified-rail/">
    <title type="text">Caltrain Begins Construction to Prepare for Electrified Rail</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:17d019ab-d9e3-3026-88a5-8fa257d88d08</id>
    <updated>2016-11-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/caltrain-begins-construction-to-prepare-for-electrified-rail/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After enduring years of litigation, the diesel train system connecting San Francisco to the Peninsula and South Bay cities of San Jose and Gilroy will soon be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/caltrain-begins-3-month-construction-project-anticipation-system-electrification/&quot;&gt;upgraded&lt;/a&gt; to an electric rail system, in preparation for integrating with a future High Speed Rail. As part of the Caltrain Modernization Program (CalMod), the agency will begin work this week on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.caltrain.com/projectsplans/CaltrainModernization/Modernization/PeninsulaCorridorElectrificationProject.html&quot;&gt;Peninsula Corridor Electrification Project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Over the next three months, Caltrain will be upgrading utilities and testing soil along Peninsula stations, with an occasional need for single-tracking trains resulting in reduced service. By mid-2017, the agency expects to begin construction. The Peninsula Corridor portion of CalMod is expected to be completed by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/caltrain-begins-construction-to-prepare-for-electrified-rail/calmod.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(courtesy: Caltrain)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Among numerous improvements cited, Caltrain expects a 97% reduction in carbon emissions, less noise, and an approximately threefold increase in train service.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/bitter-sf-supes-send-landmark-mission-project-back-to-drawing-board/">
    <title type="text">Bitter SF Supes Send Landmark Mission Project Back to Drawing Board</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:6f068684-3927-3f39-9b14-cc71914a1abc</id>
    <updated>2016-11-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/bitter-sf-supes-send-landmark-mission-project-back-to-drawing-board/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At a bitter and raucous meeting in San Francisco’s City Hall, the Board of Supervisors voted to uphold an appeal and require developers of a project at 1515 South Van Ness Avenue with 157 residential units to go back to the drawing board. By a unanimous 9-0 vote, the Supervisors urged Lennar Multifamily to await further review of economic impacts under the framework of the California Environmental Quality Act (CEQA). (Supervisors Yee and Wiener were absent.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The project will now be remanded to the city’s Planning Department, with instructions to report on the potential impacts of gentrification its market-rate units would bring to the area.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Watch full highlights from the Board meeting below:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/flFLGpnQ-AM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Some supporters of the project objected that the Mission District advocacy group Calle 24 based their appeal on CEQA grounds after failing to obtain enough signatures to appeal the Conditional Use Permit (CUP) itself, which was granted by a unanimous vote of the city’s Planning Commission. Supervisor David Campos echoed these concerns, saying “I don’t think they [the appellants] did a good enough job in many respects,” when explaining his vote to uphold the appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Previously, &lt;em&gt;Mission Local&lt;/em&gt; had &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/08/mission-district-housing-project-reaches-25-percent-affordable/&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that the project at 1515 South Van Ness had reserved 25% of dwelling units for middle- and low-income households, despite being approved before citywide requirements were raised to 25%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Even by San Francisco standards, the special meeting was particularly rife with partisan vitriol. One opponent of the project roared against the Board, accusing Supervisors Farrell and Tang of donning “klan robes.” The man proceeded to call the entire Board “nasty, vile humans” and “whores” before Board President London Breed calmly dismissed him from the dais.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Both sides framed the debate in terms of the need to preserve San Francisco’s sanctuary city status in light of an impending anti-immigrant Presidency, but disagreed on whether the project as currently proposed was conducive or deleterious to those ends.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/bitter-sf-supes-send-landmark-mission-project-back-to-drawing-board/berniepuppet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;An opponent of 1515 South Van Ness speaks through his Bernie Sanders puppet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Local landlord Spike Kahn, who owns multiple rental properties and also rents short-term on Airbnb, decried an impending loss of “a more diverse community” that had initially motivated her to buy a home in the Mission District three decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Another woman speaking in favor of the appeal, a native of the Mission, expressed frustration that some supporters of Lennar’s development had opposed an apartment complex for low-income seniors at 1296 Shotwell Street because it could obstruct views for residents in the wealthier Bernal Heights neighborhood (coincidentally, where Supervisor Campos owns an eight-bedroom home). Though she followed Marie Sorenson of Calle 24, who also opposed the project, Sorenson had &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/05/neighbors-of-mission-district-affordable-housing-cry-too-tall/&quot;&gt;previously stated&lt;/a&gt; her opposition to the senior housing complex, fearing that its height would set a bad precedent for the Mission.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite this rhetoric, Supervisor David Campos attributed his vote to uphold the appeal—a vote which the rest of the Board dutifully supported—on an inflammatory speech decrying perceived nativism. “Someone said this building would be a stranger in the neighborhood, as though it were self-evident that it’s bad…and that disturbed me a lot,” said Sonja Trauss, co-founder of the San Francisco YIMBY Party and webmaster of this publication. Trauss also noted that the City Controller found in a study last year that 84% of residents in new buildings were already residents of San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Campos claimed that Trauss’s speech, along with public comment from Patrick McMillan, CEO of McMillan Electric, about “gangs” and “drug-dealers” that Trauss later described as “unacceptably classist,” for changing his mind.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lennar Multifamily Communities has paid McMillan Electric, the previous occupants at 1515 South Van Ness, to move to a new location on Cesar Chavez Street. McMillan testified before the board that the payoff enabled him to hire 25 new employees.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While many white commenters bemoaned the loss of the neighborhood’s Latino population, others noted that a separate subsidiary of Lennar was involved in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/toxic-soil-scandal-halts-hunters-point-development/&quot;&gt;scandal-ridden development&lt;/a&gt; in the Hunters Point Shipyard, where the Navy’s contractor Tetra Tech was found to have falsified their soil samples intending to decontamination of the radioactive land. (Some commenters erroneously described TetraTech as a contractor hired by Lennar.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Campos, a graduate of Harvard Law School, explained to the other supervisors that he was fully aware his comments could open the city up to litigation. To that admission, he simply added, “Bring it on.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/activists-and-developers-negotiate-in-oakland-chinatown/">
    <title type="text">Activists and Developers Negotiate in Oakland Chinatown</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:7f396066-d5b8-3bea-8b35-1143728a6979</id>
    <updated>2016-11-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/activists-and-developers-negotiate-in-oakland-chinatown/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Oakland’s City Council reviewed an appeal during a special meeting last night contesting the approval of 226 13th Street, a six-story mixed-use project with 262 residential units proposed by local developer Wood Partners. Though no legal basis was cited, a coalition of Chinatown neighborhood groups organized to oppose the project in order to “extract concessions” from the developer in the form of a “community benefits package.” Organized opposition was spearheaded by Lailan Huen, daughter of former Oakland Mayor Jean Quan.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Among a litany of community benefits acquired, Councilmember Abel Guillen cites retail space reserved for small businesses in Oakland's new Black Arts Movement Business District; $100,000 for local construction job training; a 20% local hire goal; a $250,000 contribution to anti-displacement programs; and a 1% “art fee” for the nearby Malonga Center. In total, Wood Partners will grant $1.8 million in community benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/activists-and-developers-negotiate-in-oakland-chinatown/quan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Mayor Jean Quan speaks at City Hall, with her daughter Lailan waiting in line behind her&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;With reference to current debates over immigration policy, Pamela Drake of the Wellstone Democratic Club said, “we also need to be a sanctuary for people who are already here…it’s incumbent upon regular residents to spend hours, days, and months making sure that we actually recognize the needs of our residents.” She urged city staff to find representatives with local experience to incorporate community concerns into the planning process, “not at the other end” after permits are issued.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/abelguillencinco/posts/1878592962372112&quot;&gt;Facebook post&lt;/a&gt;, Guillen elaborated: “Although this project predates the adoption of impact fees in Oakland, the developer will make a $675,000 contribution that will help close the gap necessary to build 60 units of affordable housing in the neighborhood.” The Councilmember added that replacing a surface parking lot with housing was essential for mitigating the housing shortage and curbing car dependence, but that he also intended to promote plans for creating a “historic overlay” to protect Chinatown as a cultural asset.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“This sets a precedent that is really critical…We don’t want to have to fight every development,” Huen said during the public comment period. “We need the city to have more comprehensive development policies.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Oakland’s new &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/Oakland-to-impose-impact-fees-on-new-housing-7280444.php&quot;&gt;impact fee requirements&lt;/a&gt; for market-rate development came into effect on September 1st, before Wood Partners completed the permitting process for the project. Observers have speculated whether or not such policies will indeed satisfy community activists who would otherwise insist on politically bartering with every development that gets proposed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/study-on-tech-shuttles-confirms-more-is-safer-and-greener/">
    <title type="text">Study on “Tech Shuttles” Confirms, More Is Safer (and Greener)</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:ea62d7ae-59e4-3577-8599-331662e7933f</id>
    <updated>2016-11-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/study-on-tech-shuttles-confirms-more-is-safer-and-greener/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Whenever a public agency evaluates the efficacy of a private enterprise, tensions inevitably arise. This dynamic remains true today now that San Francisco’s Municipal Transportation Agency (SFMTA) has released its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfmta.com/sites/default/files/agendaitems/2016/11-15-16%20Item%2011%20Commuter%20Shuttle%20Program%20Mid%20Term%20Status%20Report.PDF&quot;&gt;study on commuter shuttles&lt;/a&gt;, and in a separate report, found major faults with recent proposals to consolidate shuttle stops into a handful of “hubs.” Supporters of widespread commuter shuttle programs were not surprised by the results.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;SFMTA &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfmta.com/sites/default/files/projects/2016/Commuter_Shuttle_Hub_Report_Final.pdf&quot;&gt;evaluated&lt;/a&gt; four potential scenarios for redistributing commuter shuttles throughout the city, finding that each option would result in more commutes taken via personal vehicles. Despite decreasing the number of loading zones in the city by almost half, SFMTA’s initial status report found that their Commuter Shuttle pilot program had nevertheless reduced anticipated carbon emissions and increased ridership by 1,000 daily commuters.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For some political stakeholders, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/city-makes-last-call-tech-shuttle-transit-hubs/&quot;&gt;that isn’t enough&lt;/a&gt;. Though hubs remain a popular option, SFMTA withholds any optimism from such proposals. In their concluding remarks, SFMTA states, “nearly all, or approximately 90%, of those riders who shift modes are expected to switch to driving. This forecast holds true under all scenarios.” The first option studied, a “Single Hub” plan with bus stops clustered around the developing Transbay Terminal, would result in an estimated eightfold increase of Vehicle Miles Traveled (VMT). The remaining three options were all estimated to encourage a fivefold VMT increase. All scenarios would also be expected to increase traffic collisions.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/study-on-tech-shuttles-confirms-more-is-safer-and-greener/shuttlehub2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;source: SFMTA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In other words, workers commuting from San Francisco to jobs on the Peninsula are generally expected to commute via automobile and contribute to increased traffic congestion if deprived of their current shuttle options. Only 10% of those surveyed said they would opt to take some form of public transit, such as Caltrain.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/study-on-tech-shuttles-confirms-more-is-safer-and-greener/shuttlehub1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;source: SFMTA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Other scenarios still involved a significant decrease in the number of permitted shuttle stops: a BART-Oriented Scenario would have five bus hubs located around highly frequented BART stations in the city, namely Embarcadero, Civic Center, 16th &amp;amp; Mission, 24th &amp;amp; Mission, and Balboa Park. A Freeway-Adjacent Scenario would have nine hubs within a quarter-mile of freeway on-ramps, with all but two clustered around the eastern portion of the city. Finally, a Consolidated Network Scenario would preserve the current clustering of shuttle zones while aiming to reduce the total amount by at least half.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Erin McElroy, founder of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.antievictionmap.com/&quot;&gt;Anti-Eviction Mapping Project&lt;/a&gt;, expressed adamant opposition to the shuttle program. She claims her organization’s data shows a strong correlation between shuttle stops, evictions, and rent increases. “It seems as if the city is subsidizing the lives of people who ride the luxury commuter shuttles at the expense of those who don’t,” she stated &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Cutting-tech-shuttle-stops-will-add-cars-in-SF-10610440.php?t=66bdcd6df6&amp;amp;cmpid=twitter-premium&quot;&gt;in an interview&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;em&gt;Chronicle&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Currently, there are 16 commuter shuttle services operating with permits from SFMTA. SFMTA’s current Commuter Shuttle Program has 110 shuttle stops in operation, with the total allowable number capped at 125 (down from over 200 before the program was implemented). Companies operating these shuttles are required to pay a “stop event” fee of $7.31 for every individual stop in a shuttle zone.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;McElroy moved to San Francisco to attend the Center for Integral Studies after receiving a BA in Cultural Studies from Hampshire College and a BA in Studio Art from NYU. In a phone interview, she criticized SFMTA’s analysis for omitting data regarding displacement. “When these stops raise property values,” she argues, the poorer residents displaced by rising rents “are moving to the suburbs, and they’re often driving back into the city for school or work. So you’re still going to see more car use.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When asked what sort of analysis she would prefer to see, McElroy noted that “anyone in Urban Planning 101 can tell you, housing and transportation are very much connected. It’s unethical, I think, for the city to leave housing out of the equation.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As for Caltrain—for many, the only available transit mode connecting the city to the Peninsula—the diesel-powered train that runs once an hour is slated to upgrade its rails to an electrified system after &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/caltrain-electrification-to-proceed-after-atherton-lawsuit-fails/&quot;&gt;prevailing in a lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; that sought to stall High-Speed Rail development.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Adrian Covert, Vice President of Policy at the Bay Area Council, remains hopeful that the report will lead to improved transportation policy in San Francisco.  In his view, a calculated dispersal of shuttle stops throughout the city is critical for improving traffic safety, particularly to avoid bus travel on non-arterial or primarily residential streets. “The numbers speak for themselves,” he said in a phone interview.  “Any time you increase VMT, you minimize the benefits and maximize the impact on neighborhoods.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/analyzing-the-palo-alto-city-council-election/">
    <title type="text">Analyzing the Palo Alto City Council Election</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:4b1ce693-76d6-386c-a434-4aa3cbfd5165</id>
    <updated>2016-11-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/analyzing-the-palo-alto-city-council-election/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After facing a deluge of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/30/us/spotty-cell-reception-in-the-heart-of-silicon-valley.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;national media scrutiny&lt;/a&gt; for its resistance to residential growth, Palo Alto may have begun a new chapter in its history. After so-called “Residentialist” City Council candidates Arthur Keller and Lydia Kou raised upwards of $100,000 to run &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-council-race-gets-greener-but-not-from-grassroots/&quot;&gt;attack ads&lt;/a&gt; on candidates Adrian Fine and Liz Kniss, those in favor of keeping Palo Alto small and quaint now find themselves outnumbered in the city’s legislative body.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Hyperlocal pundits believe that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paloaltoonline.com/news/2016/11/08/kniss-tanaka-kou-and-fine-take-lead-in-council-race&quot;&gt;election&lt;/a&gt; of Adrian Fine, Greg Tanaka, and Liz Kniss—as well as Lydia Kou—now puts the “Not In My Back Yard” cohort of the City Council at a 5-4 minority.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Fine, however, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-candidates-talk-quality-of-life-and-regional-growth-in-forum/&quot;&gt;has remained steadfast&lt;/a&gt; in his refusal to play into any partisan or divisive narrative. “I'm honored and humbled to be elected,” he said in a brief interview. “I think that my message of inclusiveness and our ground game won the day. From day one, I focused on housing and transportation choices, and it really resonated.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Resonated” is one way to put it. In more practical terms, Fine’s success can largely be attributed to effective organizing and voter outreach.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The following map of voting precincts in Palo Alto illustrates the small city’s overall support for pro-housing candidates. The only precincts with a majority of votes going to the “slow-growth” coalition are in Arthur Keller’s neighborhood of Ramos Park, and Lydia Kou’s neighborhood of Barron Park. Curiously, Kou’s home precinct favored the pro-growth slate by 2%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/d/embed?mid=1mlfHeeZHKLcSkhRe7l53Ofqxmxw&amp;hl=en&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;These results could serve as a valuable cautionary tale for would-be public officials: no matter your funding, it always pays to court the vote beyond your own back yard.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-what-this-election-really-means/">
    <title type="text">Op-Ed: What This Election Really Means</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:47736e59-d423-3131-a8d0-20c10f7f3e53</id>
    <updated>2016-11-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-what-this-election-really-means/" />
    <author>
      <name>Mike Ege</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In 2017, Donald Trump will be our next president. That means that anything is possible politically, for better or worse.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Trump won in part due to the increasing numbers of people who feel marginalized, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/global-opinions/wp/2016/11/10/im-a-muslim-a-woman-and-an-immigrant-i-voted-for-trump/?wpisrc=nl_most-draw7&amp;amp;wpmm=1&quot;&gt;regardless of background&lt;/a&gt;. The national election was more than anything about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thenation.com/article/inequality-gave-rise-to-donald-trumps-presidency/&quot;&gt;inequality&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://inthesetimes.com/article/19618/listen-leftist-thomas-frank-donald-trump-hillary-clinton-bernie-sanders&quot;&gt;failure of political Progressives&lt;/a&gt; to respond to the marginalized in a meaningful way.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Whether you rent or own, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2014-07-17/housings-30-percent-of-income-rule-is-near-useless&quot;&gt;paying for housing&lt;/a&gt; makes up the biggest chunk of working families’ budgets, and the rising cost of housing, along with stagnant wages, has been a primary engine of inequality in the United States. The result is that a whole range of working people, from food service workers to middle managers, now live in a state of &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedisorderofthings.com/2013/10/12/struggling-with-precarity-from-more-and-better-jobs-to-less-and-lesser-work/&quot;&gt;economic precarity&lt;/a&gt;. This includes many sectors that political Progressives simply &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lrb.co.uk/v16/n07/edward-luttwak/why-fascism-is-the-wave-of-the-future&quot;&gt;don’t care about&lt;/a&gt;, because of the perception that they don’t vote for them.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Housing also figures into the rise of Donald Trump as a public figure. Trump first made a name for himself by taking advantage of New York City’s bankruptcy in 1975 to access redevelopment financing, using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2016/07/trump-files-how-donald-tricked-new-york-huge-deal&quot;&gt;the Grand Hyatt hotel project&lt;/a&gt; to elevate his business away from a portfolio of middle-class rental housing to one of luxury properties. In doing so, he contributed to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/high-income-renters-2016-11&quot;&gt;rising inequality in our cities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;If we are to take Trump’s platform at face value, housing will continue to be an issue. While much of his rhetoric was likely &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/many-of-trumps-sweeping-promises-will-be-hard-if-not-impossible-to-fulfill/2016/11/09/b07867be-a6a9-11e6-ba59-a7d93165c6d4_story.html?wpisrc=nl_most-draw7&amp;amp;wpmm=1&quot;&gt;meant to be an analogy&lt;/a&gt; for an agenda which is at the same time more realistic and unfortunately only slightly less repugnant, that agenda will still exacerbate inequality in America, and housing will play a major role. The downsizing of government payrolls, increases in &lt;a href=&quot;https://newrepublic.com/article/138674/beware-donald-trumps-infrastructure-plan&quot;&gt;infrastructure spending&lt;/a&gt;, and the expansion of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rawstory.com/2016/11/donald-trump-will-be-the-fossil-fuel-industrys-greatest-gift/&quot;&gt;extractive industries&lt;/a&gt; will create another wave of worker migration, putting &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2015-09-29/man-camp-exodus-spurs-real-estate-crisis-across-u-s-shale-towns&quot;&gt;further stress&lt;/a&gt; on regional housing supplies.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Now more than ever, there is a real need to pivot the policy narrative on housing toward its consideration as human infrastructure, and not as an investment commodity. Here in the Bay Area, while the rhetoric will be different, the political obstacles will be the same.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Our region’s “Progressive” and “Neighborhood” movements may pay lip service to a social narrative which is very different from the Trump agenda, but in reality their agenda is equally reactionary.  The primary goals of these local anti-housing movements are to preserve existing wealth and power. This includes the continued assertion of intangible rights (such as to views) in association with property ownership, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2015/12/san-francisco-is-confused-about-the-villain-thats-making-it-unaffordable/422091/&quot;&gt;unequal tax benefits&lt;/a&gt; granted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thenation.com/article/have-california-voters-finally-had-enough-of-prop-13/&quot;&gt;Proposition 13&lt;/a&gt;, and opposition to &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.streetsblog.org/2016/06/14/mission-transit-lane-removal-nudged-closer-to-reality/&quot;&gt;better transit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2016-08-02/san-francisco-progressives-declare-war-on-affordable-housing&quot;&gt;denser housing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the sad news on the national front, the YIMBY movement has scored significant political victories in the Bay Area. San Francisco’s pro-urbanist Supervisor &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nbcbayarea.com/news/local/Scott-Wiener-Captures-State-Senate-Seat-400551351.html&quot;&gt;Scott Wiener&lt;/a&gt; was elected to the State Senate and will continue the fight for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mercurynews.com/2016/09/21/commentary-jerry-browns-by-right-housing-plan-needs-another-try/&quot;&gt;By-Right Development&lt;/a&gt; in Sacramento. A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/news/2016/11/09/sf-board-of-supervisors-housing-policy.html&quot;&gt;pro-housing majority&lt;/a&gt; will likely be restored to the San Francisco Board of Supervisors, and ballot initiatives which would’ve been most harmful to the continued development of affordable housing were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hoodline.com/2016/11/san-francisco-ballot-results-2016-proposition-q-u-v-homeless-soda-tax&quot;&gt;defeated&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, more pro-housing members were elected to the&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mercurynews.com/2016/11/03/palo-alto-city-council-race/&quot;&gt; Palo Alto City Council&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Some may attempt to portray these victories as part of a “Trump Wave.” It will be incumbent upon us to point out who the real Trumpists are.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/bay-area-protests-surge-in-response-to-national-election/">
    <title type="text">Bay Area Protests Surge in Response to National Election</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:457eab73-210c-358e-8237-6ca378922a2d</id>
    <updated>2016-11-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/bay-area-protests-surge-in-response-to-national-election/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Thousands of students in San Francisco walked out of class today to protest the election of an openly white supremacist and misogynist President. These protests follow in the wake of thousands marching along Market Street last night, from the Ferry Building to the Castro, and more confrontational protests &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/videos-photos-massive-crowd-of-anti-donald-trump-protesters-take-over-downtown-oakland/Content?oid=5030347&quot;&gt;in downtown Oakland&lt;/a&gt;. Oakland students also walked out en masse today, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/videos-photos-massive-crowd-of-anti-donald-trump-protesters-take-over-downtown-oakland/Content?oid=5030347&quot;&gt;Berkeley High School&lt;/a&gt; students staged a protest on the UC Berkeley campus yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;State Senator Mark Leno attended today’s demonstration in front of San Francisco City Hall, telling the &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; that he saw historical parallels between this year’s election and the early 1970s. “[This election] makes me remember how Richard Nixon was re-elected with one of the biggest landslides in American history, yet his term was cut short by one of the worst scandals in our history,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mayor Ed Lee's office has announced that they will make contingency plans to prepare for a complete loss of federal funding in order to preserve San Francisco's &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/SF-preparing-in-case-Trump-cuts-federal-funds-10607210.php?t=faa8df36a2&amp;amp;cmpid=twitter-premium&quot;&gt;sanctuary city status&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In deference to the strength and courage of these demonstrators, we present photographs from staff photographer Mike Ege without comment, and encourage our readers to follow coverage by other local journalists such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/11/mission-high-students-join-hundreds-in-anti-trump-protest/&quot;&gt;Joe Rivano Barros&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Mission Local&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/bay-area-protests-surge-in-response-to-national-election/conscientious.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/bay-area-protests-surge-in-response-to-national-election/dumbeldore.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/former-la-mayor-villaraigosa-announces-run-for-governor/">
    <title type="text">Former LA Mayor Villaraigosa Announces Run for Governor</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:6bff0c8b-1b30-38c0-aa45-dea8fa2807d4</id>
    <updated>2016-11-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/former-la-mayor-villaraigosa-announces-run-for-governor/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Former Mayor of Los Angeles Antonio Villaraigosa announced today that he would be running for Governor of California in 2018. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://antonioforcalifornia.com/&quot;&gt;candidate&lt;/a&gt; will be facing steep opposition in a crowded race that will include current Lt. Governor Gavin Newsom, State Treasurer John Chiang, and former schools superintendent Delaine Eastin.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Raised by a single mother in Boyle Heights, Villaraigosa served for two terms as the first Latino mayor of Los Angeles from 2005 to 2013. During his mayoralty, Los Angeles weathered a revenue shortfall resulting from the 2008 recession. After raising wages for public employees before the recession, Villaraigosa successfully &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.latimes.com/local/california/la-me-villaraigosa-legacy-20130629-dto-story.html&quot;&gt;negotiated&lt;/a&gt; pay cuts with public unions when tightening the city’s budget.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Before the recession, Villaraigosa’s proposals to address the city’s housing affordability crisis involved lobbying state and federal governments to support first-time home purchasing programs. When foreclosures began to soar, the mayor pivoted to focus on tenant protections, supportive housing for the growing homeless population, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rooflines.org/1181/keeping_hope_and_housing_alive_in_la/&quot;&gt;inclusionary zoning requirements&lt;/a&gt; from market-rate development.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;His administration weathered numerous scandals, including an infidelity charge, and Villaraigosa encountered numerous roadblocks to his housing platform. First, a 2010 court ruling known as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.laobserved.com/boyarsky/2010/02/a_city_hall_backstabbing.php&quot;&gt;Palmer decision&lt;/a&gt; invalidated his plan to require a minimum amount of price-indexed units for lower incomes from private developers. The following year, outrage erupted when the city’s former Housing Authority director Rudolf Montiel received a $1.2 million severance package to settle his wrongful termination claim, and the Mayor’s office initially &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailybreeze.com/20111210/editorial-mayor-antonio-villaraigosa-looks-bad-over-housing-authority-head-scandal&quot;&gt;claimed&lt;/a&gt; Villaraigosa was unaware of the payoff.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Antonio Villaraigosa initially considered the gubernatorial race in 2010, before former and current Governor Jerry Brown obtained the Democratic nomination. His nascent campaign is at a monetary disadvantage compared to that of top contender Gavin Newsom, who has been fundraising since announcing his candidacy in February of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The answer to fear is hope,” Villaraigosa said in a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.latimes.com/politics/la-pol-ca-governor-villaraigosa-20161110-story.html&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with the Los Angeles &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt;. “I’ll be as fair as the day is long.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/letter-from-the-editor-who-is-we/">
    <title type="text">Letter from the Editor: Who Is &quot;We&quot;?</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:966a6470-b922-3961-8cd9-5e99b48bc8b7</id>
    <updated>2016-11-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/letter-from-the-editor-who-is-we/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This is a failed experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;White people are the quintessential carpetbaggers. Insofar as “white” has coalesced as an abstraction to include once-disparate cultural groups united by colorist prejudices, today it seems merely a distinction of who emigrated to the Americas with some degree of autonomy (Bering Strait notwithstanding, of course). Abstractions may not be tangible, but they can kill.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We—and my hand trembles as I type “we,” since my status among you has always been ambiguous—we fled Europe for a better life here, bringing smallpox, swine, and iron-fisted ideals. Sometimes we fled war, only to settle on land other Europeans had conquered long ago. My great-grandfather fled Spain during the Civil War, opting to grow crops on barren soil in Puerto Rico centuries after the last Taino stood there.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When he was almost exactly my age, my father fled his hometown of Mexico City after surviving the 1968 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tlatelolco_massacre&quot;&gt;Tlatelolco Massacre&lt;/a&gt;. As we spoke on the phone this morning, both on the verge of tears, he told me he feels quite old, and frankly, he doesn’t know if he’ll live to see the silver lining. “I understand if you want to run away,” he said. “I know the feeling.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Today I live in fear that my relatives will be murdered by a white supremacist militia, or that they will starve, or—anything. Which “we” does this put me in now?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Latinx community, as long as it has existed, is defined by feeling like refugees in any country with a spare bed for us. Hijos de la chingada: children of the rape. Bastards, anomalies. Last night, many of those with the privilege of a discrete identity reinforced the popular notion that we do not matter. Entire generations have lived and died wondering if they will ever matter.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Abstractions can kill, but only tangible action can save lives. In San Francisco, the campaign for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/Moratorium-on-new-Mission-District-housing-is-6609187.php&quot;&gt;Mission Moratorium&lt;/a&gt; wasn’t about distorting market forces. For many residents, it was simply a desperate attempt to stop Colonialism in its tracks. Desperate, yes, but not stupid. We (again, we?—not I) know how this goes. We know this chimeric, ancient evil will take on any form it needs to, particularly a benevolent one. Especially greatness, past or future.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Those of us with the privilege to dwell in abstractions—and clearly, I am one of them sometimes—scoffed at this paranoia. It seemed absurd, unrealistic, that shiny new condos would bring about some insidious cultural genocide.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;How many of us opposing Proposition I offered our free time to help undocumented migrants living in fear of deportation? Did we do our part to stand up to daily horrors with daily acts of solidarity? I fear not.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many also laughed when this all started. We told you this wasn’t funny: here I count myself among this “we.” We never found this funny. We knew, despite all the snickering at the primaries, the certainty that scandal after scandal would rescue this Republic, we knew we’d seen this before. We’ve seen it before because today’s nightmare is the nightmare the United States has inflicted on so many countries around the world, including in Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;So where do I belong? For a few years, I thought it was the Bay Area. I’ve dedicated my relatively young career to advocating for a more inclusive, open region, documenting the many harms wrought by localized immigration controls (hello, Palo Alto). Along the way, I occasionally confronted older residents who wondered why I had to come here at all. Why did I have to add to the growth this region struggles with so strenuously?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I’ll tell you. With federal and private grants, I was able to attend Stanford University at virtually no cost to my family. My parents, both professors on the east coast, could not afford to send me anywhere out of state (and hardly anywhere in our home state) without this financial aid.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;My education, and yes, much of the gratuitous privilege that bolsters my life, is premised on a country that values economic mobility. Do we really value this? Shall we accept that for many others, the grass &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; indeed greener on our side?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I have no idea what to do. To be perfectly honest, I plan on visiting family in Vancouver in the coming weeks, and maybe I’ll ask them if they know anyone with a job opening. The terrible choice such privilege presents us is whether or not to take advantage of it for survival, or squander it to remain in solidarity with those less fortunate.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night, I could hear neighbors around me screaming. I couldn’t sleep. Neither could you.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We must listen to our neighbors. We must listen closely, and be there for them—lest something louder comes to drown out their anguished cries.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover image: &quot;The Disembarkation of Christopher Colombus on the Island of Guanahani in 1492&quot; by Jose Garnelo y Alda&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/cartoon-not-for-sale/">
    <title type="text">Cartoon: &quot;Not For Sale&quot;</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:fa41cc91-7c25-3fc5-9a14-86cdb6bf8fe8</id>
    <updated>2016-11-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/cartoon-not-for-sale/" />
    <author>
      <name>Krusty Wheatfield</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Copyright &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.krustywheatfield.com/&quot;&gt;Krusty Wheatfield&lt;/a&gt; 2016 ©&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-questioning-priorities-in-the-affordable-housing-community/">
    <title type="text">Editorial: Questioning Priorities in the Affordable Housing Community</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a5e52183-da1f-314f-bdf5-9e448f876507</id>
    <updated>2016-11-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-questioning-priorities-in-the-affordable-housing-community/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We recently &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-why-is-ccho-afraid-of-the-city-controllers-prop-c-study/&quot;&gt;responded to an open letter&lt;/a&gt; from the Council of Community Housing Organizations (CCHO), an affordable housing organization, to the City Controller on its &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/09/prop-c-affordable-housing-study-for-sf.html&quot;&gt;study of Proposition C&lt;/a&gt; and its 25% inclusionary requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;One of  CCHO’s most surprising positions was that the very first goal of the city’s housing policy should be to “capture the windfall profits resulting from increased land values.” This means the actual creation of affordable housing comes somewhere after first in CCHO’s ranking of goals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this indicates that we can add “personal political agendas” to the list of priorities that rank above affordable housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As part of its case for the 25% middle- and low-income housing requirement, CCHO cited two real-world projects that demonstrate the feasibility of the policy, one of which is an affordable housing proposal by a private developer at 915-917 Cayuga, SST Investments. The project is an unusually generous one: 103 units with 51 of them set to be rent-controlled, and 52 rented at below market-rate rents at varying low and moderate income levels. The developer has been working with the Mayor’s Office to ensure tenant protections under the city’s rent control laws, which currently extend only to properties built before 1979.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At the same time, CCHO has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfccho.org/some-sf-ballot-measures-trump-would-love/&quot;&gt;stated support&lt;/a&gt; for Proposition M, a ballot measure to create a new commission to oversee housing and economic development, in addition to replacing two existing commissions. One of the major concerns about Prop M from opponents is that it would obstruct or delay the building of housing, including affordable housing when it is rolled into market-rate as part of the city’s inclusionary program.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Now it turns out 915-917 Cayuga, CCHO’s 25% inclusionary champion, might be on &lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/San_Francisco,_California,_Housing_and_Development_Commission_Establishment_Amendment,_Proposition_M_(November_2016&quot;&gt;Prop M&lt;/a&gt;)’s chopping block (if it passes), by way of the district’s own supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Joe Fitz Rodriguez of the &lt;em&gt;SF Examiner&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/related-entities/?eid=3083244971&amp;amp;ename=Aaron%20Peskin&amp;amp;lang=en&quot;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt;, “The newest barrier for the plan for 915-917 Cayuga Ave., the site of the affordable housing, may be Supervisor Aaron Peskin’s Proposition M, which is now on the ballot.” According to Fitz, insiders familiar with the deal believe the project will face scrutiny from Prop M due to possible ethics violations committed by Ahsha Safai, the District 11 Supervisor candidate who played a role in the deal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The complaint against Safaí, filed by Supervisor John Avalos, is that Safai failed to register as a lobbyist when pitching the affordable housing idea to his friend, project developer Siavash Tahbahzof. According to the complaint, Safai’s consulting firm, Kitchen Cabinet Public Affairs, has between $10,000 and $100,000 in business activity with SST Investments, a fact he should have disclosed to the city before negotiating the deal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Avalos &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Developer-wants-to-create-rent-controlled-housing-10152241.php&quot;&gt;was skeptical&lt;/a&gt; of the deal from the beginning, calling the near-election timing “dubious.” He accused Safai of using insider deal to get “maximum benefit” during election season. Avalos is supporting Safai’s opponent, Kimberly Alvarenga, and defeated Safai in his first run for D11 Supervisor in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To reiterate, CCHO supports the creation of Proposition M, a commission to oversee proposed housing developments, which in theory should line up with its push for more affordable housing. Now, one of only two affordable housing projects CCHO is holding up as an example of 25% inclusionary feasibility &lt;em&gt;is expected to be held up, if not blocked entirely&lt;/em&gt;, by Prop M&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There are two takeaways from this: 1) At least one of the two projects CCHO cites as a “real-world” project that can pencil out 25% affordable units is probably not going to end up going through in the real world, and 2) The reason it won’t go through is because a politician has an axe to grind, and would rather see his opponent’s project go down than get affordable housing built in his own district.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Affordable housing should not be a political tool, and holding projects hostage in petty political battles doesn’t help people who need affordable housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/at-regional-record-fair-tapes-steal-the-show/">
    <title type="text">At Regional Record Fair, Tapes Steal the Show</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:87cd757e-b18e-330a-9fc0-8f004537295a</id>
    <updated>2016-11-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/at-regional-record-fair-tapes-steal-the-show/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco’s Swedish American Hall was packed to the rafters yesterday with nerds, hipsters, and socialites alike basking in their shared reverence of the vinyl revival. Even without its stellar roster of vendors, I knew the Bay Area Record Fair (BARF) was where I belonged on a Sunday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The main auditorium was brimming with several live DJs, cash transactions, and cute tote bags holding bucketfuls of indie rock over neatly corduroy-covered shoulders. Some tables were more active than others: local metal purveyors from &lt;a href=&quot;http://theflenser.com/&quot;&gt;The Flenser&lt;/a&gt; saw lines of collectors flock to their table, while the San Francisco Guitar Center table next to them had hardly a single visitor claim their offering of free picks.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Music on vinyl has seen a surge in sales recently, presumably because it’s easier to impress a Tinder date with a thick, brittle disc than a randomized playlist. Despite the requisite multitude of thinkpieces attempting to explain the trend in more complicated narratives, Occam’s razor has kept the debate relatively muted for the companion medium: cassettes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tabsout.com/?p=11136&quot;&gt;No one needs to justify cassettes&lt;/a&gt;. They just are. Love them or hate them, the costs to enter the market are far lower than vinyl’s, and the product is guaranteed to last decades more than CDs.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After dutifully fortifying with some liquid courage, I trudged through the thicket of vintage pleated-skirts and acid-washed denim vests to find the tables of two trusted Oakland imprints, &lt;a href=&quot;https://innerislands.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Inner Islands&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ctatsu.bandcamp.com&quot;&gt;Constellation Tatsu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Steven Ramsey has been churning out brilliant, manifestly soothing music under the Constellation Tatsu imprint for nearly seven years. Each season, three or four echo-drenched soundscapes arrive at my doorstep (okay, email inbox) and, as I say nearly each time, these newest tapes may be the label’s best yet. Two in particular caught my attention: &lt;em&gt;In the Heart of Solitude&lt;/em&gt; by Stuart Chalmers, and &lt;em&gt;Exile&lt;/em&gt; by Rose.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Stuart Chalmers extends the autoharp beyond its standard mechanical paradigm into a ritualistic factory of sound. On &lt;em&gt;In the Heart of Solitude&lt;/em&gt;, strings ring and shimmer like church bells, and soft chords hover like blizzards on the horizon. Tracks like “The Void” show the instrument’s potential for low, almost didgeridoo-like resonances, while atonal whimsies such as “Lake At Dawn” evoke &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hIvP2otHGiw&quot;&gt;Laraaji’s&lt;/a&gt; new-age zither meditations and prepared piano odysseys in the style of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pUTXNxFvjDw&quot;&gt;John Cage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1444130369/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ctatsu.bandcamp.com/album/in-the-heart-of-solitude&quot;&gt;In the Heart of Solitude by Stuart Chalmers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though the Chalmers album is billed as “musique concrete,” a phrase coined by French avant-garde composer Pierre Schaeffer, one can only assume 20th century academic sensibilities would have scoffed at music so eminently enjoyable. This is far more true on Rose’s &lt;em&gt;Exile&lt;/em&gt;, a blending of grandiose orchestral textures and unassuming deep-house rhythms. While opener “Hydration Cherub” and closing tune “Gate” belong in an underwater coke lounge, replete with cooing whispers and distant piano etudes, the true elegance is on “Marble,” a song as simple and austere as the title suggests. A single synthesizer chord breathes and undulates like dough in a brick oven, gradually building mass until the drones feel solid in your ear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=555660932/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ctatsu.bandcamp.com/album/exile&quot;&gt;Exile by Rose&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Next to Ramsey’s table, Inner Islands impresario Sean Conrad sat smiling behind a rack of new tapes, a self-published photography zine, and records.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Foremost among his new releases is &lt;em&gt;Velvet and Bone&lt;/em&gt;, from Utah’s brilliant shaman-techno-bliss-rock chanteuse Stag Hare. The long-anticipated follow-up to the commissioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://innerislands.bandcamp.com/album/tapestry&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tapestry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; box set, the songs on &lt;em&gt;Velvet and Bone&lt;/em&gt; saunter along, in no hurry to make their statement. Though Stag Hare’s gentle beats thump at a uniformly slow-dance pace, there’s a story worth absorbing in the massive walls of guitar strumming and robotic singing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=2366098007/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://innerislands.bandcamp.com/album/velvet-and-bone&quot;&gt;Velvet And Bone by Stag Hare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Formally speaking, there’s nothing here the avid Stag Hare fan hasn’t heard before, but from ambient masterworks like “Locket” to the faux-krautrock groove in the closing “Ghosthunter,” new and old fans alike will hear the best iterations yet of a tried and true formula.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Stag Hare, a.k.a. Zara Biggs-Garrick, always includes aptly laconic liner notes. This time around they begin with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&quot;Velvet and Bone is structured as a gothic fable. 
It is about the act of self reflection through knowing another. 
It is about seeing the shadow and knowing the shadow. 
It is about seeing death and knowing death. 
It is about bones, and the way they are shaped 
by the tensions put on them by various 
opposing muscles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As promised, every moment of tension contains its own soothing resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Among the more pleasant surprises was Braeyden Jae, who, unbeknowns to me, had been sitting next to Conrad the entire time we chatted. An ambient musician from Salt Lake City, Jae recently relocated to Oakland, and has remained prolific in 2016. Under the new moniker “softest,” Jae has issued a new cassette, &lt;em&gt;Hidden Guitar &amp;amp; Water Music.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=932427956/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://innerislands.bandcamp.com/album/hidden-guitar-water-music&quot;&gt;hidden guitar &amp;amp; water music by softest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A single epic movement stretching over a half-hour in time, Jae crafts a sound environment wholly unrecognizable as guitar, a stream of tangible melody that blends into the trickling river-sounds hinted at by the title. The dissonance swells with the intensity of the water flow, and consonance breaks through the fog only when the tide has receded.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“So this is the new one from Braeyden Jae?” I asked.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I’m Braeyden,” a voice responded.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I saw a somewhat familiar pair of eyes, but the face was unrecognizable to me with a new beard and thick red glasses. It took a few more seconds of squinting to assure myself this was the same man I had met over a year ago, when he last graced an Oakland stage. Somehow, he still recognized me. Jae gave me a copy of his new LP &lt;em&gt;Fog Mirror&lt;/em&gt; at a discount—but this piece is about tapes, so we’ll wrap this up now.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;With enough tension and bad vibes to fill up the news cycle for the next few days, we all deserve this break. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1551926820/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://braeydenjae.bandcamp.com/album/fog-mirror&quot;&gt;fog mirror by braeyden jae&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/soda-lobby-stumps-generously-with-mailers-consulting-in-district-1-race/">
    <title type="text">Soda Lobby's Ties to District 1 Race Run Deep</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:19d87e0b-da2c-3bea-8977-b1883e271c03</id>
    <updated>2016-11-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/soda-lobby-stumps-generously-with-mailers-consulting-in-district-1-race/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update: the Fewer campaign has informed us that the candidate supports Proposition V.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At last count, the American Beverage Association had poured &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/Powerful-interest-groups-funding-Wiener-Kim-state-10130727.php&quot;&gt;at least $21 million&lt;/a&gt; into San Francisco’s election to defeat Proposition V, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/prop-v-tax-sugary-beverages-san-francisco/&quot;&gt;a tax on sugary drinks&lt;/a&gt;. This count often overlooks a curious anomaly—not all campaign media spending is required to be reported locally via periodic filings at the San Francisco Ethics Commission. Slate mail organizations, which are prohibited from advertising in any way other than physical USPS mailings, are only required to report to the state of California.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This can result in what some observers describe as “distortions” of the campaign finance narrative. For example, it is public record that the San Francisco Tenants Union mailed slate cards with $120,000 donated by the American Beverage Association’s No on V PAC. Meanwhile, the Affordable Housing Alliance—a slate mail organization funded entirely by the same PAC—need not report at the local level. Its latest expenditure reports will not be public until early 2017. The most recent filings date to October 22nd, before the latest wave of mail campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At the latest report, No on V has donated $280,000 to the Affordable Housing Alliance. The latter also shares its sole consultant, Jim Stearns, with the campaign of District 1 Supervisorial candidate Sandra Lee Fewer. As of October 22nd, Stearns is also on record receiving $20,000 in consulting fees from the No On V PAC.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;(Curiously, Stearns has also collected consulting fees from District 5 Supervisorial candidate Dean Preston, who supports the soda tax.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Because the Affordable Housing Alliance is not registered as an independent expenditure committee, it is not illegal for the Fewer campaign to directly coordinate with the Affordable Housing Alliance, whose No On V-funded mailers promote Fewer’s campaign and frequently attack her opponent, Marjan Philhour.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;According to Todd David of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sfparentpac.com/&quot;&gt;San Francisco Parent PAC&lt;/a&gt;, coordination doesn’t get much more direct than that. Although he’s familiar with slate mail organizations coordinating with independent expenditure committees (IEs), the collusion via a consultant is unprecedented. Although it is legal, he said, “I’ve never, and people I’ve spoken to have never seen anything like this before.” Referring to Stearns’ multiple roles, David added, “you can’t not coordinate with yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/mayor-lee-joins-three-supervisors-in-urging-common-sense-over-petty-politics/">
    <title type="text">Mayor Lee Joins Three Supervisors in Urging “Common Sense” over “Petty Politics”</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:923e9186-a47b-3209-953d-acb1cd88fa2f</id>
    <updated>2016-11-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/mayor-lee-joins-three-supervisors-in-urging-common-sense-over-petty-politics/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco’s Noriega Street bustled with lunchgoers basking in the sun, lining up for Dim Sum. On the corner of 31st Avenue, Supervisor Katy Tang shopped for pastries at Donut Time before her colleagues arrived. She was soon joined by Mayor Ed Lee, along with fellow Supervisors Scott Wiener and Mark Farrell, to advocate for their preferred ballot measures.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Local activists and merchants flanked the quartet of elected officials with signs for various campaigns: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dumbharmfullotsofmoney.com/&quot;&gt;No on DHLM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.housingnottents.com&quot;&gt;Yes on Q&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/j5qhWnirWU&quot;&gt;Yes on J &amp;amp; K&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In her introduction of Mayor Lee, Supervisor Tang discussed her opposition to this year’s Proposition M. “These are four measures I believe will cost taxpayers more money, but actually be less effective in terms of how we better serve San Francisco residents,” she said. “In particular, M will hurt our small businesses and affordable housing.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lee began his speech by underscoring his support not only for Hillary Clinton, but also Kamala Harris in the U.S. Senator race, and Scott Wiener for State Senate.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Keep it simple, keep it rational, keep it common sense,” the Mayor said of his ballot endorsements. He urged those in attendance to support Propositions J and K, which will allocate and fund new sales tax revenue for transit and homelessness services. Lee followed by adding his support for Proposition Q, a “Housing Not Tents” measure proposed by Supervisor Farrell.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It’s important…for all of us lucky enough to have a place to live, to help get [the homeless] off our streets,” Lee said. “I’m all about building more housing, preserving affordable housing—but I also have to help the most challenged, our homeless. Prop Q, along with J &amp;amp; K, will do that.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Farrell added that recent statistics on health and safety hazards in the city’s various tent encampments exemplified the urgency of his measure, which would require 24-hour notice and guaranteed shelter before clearing tent encampments. (Editor’s note: the SF YIMBY Party has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfyimby.org/endorsementexplainer/&quot;&gt;endorsed No on Q&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Wiener added his support for J &amp;amp; K, noting that local legislation was necessary before greater state and federal reform could occur. “The Bay Area is going to grow by 2 million people in the next 20 years…if we don’t get this funding, the gridlock we see on our roads and freeways will look like child’s play.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mayor Lee ultimately kept his scorn for Propositions D, H, L, and M quite brief. “None of these measures were put on the ballot to improve anything,” Lee insisted. “They are petty politics that will waste time and waste money. I hope people study them and vote No.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After the press conference, Lee dismissed press questions about the recent rumors that Hillary Clinton was considering him for a cabinet position as mere “speculation.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Watch the press conference in its entirety below:&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2FNoDHLM%2Fvideos%2F382961665379908%2F&amp;show_text=0&amp;width=400&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowTransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-council-race-gets-greener-but-not-from-grassroots/">
    <title type="text">Palo Alto Council Race Gets Greener, But Not from Grassroots</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:1c8b75ed-1314-38e2-9fe8-8914dbf2363c</id>
    <updated>2016-11-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-council-race-gets-greener-but-not-from-grassroots/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There are four seats open on Palo Alto’s City Council, eleven candidates vying for them, and hundreds of thousands of dollars pouring into the race.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The October cash infusion into two candidate’s campaigns set a new level of political spending for a local race in Palo Alto, raising the eyebrows of residents, journalists, and former elected officials alike. &lt;a href=&quot;http://paloaltoonline.com/news/2016/10/19/huge-political-contributions-spark-outcry-suspicion-in-palo-altos-council-race&quot;&gt;Five families recently donated over $160,000&lt;/a&gt; to “residentialist” candidates Lydia Kou and Arthur Keller. “Residentialist” refers generally to slow-growth constituents who prefer to see the city temper new development, emphasizing concerns around traffic, parking, and overcrowding in schools.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;These amounts were surprising, to say the least, given the historic size of contributions in a city that prides itself on its small town character. A letter from Palo Alto’s eight previous mayors called the contributions “shocking”, noting that checks for $5,000 or more were unprecedented in Palo Alto City Council elections, with individual donations typically not exceeding $500. Lydia Kou, in fact, remarks &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lydiakou.com/&quot;&gt;on her campaign website&lt;/a&gt; that after moving to Palo Alto she “grew to love belonging to a village”.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But if its local elections are any indicator, this village, hen it comes to politics, plays the big city game.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The donors of $160k in question &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paloaltoonline.com/news/reports/1476859852.pdf&quot;&gt;defended their contributions&lt;/a&gt; as a response to “big developer money” and a Chamber of Commerce endorsement, which they perceive to be unfairly influencing the campaigns of “pro-growth” or “pro-development” candidates, including Adrian Fine, Greg Tanaka, and incumbent Liz Kniss. In line with those remarks, a recent mailer ad from the Kou and Keller camps claims that nearly one-third of Fine’s contributions came from developers.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This claim was fact-checked by &lt;em&gt;Palo Alto Weekly&lt;/em&gt;, who concluded that &lt;a href=&quot;http://paloaltoonline.com/news/2016/10/25/palo-alto-council-candidates-trade-barbs-over-negative-ads&quot;&gt;only about $6,000&lt;/a&gt; of the $50,000-plus Adrian Fine has raised to date actually came from real estate developers.  Palo Altans for Sensible Zoning, the residentialist political action committee who is behind the ad, appears to have overreached in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paszaction.com/developer_money_part_2&quot;&gt;their definition of real estate&lt;/a&gt;, including donors in professions such as land use consulting, environmental planning, and architecture –  even retired architects and consultants.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;If one considers campaign finance to be the sole determining influence over future city policy, it seems Palo Alto is destined to become a retirement community.  Of $63,124 contributed to Lydia Kou’s campaign in the last month, more than half of donations were made by retirees. Keller’s numbers are even higher; of $63,575 raised in the last reporting period, $44,150 came from retired donors – more than two-thirds of the total. In total, Lydia Kou has raised $90,061 to date and Arthur Keller has raised $97,650.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Fine, on the other hand, seems to be receiving financial support from a broader base of the community – technology workers, attorneys, consultants, and entrepreneurs. His contributions have also come in much smaller dollar amounts. In his latest filing, the vast majority of donations came in under $500, and all but three were under $1,000. In &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.votefine.com/negative_ad_response&quot;&gt;a response to the negative ad claim&lt;/a&gt;, Fine notes that his campaign is funded by 182 individual donors, averaging $280 per donor. In total, Adrian Fine has raised $68,821.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Tanaka has received support from residents in fields such as technology, finance, consulting, architecture, public service, and yes, real estate. Liz Kniss’s contributors show similar professional diversity, with total dollars raised to date of $54,158. Tanaka raised $11,249 in the last month, bringing his total funding to $58,572.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In total, the “pro-growth” slate of Adrian Fine, Liz Kniss, and Greg Tanaka have raised $181,541, coming in just shy of Keller and Kou’s combined $187,711.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The latest development in the residentialist campaign is the sizeable expenditures by the committees of Lydia Kou and Arthur Keller on a political consultancy firm, RMS Associates. RMS Associates, a subsidiary of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rmsdigitalinteractive.com/team/&quot;&gt;RMS Interactive&lt;/a&gt;, is a political consultancy firm founded by Richard Schlackman. Schlackman touts over 40 years of experience in political campaigns and is credited with conceiving the idea of mailed ads as an effective tool for political advertising.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The two candidates combined have spent $86,148 on RMS Associates’ services, according to filings published by Lydia Kou’s and Arthur Keller’s campaigns last Thursday, $47,321 by Ms. Kou and $38,827 by Mr. Keller. The services rendered by Mr. Schlackman’s firms appear to be related to the mailer ads targeting Adrian Fine discussed above. In total, Lydia Kou and Arthur Keller have spent over $130,000 combined in their political campaigns for city council, just over $66,000 each.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Palo Altans for Sensible Zoning, the political action committee supporting residentialist policies and candidates, has raised nearly $30,000 itself to date. In its latest filing, PASZ reports spending $20,000 to have two polls conducted for Kou and Keller, at $10,000 per survey. The poll was conducted by Lincoln Park Strategies, a nationally-known, Washington D.C.-based firm. Its founder, Stefan Hankin, worked as a pollster on Barack Obama’s presidential campaign in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;No other candidates aside from Mr. Keller or Ms. Kou have retained political consulting firms in their campaign efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Evidently, when it comes to raising campaign funds for the residentialists, it takes a village.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/tenants-in-todco-property-allege-abuse-neglect-and-intimidation/">
    <title type="text">Tenants in TODCO Property Allege Abuse, Neglect, and Intimidation</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:eccb9595-f176-3d94-9b90-26ea8dc34532</id>
    <updated>2016-11-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/tenants-in-todco-property-allege-abuse-neglect-and-intimidation/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Donna Muir has terminal liver cancer. She spends her days shuffling between medical treatments, seeing family, and tidying up her room. Ms. Muir lives in a tiny apartment at the Knox Hotel, a Single-Room Occupancy (SRO) building in San Francisco’s South of Market district. Recently, she successfully fought off an eviction suit, one which her attorneys describe as “frivolous” given its suspicious timing. Muir had been complaining about a lack of hot water in her room for four months—once the suit was dropped, she suddenly had hot water again.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The tenant of 17 years received a notice to vacate by August 1st, just after the Department of Building Inspection (DBI) made an unannounced visit to the property on July 26th.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ms. Muir likes to collect aloe vera plants. Every so often, she trudges out of the Knox Hotel with a knife and a backpack to carry pieces of aloe home. One day, her knife fell out of her backpack, and building management alleged that she intended to stab someone. They had been waiting, she says, and now they had their chance. “They wanted to make an example of me, because I spoke out,” Muir told me.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tenants-in-todco-property-allege-abuse-neglect-and-intimidation/faucet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;When she had no hot water, Ms. Muir says she brought hot water up in milk bottles from this sink in the basement, until the faucet was removed. (Courtesy: Donna Muir)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;TODCO, the non-profit developer responsible for the Knox Hotel, is &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/dark-money-from-subsidized-real-estate-faces-calls-for-investigation/&quot;&gt;under investigation&lt;/a&gt; for funneling money earned from refinancing several properties into political campaigns through a shell company, the Yerba Buena Neighborhood Consortium. In an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Pre-election-opening-for-Warm-Springs-BART-looks-9981990.php&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with the San Francisco &lt;em&gt;Chronicle&lt;/em&gt;, TODCO director John Elberling admitted to doing so and insisted the process was fully transparent and legal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Critics have urged investigators to consider what else TODCO could have done with its profit—for example, building new affordable housing or repairing existing properties. Our research at the Knox Hotel shows that this is beyond mere speculation: TODCO and the John Stewart Company, the building’s property manager, have been intentionally skimping on repairs, and intimidating residents who voice their complaints.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Donna Muir is going public with what she describes as a lengthy pattern of abuse and exploitation of residents by the property managers. She alleges that Janet Thompson, the property manager since 2006, collects a bonus for implementing cost-savings by skimping on repairs, even as the Knox Hotel raises its rent every year. Now, she claims, Thompson is refusing to accept her rent payments. She alleges that the Knox Hotel also requested a duplicate payment of $150, which her medical provider offers to assist with rent, after they had already cashed their first check.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“They don’t give a shit about us,” says her neighbor, Henry Savage. “She’s got health problems, and I’m the only one who can help her.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mr. Savage cannot take a shower without scraping up a handful of lead paint from the floor. Recently, he slipped in the shower and injured his back; Thompson, he alleges, told the judge of a decades-old criminal record in Minnesota, before his small claims case was dismissed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tenants-in-todco-property-allege-abuse-neglect-and-intimidation/shower.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lead paint peeling off the floor in Mr. Savage's shower. (Courtesy: Henry Savage)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“When I moved in, the place was filthy. Dust and grime everywhere,” he told me. “When I asked, they said my home-care had to do that. That’s not their job! When you move in to an apartment, it’s supposed to be clean and tidy. They gave the last guy his deposit back, so why didn’t they clean anything?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In addition to receiving treatment for a brain tumor, Mr. Savage shows me a blister on his arm, where he was given an injection to test for tuberculosis. “There’s thirty people in this building with TB, and they walk around not covering their faces when they cough. That could be an epidemic,” he says. We have not been able to verify this claim.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ms. Muir claims that the Knox Hotel received grant money to repair showers, but sought out the cheapest plumbers they could possibly find to save funds. “They literally hired people off the street,” she says. “This shower was filthy underneath—mold everywhere. See this grouting?” She directs my attention to a white stripe beneath the edge of the shower. “I did that all myself.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tenants-in-todco-property-allege-abuse-neglect-and-intimidation/broomfan2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ms. Muir also insists that building management has refused to fix her broken bathroom fan. (Courtesy: Donna Muir)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Her toilet, she claims, was left to run for four months. She showed me a video she took on her phone as proof. “This was during a water shortage. They didn’t send anyone. Unbelievable.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Donna Muir’s apartment has broken windows that do not close all the way; her heater is a paltry comfort. Her kitchen faucet was replaced with used, moldy parts until she complained enough to get a new one. “I watched them take that one out of the box,” she assures me. “Otherwise, who knows what they would’ve tried.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tenants-in-todco-property-allege-abuse-neglect-and-intimidation/window.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ms. Muir's window, which does not close properly&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Muir also purchased her own mini-fridge, just in case, after building management refused to replace her leaking refrigerator. She claims it took three years of complaints—which public records from the Department of Building Inspection corroborate—to get faulty electrical sockets fixed. A painful rivet in her bedframe jabbed into her spine and gave her bed sores. “After a whole year,” she tells me, “I finally got them to replace the bed.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tenants-in-todco-property-allege-abuse-neglect-and-intimidation/dbi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;An excerpt from one of many Department of Building Inspection documents following up on Ms. Muir's complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;More recently, her shower drain began overflowing with raw sewage late at night. Building management refused to pay for an after-hours plumber to repair the pipes until she threatened to call the police.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“They hire the biggest crooks,” Ms. Muir says of the John Stewart Company. “I contacted John Stewart, and Elberling at TODCO, they didn’t care. They just referred me back to Janet [Thompson].” Her complaints to Supervisor Jane Kim and Representative Nancy Pelosi also went largely unanswered, she says.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Paradoxically, Muir explains that the Knox Hotel is reluctant to pursue eviction proceedings for the most egregious violations. “These neighbors were dumping feces out of their window every single day,” she says as she pulls out a picture on her phone. “They did nothing until all the businesses on the street complained.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tenants-in-todco-property-allege-abuse-neglect-and-intimidation/shit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A trail of fecal matter descending from a nearby window. (Courtesy: Donna Muir)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Worse, she says there is ongoing exploitation of senior citizens bordering on the criminal. Muir says she’s reported the building’s maintenance person, known to residents only as Noki, for illegal entry. “He has master keys, and goes in when we’re not there. I’ve caught him leaving,” she insists. “The desk clerk, thankfully, he tries to call people to warn them.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“There’s elderly abuse here too, don’t think they don’t know about it,” she went on. “One woman was being beaten, and they did nothing. I said they had to call social services, do something, but they didn’t. Finally they dragged her out of here, dead from blunt force trauma, and sold all her furniture out the back door.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Muir adds that she’s certain building management has taken narcotics medication from deceased residents to sell on the black market as well.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Basically,” she said to me as I left her room, “when you live here, you have no voice.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At press time, TODCO had not responded to requests for comment. The John Stewart Company could not discuss specific legal proceedings regarding their residents.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/comics-the-atherton-police-blotter/">
    <title type="text">Comics: The Atherton Police Blotter</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:88b4ba4e-ddc9-352b-9764-cf76106c248f</id>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/comics-the-atherton-police-blotter/" />
    <author>
      <name>Krusty Wheatfield</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an illustrated adaptation of &quot;The best of the Atherton police blotter,&quot; an irregular feature on the&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mercurynews.com/2011/08/27/the-best-of-atherton-police-blotter/&quot;&gt;San Jose Mercury News&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;-Eds.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Copyright &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.krustywheatfield.com/&quot;&gt;Krusty Wheatfield&lt;/a&gt; 2016&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/video-san-franciscos-pony-tailed-godfather-of-white-paternalism/">
    <title type="text">Video: San Francisco's &quot;Pony-Tailed Godfather of White Paternalism&quot;</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:f06c9c06-3ebd-38bd-b7b4-24352a81ebfa</id>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/video-san-franciscos-pony-tailed-godfather-of-white-paternalism/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This fascinating documentary on San Francisco’s Haight-Ashbury District sheds some much-needed light on the city’s topsy-turvy housing politics. The KRON film &lt;a href=&quot;https://diva.sfsu.edu/collections/sfbatv/bundles/218071&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assignment Four: A report from the neighborhood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; chronicles the Haight neighborhood’s down-zoning in 1972 in response to a nationwide period of urban renewal, in which several lower-income neighborhoods in the city were demolished for freeway construction.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In light of today’s op-ed in the &lt;em&gt;Examiner&lt;/em&gt; titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/progressives-black-problem/&quot;&gt;“The progressives’ black problem,”&lt;/a&gt; it is important to note early footage of Haight-Ashbury homeowner Calvin Welch, whom Jacquelyn Otumalade describes as “the pony-tailed godfather of white paternalism in San Francisco.” At the 21:48 mark, Welch says the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Some of the most conservative people in this neighborhood are what we might call middle-class black people. They are still striving for that traditional American dream. It’s not up to me to tell them that I feel it’s a bankrupt dream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Welch owns a duplex in a neighborhood with average sale prices surpassing $2 million, but thanks to legacy property tax caps implemented under &lt;a href=&quot;http://lao.ca.gov/Publications/Report/3497&quot;&gt;Proposition 13&lt;/a&gt;, its net taxable value remains only slightly above $65,000. The property was purchased in 1973 for $31,000, or $172,000 in today’s dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;video class=&quot;video-js vjs-default-skin&quot; controls width=&quot;auto&quot; height=&quot;auto&quot; poster=&quot;https://diva.sfsu.edu/bundles/preview/798759&quot; data-setup=&quot;{}&quot;&gt;&lt;source src=&quot;https://diva.sfsu.edu/bundles/preview/798758&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover photo: Calvin Welch &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/stakeholders-search-for-common-ground-in-land-use-debate/&quot;&gt;debates&lt;/a&gt; Angelo King on Proposition O, October 2016. Courtesy: Brian Hanlon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-why-is-ccho-afraid-of-the-city-controllers-prop-c-study/">
    <title type="text">Editorial: Why is CCHO Afraid of the City Controller’s Prop C Study?</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:8a60e13c-2922-3b83-91df-719bb34bd483</id>
    <updated>2016-10-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-why-is-ccho-afraid-of-the-city-controllers-prop-c-study/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When Proposition C passed in June of this year, increasing the required amount of affordable housing in new developments to 25%, the Supervisors behind the measure agreed to let the city conduct a study on how the policy would actually impact development. Many opponents of the measure, including the mayor, had concerns that such a requirement could slow down overall housing production if developers faced difficulty financing new projects.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Controller’s Office published preliminary findings suggesting that 25% is indeed too high. According to the Controller, 18% is the economically feasible maximum for most developments. The Office is continuing to develop its findings, with its most recent draft available &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfcontroller.org/sites/default/files/Preliminary%20Report%20September%202016.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
In the meantime, the Community Council of Housing Organizations (CCHO) apparently has deep concerns about what the Controller might find in regard to the 25% requirement, and penned an &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0BwIcMtCqttV2T3B3R0hTWXBTQ3NsSmZ6NDJ3M05uMl8wbFdN/view&quot;&gt;open letter&lt;/a&gt; urging the office to consider some additional factors. The letter to the Controller outlines six main points for the working group to consider, which in sum champion the current 25% requirement and take issue with any findings which might disturb that number.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Most of these points have their own problems, however.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Most glaringly, Directors Peter Cohen and Fernando Martí seem to consider housing low-income residents to be merely a tangential policy goal. “First,” they write, “is the goal of capturing the windfall profits from increasing land value.” Really? That’s their first goal?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Even if maximizing the construction of affordable housing units isn’t the primary goal, the authors go on to explain why economic feasibility should be a non-issue for the Controller.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;CCHO points us to two recent “real world projects” to be built a 25% inclusionary requirement. A large project at 1515 South Van Ness, as well as another development in the Excelsior, are both in the works and are slated to contain 25% affordable units. The South Van Ness development, it is worth noting, has still received &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/08/mission-district-housing-project-reaches-25-percent-affordable/&quot;&gt;numerous complaints&lt;/a&gt; from resident groups such as Calle 24, who want to see the number bumped even higher.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The second development at 915-917 Cayuga &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a noteworthy and even exceptional project when it comes to affordability. The developer, SST Investments, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Developer-wants-to-create-rent-controlled-housing-10152241.php&quot;&gt;has agreed to build 51 rent-controlled units and 52 BMR units&lt;/a&gt;, which is almost unheard of for a private developer.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;CCHO omits the fact that SST bought the land in 2009 for $1.8 million, an incredibly low price for 25,000 square feet. $1.8 million may only get you a single &lt;em&gt;house&lt;/em&gt; in San Francisco today. So, what does this example mean for developments more generally? Hardly anything. This scenario is &lt;strong&gt;extremely unlikely to be repeated today.&lt;/strong&gt; The referenced article, in fact, refers to the deal as “an unusual combination of the right developer buying the right piece of property at the right time.” Meanwhile, the developer called the deal a “philanthropic legacy project.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Touting &lt;strong&gt;two&lt;/strong&gt; real world projects is an arguably light body of “evidence.” Prop C passed in June of this year - it’s been four months since that happened, and if two projects that is all we can show, it doesn’t bode well for this mandated level of BMR.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;CCHO further claims that the Controller report ignores state density bonuses its study. The state density bonus lets developers build more floors if they include a certain portion of affordable units, which CCHO argues would make any project with 25% affordable housing eligible for the bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;First of all, let’s not forget that &lt;em&gt;CCHO itself opposed an affordable housing density bonus in San Francisco&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/SF-housing-density-plan-meets-opposition-6810769.php&quot;&gt;earlier this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This is a red herring. Just because a project is eligible for a density bonus doesn’t mean that project can economically support it, as CCHO eagerly concludes. Moreover, CCHO appears to be looking at the wrong starting point here. It argues that once a project is compliant with a 25% inclusionary rate, it becomes eligible for the 35% state density bonus. How does that &lt;em&gt;prove&lt;/em&gt; the 25% itself is supportable? It doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;CCHO also wants the Controller to consider increasing the inclusionary requirement for taller buildings, meaning those over 300 feet, which it characterizes as “a luxury category unaffordable to all but the wealthiest of buyers or renters.” With exactly zero numerical basis or any economic analysis attached this statement, CCHO insists that taller “luxury” buildings be subject to higher inclusionary requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The entire point of the Controller’s analysis is to identify the upper limit of economic feasibility on new developments using rigorous, quantitative analyses. More importantly, the regression model developed for the Controller’s analysis &lt;em&gt;already takes building height into consideration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;From the Controller’s report:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Second, the size of the potential development, &lt;em&gt;which is primarily driven by height restrictions&lt;/em&gt; and density limits, also matters.&lt;/strong&gt; The potential size of the housing that can be developed on the parcel is positively correlated with the addition of multifamily market-rate housing.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Based on this relationship derived from our regression analysis, we developed a simulation model to estimate the likely change in development that would result from setting an inclusionary policy at various levels.” (Emphasis added)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In any arena of policy, selecting a number and working backward to support is recipe for cherry-picking and selective thinking. That is what CCHO appears to be doing in this letter. The Controller isn’t even finished completing its analysis, and already an outside organization is attempting to exert influence over the conclusions, based on a preconceived idea of what their touted policy will deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Creating more affordable housing through targeted policy is a good thing. Ignoring evidence that the policy in question &lt;em&gt;might not deliver the intended goal&lt;/em&gt; is dangerous thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/five-alarm-fire-spells-uncertain-future-for-lake-merritt-development/">
    <title type="text">Five-Alarm Fire Spells Uncertain Future for Lake Merritt Development</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:2d67bd0a-d4ce-33c2-b8ab-e1cec84c5804</id>
    <updated>2016-10-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/five-alarm-fire-spells-uncertain-future-for-lake-merritt-development/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Residents in Oakland’s Eastlake neighborhood awoke in the early morning hours today to a frenzy of sirens and a massive conflagration. The five-alarm fire consumed a construction site at 317 Lester Avenue and forced nearly 200 locals to evacuate the area. Firefighters managed to contain the blaze and prevent it from spreading to nearby buildings, though ABC 7 News has since &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LauraAnthony7/status/793171989926031360&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms (ATF) will be launching an investigation due to the size of the construction site.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Maria Grazer, resident of a nearby condominium, awoke to sirens around 5 A.M. and just barely had time to evacuate with her dog. “The flames looked like they were growing and we were moved down the street because the embers were falling all around us,” she wrote in an email. “It was a rather scary scene, and I kept thinking that it could jump to our building at any moment. It's a scary feeling, thinking that in a moment, you could lose absolutely everything.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/five-alarm-fire-spells-uncertain-future-for-lake-merritt-development/fire4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The site at 317 Lester Avenue had been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildzoom.com/property-info/317-lester-ave-oakland-ca&quot;&gt;permitted&lt;/a&gt; for the construction of a five-story building with 41 market-rate housing units. Athan Magganas, manager at the development firm Adelphos LLC, told &lt;a href=&quot;https://ww2.kqed.org/news/2016/10/31/massive-4-alarm-fire-near-oaklands-lake-merritt-causes-millions-of-dollars-in-damage/&quot;&gt;KQED&lt;/a&gt; that he estimated nearly $5 million in property damage. The site’s contractors are now out of work, and he is uncertain that Adelphos’s insurance policy will cover it.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This is the second construction project in Oakland to burn down this year. In July, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/construction-site-in-emeryville-burns-down/&quot;&gt;a fire&lt;/a&gt; forestalled a project with 100 units on the Emeryville border.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photos courtesy of Maria Grazer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-when-will-we-use-this/">
    <title type="text">Dispatches from the Vote16 Campaign: When Will We Use This?</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:fca155ce-daa9-3466-80ef-4b3e8aa60568</id>
    <updated>2016-10-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-when-will-we-use-this/" />
    <author>
      <name>Cami Doo</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Students often lament, “When will we ever use this in real life?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It’s a valid question. Engineers don’t need to know how to perform calculus; it comes in software packages. No average worker has to recite all the presidents in order and know how many terms they served, but AP US History students do.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yes, all the materials learned in high school have basis in how the world functions today and the advanced technology we enjoy. It’s important to know these things for the sake of knowing them, but very little skills are applicable in life after high school or college.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There used to be classes for practical skills like cooking, sewing, and home repair. How about connecting current events and history with our everyday lives?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Specifically, schools rarely have classes that teach students how to register to vote or review the local and state propositions; yet these decisions influence their future. Whether it’s about tuition, housing, or other issues, all are relevant to students’ lives.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/San_Francisco_City_and_County,_California_ballot_measures&quot;&gt;Proposition F&lt;/a&gt; seeks to do just that: make history class pertinent to life outside of school. During the endorsement meeting with the Board of Education, youth persuaded every single commissioner. Then the Board promised to reform the curriculum to prepare 16 and 17 year olds to vote.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Part of Prop. F’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/opinion/editorials/article/Voting-should-remain-a-privilege-for-adult-9206099.php&quot;&gt;pushback&lt;/a&gt; has stemmed from doubts that 16 year olds are informed enough, but who or what iss to blame? Perhaps it is a systemic problem, that schools aren’t designed to connect curricula with current events.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;With Prop. F, however, teachers will educate juniors and seniors about the responsibility of voting.  Also, at school, students can have educated discussions with their teachers and peers.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, by participating in local elections, students would gain experience in order to take on the bigger responsibility of national elections.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Prop. F could transform the classroom into a more relevant and lively place of education and discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover photo: Sonja Trauss,&lt;/em&gt; Metro Observer &lt;em&gt;webmaster, voting Yes on F.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/asian-community-alliance-rallies-against-dark-money-in-kim-and-fewer-campaigns/">
    <title type="text">Asian Community Alliance Rallies Against “Dark Money” in Kim and Fewer Campaigns</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:618b9f34-d449-3b97-bf10-0405d395b709</id>
    <updated>2016-10-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/asian-community-alliance-rallies-against-dark-money-in-kim-and-fewer-campaigns/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Under a drizzle of rain on the steps of city hall, a crowd of several dozen gathered, hoisting signs critical of State Senate candidate Jane Kim and District 1 Supervisorial candidate Sandra Lee Fewer.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Some read “Jane Kim Is For Sale” while others were more simply labeled, “$$$ Dark Money $$$.” The Asian Community Alliance’s grievances are twofold: first, they sought to draw attention to the American Beverage Association’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/Soda-industry-trying-hard-to-block-Bay-Area-taxes-10326676.php&quot;&gt;$19.3 million&lt;/a&gt; in local campaign contributions this election cycle. In particular, $40,000 went to fund an election mailer from the San Francisco Tenants Union endorsing Supervisor Kim and Supervisor-hopeful Fewer, and $180,000 from a similar mailer by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/big-soda-backs-jane-kim/&quot;&gt;Affordable Housing Alliance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Second, John Elberling of affordable housing developer TODCO was &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/dark-money-from-subsidized-real-estate-faces-calls-for-investigation/&quot;&gt;recently revealed&lt;/a&gt; to have funneled millions of profits from refinancing subsidized housing into a shell company, the Yerba Buena Neighborhood Consortium, to fund ballot measure campaigns. Elberling contributed significantly to the Yes On C campaign in June in support of a ballot measure largely spearheaded by Supervisor Kim.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Demonstrators alternated between chants of “No no no—No vote for Jane Kim!” and several slogans in Chinese.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/asian-community-alliance-rallies-against-dark-money-in-kim-and-fewer-campaigns/aca2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sonja Trauss, founder of the SF Bay Area Renters Federation and webmaster of this publication, was also present. She posed for cameras with a detailed sign critical of TODCO and the American Beverage Association.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of the rally, Trauss was given the megaphone to explain the TODCO scandal, with interpolation from a Chinese interpreter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;TODCO owns nine affordable housing developments in Jane Kim’s District. Recently, they made a large profit off of their building by refinancing. They did not use that profit to build more affordable housing, even though we need it. Instead, they used that money to attack good people like Marjan Philhour, and to promote bad politicians like Jane Kim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“At first TODCO hid the fact that it was spending money on politics,” Trauss later said to a nearby reporter (not yours truly). “Now Elberling is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Pre-election-opening-for-Warm-Springs-BART-looks-9981990.php&quot;&gt;saying&lt;/a&gt; quite plainly that they had an excess of income over expenses—which as a non-profit, that’s not supposed to happen, they’re supposed to reinvest it…That’s the public’s money, and we really do need more subsidized housing. He’s wasting our money on politics.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-capitelli-campaign-responds-to-lauriefactscom-attacks/">
    <title type="text">Op-Ed: Capitelli Campaign Responds to Attacks</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:4b025353-215e-329b-ac6d-6a0981a30f89</id>
    <updated>2016-10-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-capitelli-campaign-responds-to-lauriefactscom-attacks/" />
    <author>
      <name>Jill Martinucci</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jill Martinucci serves as Campaign Coordinator in the Laurie Capitelli for Berkeley Mayor campaign.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As the Berkeley mayoral race heats up, the two leading candidates have begun sparring on their respective housing policy records. Jesse Arreguín’s campaign recently paid for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lauriefacts.com/affordable-housing&quot;&gt;LaurieFacts.com&lt;/a&gt;, a website primarily dedicated to attacking opponent Laurie Capitelli’s votes on affordable housing. The Capitelli campaign released a rebuttal to what they describe as misleading misinformation from Arreguín. It is reprinted here in full, with permission from the campaign. &lt;em&gt;—Eds.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 1.  February 2010: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ci.berkeley.ca.us/Clerk/City_Council/2010/02Feb/City_Council__02-09-2010_-_Regular_Meeting_Annotated_Agenda.aspx%20Despite&quot;&gt;Capitelli votes against allocating funding&lt;/a&gt; from the General Fund to conduct a study about expanding affordable housing. Despite Capitelli’s “no” vote, the legislation passes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This vote was part of the full budget adoption. One of the funding items was to allocate $30,000 to do an affordable housing Nexus study. Laurie’s comments at the time were about the overall budget, and that other jurisdictions were beginning their studies and we could possibly piggy back on theirs and save some money. Laurie moved to defer the allocation until the subsequent budget cycle. Kriss [Worthington] made a substitute motion to accept the budget item and allow staff to work with other jurisdictions if possible. He voted to oppose on budgetary grounds and was joined by Councilmember Wozniak and Wengraf.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Let’s remember, this was 2010, just 18 months after an economic collapse, and the City’s financial outlook was not good.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;From the accompanying city Manager’s mid-year budget report:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The economic downturn is deeper and longer lasting than other recessions in the last four decades. Like other California cities, we are experiencing substantial erosion of our local revenues (property-based and other economy-driven taxes and fees). These revenue losses result in budget deficits and present Council with the difficult challenge of re-balancing the budget, largely through cost reductions. The projected citywide shortfall for F[iscal] Y[ear] 2010 is significant – about $14.3 million”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/op-ed-capitelli-campaign-responds-to-lauriefactscom-attacks/fullsizerender-4-.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jesse Arreguin's campaign mailer attacks Laurie Capitelli using a copyrighted photo of him from &lt;em&gt;Berkeleyside&lt;/em&gt; without permission. (courtesy: editor's mailbox, and &lt;em&gt;Berkeleyside&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.  June 2011: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ci.berkeley.ca.us/Clerk/City_Council/2011/06Jun/City_Council__06-28-2011_-_Regular_Meeting_Annotated_Agenda.aspx&quot;&gt;Capitelli refuses to support&lt;/a&gt; the adoption of a housing impact fee, which would provide millions of dollars in funding for affordable housing. Despite Capitelli’s refusal, the legislation passes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The issue of adopting an affordable housing impact fee first came before council on June 7th, 2011.  It was carried over to June 14th.  The issue of an impact fee had already been split into two parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Part 1) adopting an ordinance (which would be amending BMC section 22.20.065) establishing an affordable housing impact fee (just the policy piece)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Part 2) establishing the fee which was to be set at a later date, and whether this would apply to all new rental units, or those with 2 or more units (the details of the policy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There was no comment on this Consent Calendar vote on which Wozniak and  Capitelli abstained, and Wengraf voted no.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There were so many issues on the table about the ordinance and the actual fee that there was a desire for staff to do further analysis (See #3).  Setting the policy without the fee would be a feel good gesture, not thoughtful policy.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. July 2011: Capitelli &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ci.berkeley.ca.us/ContentPrint.aspx?id=62970&quot;&gt;votes to delay a public hearing&lt;/a&gt; on the issue of adopting the fee that would fund the new affordable units.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Council adopted in June 2011 an ordinance to set an affordable housing mitigation fee for new developments. The council at the time asked for staff to come back with information on the city’s fees as a whole for new development, before deciding on a fixed amount for the fee. Councilmember Arreguín decided to place on the council agenda for July 12, 2011 to have the council schedule a public hearing to decide on a fee of $34,000. He wanted to ensure a streamlined approach to setting the council fee. Mayor Bates and Councilmembers Maio, Moore, Capitelli, Wengraf, and Wozniak all had concerns about this fast approach.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;During the council discussion, each Councilmember expressed their concerns at not knowing the larger picture of all the proposed fees and their desire to wait until an already scheduled work session occurred on October 11, 2012. Laurie said (4:04:41) that he supports taking action to create affordable housing, but wants to do so with a full understanding of the overall impact of the many fees being considered- Transportation, Open Space, Childcare, and Affordable Housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We need to make informed decisions,” he said, adding, “We need to make policies that are about people, not about posturing.”  The item was amended to wait until after the workshop on October 11, 2011 to schedule any public hearing on setting a fee.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vote: Ayes – Maio, Moore, Capitelli, Wengraf, Wozniak, Bates; Noes – Arreguín, Worthington; Absent – Anderson.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. July 2012: Capitelli compares affordable housing to “chocolate fudge cake” &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lauriefacts.com/s/Laurie-Capitelli-Chocolate-Cake-Comment.pdf&quot;&gt;[PDF Transcript]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://berkeley.granicus.com/MediaPlayer.php?publish_id=911&quot;&gt;[Video]&lt;/a&gt;: and then &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cityofberkeley.info/ContentDisplay.aspx?id=88352%20&quot;&gt;opposes creation of the affordable housing fund again&lt;/a&gt;. The legislation still passes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Councilmember Arreguín insinuates that when Councilmember Capitelli made the analogy of comparing affordable housing to going to the store as a child with ten dollars, and buying a chocolate cake for $9.95, that he meant that affordable housing was a luxury.   He did not mean this – he was trying to make a point about budgeting priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Capitelli later acknowledged in the same meeting that the analogy might not have been apt, and apologized for it.  More importantly, the analogy was not meant to imply that affordable housing is a luxury, but rather that the affordable housing mitigation fee was the most eye-catching and important aspect, but not the only fee being considered.  In fact, he followed this comment by asking if the $28,000 fee prepared by the staff included other inclusionary fees, which it did not.  In sum, a more nuanced understanding of the chocolate cake comment should be that perhaps one shouldn’t spend the $9.95 on a cake which would only leave you 5 cents left- not that one shouldn’t spend a lot on a cake, and certainly not that one shouldn’t buy the cake at all.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As for the “no” vote, the motion on hand was not to approve the mitigation fee at that meeting, as Arreguín insinuates, but only to approve that a vote on the fee would appear on the agenda at the meeting in October.  Capitelli explicitly states that he would be prepared to vote on the fee given enough time to consider the implications and the other fees, which had yet to be decided at that meeting.  He also pledged to vote on it by the beginning of the December, only a month later than what Councilmember proposed.  Furthermore, the City Manager states that, “the timeline that Councilmember Capitelli identified is doable. Anything short of that could be problematic.  Unlike the affordable housing impact fee where we have an ordinance that was adopted…the other fees would have to create the necessary legislation to bring forward.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In the end, Capitelli, along with the council majority, did vote “yes” on a fee after the implications and other fees were dutifully considered.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor’s Note: As&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/10/27/top-contenders-for-berkeley-mayor-have-sharp-differences-towards-development/&quot;&gt;Berkeleyside&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;points out, Arreguín has cited lower mitigation fees—“developer giveaways,” in his words—as reasons for voting against housing projects. However, in the case of 2211 Harold Way, he voted for the original fee that was applied to all projects approved by the Zoning Adjustments Board (ZAB) up through October 2016.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Berkeleyside &lt;em&gt;also notes that Arreguín voted to support a total of 252 housing units, but voted ‘no’ or abstained on 935 units. Our count is higher. Below, we provide a map of all proposed projects in Berkeley that Arreguín has declined to support during his tenure on the City Council and ZAB.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/op-ed-capitelli-campaign-responds-to-lauriefactscom-attacks/jessehousingmap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-convergence-and-consolidation-in-san-francisco-real-estate/">
    <title type="text">Op-Ed: Convergence and Consolidation in San Francisco Real Estate</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:625cbb61-3c2b-3c92-9c42-cba17a64785a</id>
    <updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-convergence-and-consolidation-in-san-francisco-real-estate/" />
    <author>
      <name>Mike Ege</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Two new articles discuss interacting milestones in the global economy and local housing market, and how the fundamental problem of supply still remains.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;First, the bad news: on Thursday, the SF &lt;em&gt;Business Times&lt;/em&gt; published a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/2016/10/guest-opinion-sf-housing-future-nimby-rental.html?utm_content=buffere66a1&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_source=facebook.com&amp;amp;utm_campaign=buffer&quot;&gt;guest editorial&lt;/a&gt; by affordable housing developer John Stewart, discussing how the recent bump in unit production fails to put a meaningful dent in San Francisco's affordability problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;...As the Business Times reported last week, that’s resulted in a historic burst of housing, with an estimated 5,000 units to be completed this year. Unfortunately, this slope reversed direction just as quickly: Concord’s estimate of permit issuances for this year is approximately 3,000, meaning San Francisco will return to its low level of housing production.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In round numbers, the city of San Francisco has approximately 365,000 dwelling units of which two-thirds, or about 250,000 units are rental. Producing 3,000 unis a year (and San Francisco normally does even less) represents a modest 1.2 percent annual increase in rental inventory. When attrition and Ellis Act conversions are taken into account, we are barely better than replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;He then points to the slim pickings left in the pipeline: these include large-scale, long-timeline projects such as Treasure Island, Park Merced, Pier 70 and Schlage Lock, well away from the City center, and which continue to face considerable political and financial difficulties, all for “a little over 24,000 units.” It also includes another not quite 17,000 units in the neighborhoods, which while lower profile, also have lower percentages of affordable housing, and are more exposed to the City’s death-of-a-thousand-cuts discretionary permitting.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Stewart’s prognosis, particularly for renters, isn’t good: any drop in rents will come from lower demand, if at all.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, in San Francisco Magazine,  Kim-Mai Cutler has only &lt;a href=&quot;http://modernluxury.com/san-francisco/story/the-great-cooling&quot;&gt;slightly better news&lt;/a&gt; for prospective home buyers, mainly as a consequence of uncertainty over the throttling of economic growth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a dramatic slowdown. After all, employment levels are near all-time highs, as are rents and median housing prices. And inventory is still distressingly low: There are currently only about 400 single-family homes and 540 condos for sale in San Francisco, and both categories of housing spend an average of 49 days on the Bay Area market, according to Zillow—the lowest in the nation. But there’s an air of uncertainty over job production in the tech sector, which has for the past several years fueled much of the outlandish growth in housing prices in the Bay Area. “We’re thinking there will be a correction in the next couple of years, but we think it starts with the high end turning, and then it spreads [to slowing] job creation,” says UC Berkeley economist Kenneth Rosen, who has been studying Bay Area real estate markets for 37 years. “The key to the Bay Area depends on capital markets. The question is, will unicorns succeed and go public or have to cut back?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Cutler then outlines how ownership demand hasn’t declined so much as diffused - rippling out to the East Bay, driven in some measure by the increasing use of company shuttles by employers. The suburbs are no longer cheap. Barring economic catastrophe, lack of supply, along with little growth in salaries, means the affordability issues afflicting the Bay Area will still be with us.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The prime takeaway from these two articles is that the struggle to reform policy and community thinking about housing supply is far from over. Talk of San Francisco’s “historic burst” of housing production in 2013 ultimately remains a distraction from the fundamental supply and structural policy issues which define the region’s affordability crisis. Nobody is off the hook on this one.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/open-letter-recommendations-for-improving-the-residential-expansion-threshold/">
    <title type="text">Open Letter: Recommendations for Improving the Residential Expansion Threshold</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:83328248-a427-34a6-b18d-670071ae1ba4</id>
    <updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/open-letter-recommendations-for-improving-the-residential-expansion-threshold/" />
    <author>
      <name>Laura Fingal-Surma</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laura Fingal-Surma serves on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://progressnoe.com&quot;&gt;Progress Noe Valley&lt;/a&gt; Advisory Board.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Dear San Francisco Planning Department staff, President Fong, and Commissioners,&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We advocate on behalf of more than 200 neighbors who believe that Noe Valley’s brightest days are still ahead of us. We want more of what urban life has to offer and not less. The current housing affordability crisis moved us beyond frustration into action. As part of the growing Yes In My Back Yard movement, we believe that our neighborhood should be part of the solution and not the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The current Tantamount to Demolition policy is too open to interpretation and doesn’t work well for anyone, including those seeking residential expansions. Unclear policies create financial incentive for less scrupulous behavior and reward the wrong people. We applaud your &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf-planning.org/residential-expansion-threshold&quot;&gt;effort&lt;/a&gt; to tackle the complex problem of replacing the current policy with something better.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;That being said, any new process of reviewing residential expansion projects in neighborhoods like ours is a major opportunity for those who resist growth and change to create a new tool that locks out newcomers, artificially inflates property values, drives gentrification of lower income neighborhoods, and pushes new housing production to environmentally irresponsible locations. Other methods of obstruction are proving unsuccessful in the midst of the unprecedented housing crisis, so opponents of growth are shifting their focus to strict interpretations of scale and neighborhood compatibility. It is very concerning to see this NIMBY preoccupation with “scale” creeping in as the focus of an otherwise sensible reworking of flawed policy.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The evidence is clear. Even the Obama administration has weighed in, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/whitehouse.gov/files/images/Housing_Development_Toolkit%20f.2.pdf&quot;&gt;saying&lt;/a&gt; that overly restrictive land use policy is driving income inequality and dragging down the national economy. We are counting on you to prevent the new policy replacing Tantamount to Demolition from becoming just another tool of obstructionism. The Residential Expansion Threshold should be data-driven and rigorously tested against real-world data from past projects. While we trust that there are certainly completed projects that could have benefited from more sophisticated design review, we already have the Residential Design Guidelines to guide scale. If appropriate scale really must be reconsidered, evidence should first be compiled to demonstrate the flaws in the current policy.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Although intellectually interesting, it is pointless to define and debate the appropriate threshold to trigger a Planning Commission hearing in the abstract. In order to define the solution, we must first clearly define the problem. We encourage the Planning Department and Commission to identify numerous examples of past projects that would have ideally been modified had they been affected by the new process — and generate the policy from there. The policy should then be tested against a substantial set of additional past projects and revised until it achieves the desired outcomes before being implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We offer our more detailed input as bullet points.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt; 
&lt;strong&gt;IDEAS WE SUPPORT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;If not floor area ratio, square footage may very well be the best way to define the threshold as it is one of the most straightforward methods for objectively quantifying a building. However, even such a simple measurement is not entirely straightforward and can be manipulated. There should be clearly defined standards for how square footage is measured for this purpose, the calculations should be easily replicable, and Planning staff should spot check for compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many of the more ambitious residential projects that we need to grow and maintain our housing stock will inevitably face Discretionary Review. Approval timelines for such projects are already exceptionally long in San Francisco. Every opportunity should be explored to prevent the proposed new hearing from adding months to approvals for these projects — through parallelization, qualifying a significant percentage of affected projects for the consent calendar, and new monthly meeting dates dedicated to this type of hearing with not just theoretical but real limits on turnaround time. Time added to a project is also cost added, and hence housing cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AREAS OF CONCERN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The current proposal amounts to a doubling down on RH-1 zoning at exactly the time we should be questioning whether such zoning belongs in the city in the first place. Reducing allowable massing in RH-1 areas all but ensures that they will never evolve into RH-2 and RH-3 areas, with the “out of scale” massing requirements of multiunit buildings cited as the excuse. RH-1 zoning is so widespread that this significantly reduces the potential capacity of the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Earlier proposals incentivized maximization of principally permitted density — without penalizing multiunit projects constrained by outdated density controls that prevent them from taking full advantage of their buildable area before exceeding the threshold. An easy win-win solution would be for such a situation to trigger a relaxation of density controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Is the intention of any expansion threshold, such as 3000 ground square feet per unit, to incentivize production of new dwelling units — or to effectively ban units larger than the threshold? If not a de facto ban, the merits of which would be dubious, does the Planning Commission belong in the business of judging who is deserving of a larger unit? How could a fair process possibly be established to determine who is deserving? Regardless of the threshold, there will be many existing units larger than it, and there will be no test for purchasing one of those. If a reduction in allowable scale can be made objective enough to be fair, surely it can be performed administratively with Planning Commission oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In addition to the many concerns about introducing even more barriers to city living for families (that were well-represented at the September 22 hearing), a de facto ban on new larger units could amount to a handout to the wealthy owners of existing larger homes and units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We see aesthetic preferences for small scale living within the city as a much greater driver of housing scarcity than the occasional oversized unit occupying space that might have accommodated more households.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We strongly question the idea of neighborhood-specific thresholds that reinforce existing patterns of economic segregation and imply that, holding lot size constant, some neighborhoods are less responsible for accommodating growth than others. The scale of building expansions allowable under the Residential Design Guidelines is already context-specific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We are especially skeptical of any neighborhood-specific threshold determined by an average of the square footages of existing buildings. Records are simply not reliable, and they err significantly low:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is little reason to believe that the available square footage records were measured consistently in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;San Francisco is full of older residential buildings that have been modified and expanded without permits. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even when older buildings were expanded with permits, records do not always accurately reflect increased floor area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even if square footage records could be trusted, they are not in terms of gross square feet like the currently proposed threshold. An older unmodified single family home often features an entire floor plate of valuable garage and/or storage space that would not show up in any records.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Excluding historic district status, what entitles an underutilized neighborhood to stay that way indefinitely? Every individual parcel derives significant value from collective investment that should not be squandered. If a citywide threshold is not appropriate, a threshold based upon lot size would be equitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;If the goal is truly to generate more units per parcel and not to appease NIMBYs, carrots are better than sticks. Have the available carrots been thoroughly explored? For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can approvals be expedited for projects that achieve this objective rather than slowed for others?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At least in our neighborhood, there are clearly market forces driving production of large single family homes on RH-2 lots that could have otherwise become two units. Would that be happening if more (smaller) units were possible within the same massing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historically, existing larger homes were commonly subdivided during hard economic times to drive costs down. How can we enable this again?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is widely recognized that small units are more affordable by design. While we understand the concerns raised about “sham units,” we are even more concerned about discouraging production of new units through a top-down approach to the distribution of space between them. Each family and building is unique, and the sizes and configurations of units affected by the new policy should not be overly prescriptive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keeping a fixed amount of housing smaller and older is not an effective method for making housing more affordable, especially in the long term. Building more housing is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In reviewing the information available about the Residential Expansion Threshold, we see and hear a strong theme of moving toward a planning process that is more predictable, accountable, and easier to explain. We have confidence in you as professionals and leaders and are optimistic that this will remain a driving principle as the new policy takes shape.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Progress Noe Valley Advisory Board&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Read the original document &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BwIcMtCqttV2aEJuNVczMFc1TGhEMXdwNHpyVnNBZmtWZ2F3&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/at-civic-center-plaza-persecuted-groups-speak-out/">
    <title type="text">At Civic Center Plaza, Persecuted Groups Speak Out</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:0451dff2-5296-3eeb-9e2b-a48523707f1e</id>
    <updated>2016-10-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/at-civic-center-plaza-persecuted-groups-speak-out/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As I walked to my office from the Civic Center BART station, I took a detour to find the source of marching band music I heard off in the distance. Sure enough, a drumline was marching in front of a massive regimented marching band, flooding most of the pavement in front of City Hall with a sea of yellow uniforms and blaring horn music.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At the first intersection, I spotted young woman in semi-traditional Chinese garb waving robotically atop a parade float. Before I could ask someone what holiday it was, someone handed me a flier—in thick bold letters, it read: &lt;em&gt;Help Stop Forced Live Organ Harvesting from Falun Gong and Other Prisoners of Conscience in China.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/at-civic-center-plaza-persecuted-groups-speak-out/falungong.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Falun Gong protesters in Civic Center Plaza&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Practitioners of Falun Gong (a.k.a. Falun Dafa), a Chinese meditation discipline, have faced violent reprisals from the Chinese communist party since the late 1990s. The parade, one of several this month, sought to draw attention to recent allegations that Falun Gong imprisonment had been used as a source of living organ donors freely exploited by the Chinese government.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This demonstration served as a bookend of sorts, after a weekend of parades and a Falun Gong &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theepochtimes.com/n3/2176742-falun-gong-experience-sharing-conference-held-in-san-francisco/&quot;&gt;conference&lt;/a&gt; held yesterday at the Bill Graham Civic Auditorium.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/at-civic-center-plaza-persecuted-groups-speak-out/protest-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Over 200,000 People Have Filed Lawsuits Against Former Chinese Dictator Jiang Zemin&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Across the street, on the steps in front of the California Superior Court, an entirely different demonstration had formed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The US PROStitutes Collective (US PROS), partnering with the Erotic Service Providers Union, the Transgender Law Center, and a member of Amnesty International, staged a protest against the arrest of Backpage.com CEO Carl Ferrer. Ferrer, founder of the paid classified service that allows sex workers to advertise their services, was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2016/10/07/497006100/ceo-of-backpage-com-arrested-charged-with-pimping&quot;&gt;arrested&lt;/a&gt; in Houston on pimping charges after three years of undercover investigations by the California Department of Justice.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Much of the crowd’s ire was directed at California’s Attorney General Kamala Harris, who many expect to win the race for U.S. Senator. “You’re ahead in the polls,” one protestor said through a megaphone, “you don’t need to persecute us with this publicity stunt for political gain.” Many signs and chants pointed to a lack of services and safety for sex workers, which criminalization would only further exacerbate.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/at-civic-center-plaza-persecuted-groups-speak-out/protest5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;I Can Not Believe I Have To Protest This Shit&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I can’t believe I have to protest this shit!” a protester chanted.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It’s digital segregation,” another demonstrator said. “When will we be allowed to join the modern age?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;One demonstrator who declined to identify themselves insisted that online advertising was essential for sex workers to feel safe in conducting business.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It will kill free speech to pursue this as a criminal case,” the demonstrator continued, asserting that the alleged victims in the Backpage.com trafficking case could have more easily sought a settlement for damages in civil court.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The demonstrator reinforced the crowd’s general sentiment that the prosecution efforts were all for show, and were unlikely to succeed. “He’s got really solid case law supporting him,” she said of Ferrer. “Beyond that, what they really want is to displace us from our work, making it harder to advertise. Back in the days of Craigslist is free—so the whole idea that they’re making money off of it, that’s because we can no longer advertise for free. You take away that, and our safety is on a slippery slope.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The original arrest warrant &lt;a href=&quot;https://oag.ca.gov/system/files/attachments/press_releases/signed%20dec%20for%20arrest%20warrant%20pdf_Redacted.pdf?&quot;&gt;confirms&lt;/a&gt; that Backpage classifieds emerged directly after the closure of Cragislist’s “Adult” section. Ferrer has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://oag.ca.gov/system/files/attachments/press_releases/File%20endorsed%20Criminal%20Complaint%20tjy_Redacted.pdf?&quot;&gt;charged&lt;/a&gt; with a total of ten separate counts of pimping.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Members of the Erotic Service Providers Union also discussed an ongoing lawsuit against the Attorney General’s office seeking to overturn California’s anti-prostitution law by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://esplerp.org&quot;&gt;Erotic Service Providers Legal Education Research Project (ESPLERP)&lt;/a&gt;. In a motion to dismiss the suit, Harris &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonblade.com/2016/01/22/marriage-ruling-cited-in-brief-to-overturn-prostitution-law/&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; that “[t]here is no fundamental right to engage in prostitution or to solicit prostitution,” a statement that has inflamed the sex worker rights community. Harris has previously &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.laweekly.com/news/a-new-movement-to-legalize-prostitution-faces-a-fight-with-kamala-harris-5570911&quot;&gt;stated&lt;/a&gt; that sex work “compromises the quality of life in a community.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Several members of ESPLERP noted a particular irony in the Attorney General’s perceived crusade against sex workers. These demonstrators alleged that Harris had dubbed herself an “honorary prostitute” in an attempt to “pander” to sex worker advocates at the Harvey Milk LGBT Democratic Club in 2007, when she was running for reelection as the San Francisco District Attorney.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“If Kamala Harris really cared about protecting women, she would investigate Bay Area police departments, which have a long history of systematically exploiting and extorting sex workers,&quot; ESPLERP's Claire Alwyne said in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://esplerp.org/sex-workers-outraged-at-backpage-charges/&quot;&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/at-civic-center-plaza-persecuted-groups-speak-out/protest1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Demonstration in front of California Superior Court, 400 McAllister St, San Francisco&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite identifying myself as a member of the press, I was eventually drafted into joining the protestors. I was given a sign reading “Stop Taxpayer Funded Witch Hunts,” and there are likely many pictures and videos of me standing in the back row, looking supportive of the cause (I hope) but unsure if I belonged up there.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I stood next to &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfist.com/2010/03/04/bisexual_sex_worker_starchild_runni.php&quot;&gt;Starchild&lt;/a&gt;, a local sex worker advocate and Libertarian Party member, as he chanted impromptu slogans into a megaphone. Starchild urged participants to view the arrest as a threat to internet privacy and net neutrality, not just workers' rights.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“First they come for the sex workers. Then it could be the LGBT community. Who’s next?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The crowd repeated after him: “who’s next?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-forward-blasts-subterfuge-by-impersonator-pac/">
    <title type="text">Palo Alto Forward Blasts Subterfuge by 'Impersonator' PAC</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:2a5fd0ba-2865-3308-8c5d-eef407c5cb75</id>
    <updated>2016-10-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-forward-blasts-subterfuge-by-impersonator-pac/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Members of the unincorporated housing advocacy group Palo Alto Forward were shocked to find filings for a Political Action Committee (PAC) under their name last week, which could set back their ongoing efforts to register as a 501(c)(3) non-profit. The PAC was registered by Timothy Gray, treasurer for the City Council campaign of Lydia Kou.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Gray claimed in an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paloaltoonline.com/news/2016/10/24/palo-alto-forward-claims-impersonation-after-its-name-is-registered-as-a-pac&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;em&gt;Palo Alto Weekly&lt;/em&gt; that he had no knowledge of the preexisting Palo Alto Forward, and that he registered the name to prevent citizens from being “duped.” Gray claims, paradoxically, that he was not aware of Palo Alto Forward’s activities, and that he registered the PAC name after the city had registered paloaltoforward.org to conduct community outreach for its Comprehensive Plan back in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sandra Slater, co-founder of Palo Alto Forward, called Gray’s claims “patently ridiculous,” given that Gray had co-signed a letter opposing the group last year. Gray registered the PAC within days of formally registering as the treasurer of Lydia Kou’s city council campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Until recently, Gray served as treasurer of Palo Altans for Sensible Zoning (PASZ), a PAC that formed opposition to a 2013 ballot measure that would have rezoned for greater residential density on Maybell Avenue, and has endorsed Kou in this election cycle. Lydia Kou’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lydiakou.com/about_me&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; boasts of the candidate’s direct involvement in defeating the referendum, known as Measure D:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Faced with an uncompromising Council, I became one of the leaders of the group that put the issue on the ballot. I knew from listening to residents that there was widespread opposition to the project, but to confirm that, I had my neighborhood association conduct a survey of its membership and subsequently authorize funding a petition drive to have a referendum on the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kou told the &lt;em&gt;Weekly&lt;/em&gt; that she was unaware of Gray’s PAC registration until recently. She asserts that he told her he was “trying to ensure the city of Palo Alto is not inadvertently being misled by an organization taking a domaine [sic] that the city has used.” Gray also claimed that Palo Alto Forward had been “under investigation for violation of reporting rules”—something Slater vehemently denies. Such allegations, Slater pointed out, further undermine his claim that he had not heard of the group.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Slater added that Gray had never contacted Palo Alto Forward to raise any concerns that the name was deceptive. Palo Alto Forward had communicated with the city before launching their own website, ensuring that Palo Alto had taken down paloaltoforward.org as legally required in 2014, after the Comprehensive Plan referendum measure was placed on the ballot.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We have never taken money from anyone, and we certainly have not spent money on electioneering or politics - just community education following the rules for 501c3 non-profits,” Palo Alto Forward said in a press release. Further:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We have NEVER been “under investigation for violation of reporting rules.”
We are trying to register as 501(c)(3) and this hurts our ability to do so because they're not supposed to be involved in political efforts and PAF isn't. We don't take in any money from outside sources and we don't spend any on political campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I buy all the refreshments for our meetings,” Slater added in a phone interview. “I pick up fruit, soda, cheese, and crackers, because we know people will be hungry when they leave work and we want them to be able to focus on the issues we’re discussing. We’re entirely about community education. I host many events at my house, and some at the public library, which is all free.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lydia Kou’s council campaign, along with that of Arthur Keller, recently made &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paloaltoonline.com/news/2016/10/14/large-checks-boost-campaigns-of-kou-keller#comment_form&quot;&gt;headlines&lt;/a&gt; for receiving over $30,000 each in contributions from a small number of residents.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kou, a local realtor, pays property taxes on a $1 million assessed value of her home, though the average sale price in the neighborhood is $2.5 million (lower than Palo Alto’s median home price of $4 million). Public tax records show she did not claim a homeowner’s exemption on filings over the past two years. The &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; has launched an ongoing investigation to ensure that Kou’s primary residence is in fact in Palo Alto, as local election laws require.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/south-bay-stoner-titans-sleep-triumph-at-the-warfield/">
    <title type="text">South Bay Stoner Titans SLEEP Triumph at The Warfield</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:65ddd43f-5588-3174-bc8c-a3936edfdb0d</id>
    <updated>2016-10-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/south-bay-stoner-titans-sleep-triumph-at-the-warfield/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, last Friday night at the Warfield would have been unthinkable. San Jose’s stoner-metal heroes Sleep were historic legends, their few albums revered as untouchable classics while the trio splintered into newer, heavier projects. But returns in the market for classic metal albums churn out slower than their songs, and over 20 years after disbanding, the band has found the audience that was always waiting for them.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Hearing the sheer force of air pressure that is their songs, it’s hard to believe the masses weren’t ready for Sleep in the early ‘90s. The trio of Al Cisneros, Matt Pike, and Chris Hakius split up in 1995 after major label London Records refused to release their “unmarketable” hour-long dirge, &lt;em&gt;Dopesmoker.&lt;/em&gt; Those record executives may have been embarrassed to see how many fans were willfully subjecting themselves to whiplash at the Warfield as they played a relatively brief, half-hour snippet of the tune.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Brandishing joints and glass pipes that filled the air with a psychedelic scent, legions chanted along with Cisneros:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Drrrop out of life&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;with BONG&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;IN&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;HAAAAAAAAAND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hIw7oeZKpZc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

Opening act Helen Money, an enormously talented solo cellist, hardly needed to mention the debt her sound owed to Sleep. Augmented with distortion and loop pedals, her strings filled the air with a thundering, metallic roar. 

“It’s really an honor” she said of her role in the short tour. The honor was equally ours in getting to see her take up the mantle of stoner-metal pioneer with such aplomb, with her own neoclassical twist.


&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cQCO-opZKBc?list=PLN3lgHnAvXz5j8_JiJq8GQLvOrpp-tbOh&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Until recently, Sleep remained in relative obscurity, their records hungrily sought-after by the niche crowd adoring “stoner metal,” “stoner doom,” “sludge,” really all the drug-laced sub-sub-genres that trace their lineage directly back to Black Sabbath’s first three albums. (One of Sleep’s songs “Inside the Sun” is not so much an homage or blatant rip-off as it is a deliberate sequel, lyrically and musically, to Black Sabbath’s “Into the Void” from 1971.) The legend seeped into some cult films—Harmony Korrine famously used “Dragonaut” for a sequence in his experimental collage &lt;em&gt;Gummo&lt;/em&gt;, and Jim Jarmusch sampled “Dopesmoker” in &lt;em&gt;Broken Flowers.&lt;/em&gt; But their influence spread like an adaptive mutation that strengthened the musical species.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sleep’s monolithic status in the metal pantheon stretches beyond the human members, who kept on being pioneers long after the group folded. Al Cisneros and Chris Hakius formed Om, initially just a drum-bass duo distilling Sleep’s slow-blues into a yoga meditation soundtrack. Matt Pike now leads a faster, more aggressive group, High On Fire, which still regularly tours the country. In the seven years since their initial reunion, as Sleep continues to headline festivals worldwide and prepare to release new music, it’s as though they never left.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sleep added one new song to their set, and a mere three songs from their perennial classic &lt;em&gt;Holy Mountain.&lt;/em&gt; The record is a testament to their underground popularity, originally an unsolicited demo tape that was released by Earache Records virtually as soon as they received it. The titular track, drawing cheers when the audience recognized its one-chord riff, was played at roughly a third of the speed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Guitarist Matt Pike, barechested as always, oozed sheer volume that could silence a jet engine. His lightspeed-blues solos, showing equal influence from Black Sabbath and Ravi Shankar, explored some quieter, subtler terrain sometimes.  Bassist Al Cisneros sang in a higher, more meditative register typical of his band Om, where he applies Sleep’s THC-drenched technique to forms inspired by Islamic and Buddhist ritual. By the end of a crushing, monumental 90 minutes, the audience was fully entranced.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y4cxaVEqZsE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While “Holy Mountain” was merely a slower, heavier interpretation of the original, “Dragonaut” took on a new life as Pike noodled through the iconic guitar lick with the drunken abandon of an early blues musician.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The line isn’t really that bad,” someone said as the crowd staggered slowly out the Warfield’s gilded doors. “It’s just everyone’s so fuckin’ high.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;True, audience members had passed me several joints—and I was up in the balcony seats. I briefly wondered how Stravinsky’s “Rite of Spring” would have fared had it debuted here, at the Warfield in San Francisco, October 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I could see plumes of smoke from below, eventually resembling a miniature diorama of a 19th century British coal town. I felt transported not so much to the past, when my fellow suburban teenagers and I would gather in secret to worship at the altar of Sleep and street-grade marijuana, but to an eternal present, a “riff-filled land” as Cisneros says. A land where the riffs never end because they’re slow enough to last forever.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo courtesy of Argyris Zymnis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/video-yimby-party-rally-for-radical-inclusivity/">
    <title type="text">Video: YIMBY Party Rally for Radical Inclusivity</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:fb9a3ce8-6d38-3bd3-941c-ca94417f23e7</id>
    <updated>2016-10-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/video-yimby-party-rally-for-radical-inclusivity/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Watch on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Periscope?src=hash&quot;&gt;#Periscope&lt;/a&gt;: Speeches &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tdfischer_&quot;&gt;@tdfischer_&lt;/a&gt; and Jesse Oliver and Scott wiener against erasing queers in tech &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/ZM7GxULmNS&quot;&gt;https://t.co/ZM7GxULmNS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; SF Yimby Party (@SFyimby) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SFyimby/status/790698128374534144&quot;&gt;October 24, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/bay-area-think-tank-ranks-policies-that-help-or-hurt-housing-affordability/">
    <title type="text">Bay Area Think Tank Ranks Policies That Help or Hurt Housing Affordability</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:74f0739d-5a8f-3e6e-8079-b61165fc19dd</id>
    <updated>2016-10-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/bay-area-think-tank-ranks-policies-that-help-or-hurt-housing-affordability/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Bay Area Council Economic Institute (BACEI), a local think tank focused on economic and policy issues, released a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bayareaeconomy.org/files/pdf/BACEI_Housing_10_2016.pdf&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; detailing the top 20 policies that impact affordability in the city of San Francisco. The analysis considers affordability based on meeting the conventional 30% of income metric, ranking policies based on their net impact to affordability.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policies That Help Affordability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The report finds that policies influencing supply are the most helpful, either by directly increase the housing supply or accelerating the increase of housing production.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The single most important contributor to affordability, according to the analysis, is expediting the completion of major developments. Large projects such as those slated for Treasure Island, Hunter’s Point, Park Merced, and Mission Rock, together represent over 25,000 units in the pipeline, of which over 6,000 will be below-market rate. The policy overlay relates largely to ballot initiatives. The Mission Rock development, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/City_of_San_Francisco_Mission_Rock_Development_Initiative,_Proposition_D_(November_2015&quot;&gt;required voter input in 2015&lt;/a&gt;) to increase the area’s height limits, since an earlier proposition prevented the city from allowing development on Port property from exceeding 40 feet unless voters approved the increase.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/bay-area-think-tank-ranks-policies-that-help-or-hurt-housing-affordability/missionrock.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rendering of Mission Rock&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Other supply-based policies the think tank reports will help include streamlining local approval of housing, easing building restrictions, legalizing accessory dwelling units, or ADUs, and facilitating of micro-units.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many of these have received attention at the state level, with varying degrees of success. Governor Jerry Brown proposed legislation earlier this year to streamline infill projects that contain a portion of affordable units, creating a “by right” process for those development proposals. According to the BACEI report, though it was never voted on, the policy would create 16,594 new market-rate units and decrease prices by 5.94%, which would make housing affordable in the technical sense, at 30% of income or less, to more than 11,000 households.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Then there are those policies that tackle affordability more directly, such as affordable housing density bonus programs and funding for below-market rate housing. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/San_Francisco_Creation_of_a_Housing_Trust_Fund,_Proposition_C_(November_2012&quot;&gt;Proposition C&lt;/a&gt;), which passed in 2012, created a Housing Trust fund to invest in affordable housing. The city estimates that this fund will help develop 9,000 permanently affordable units, assuming developers leverage the money with government subsidies such as the Low-Income Housing Tax Credits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policies That Hurt Affordability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, policies that reduce affordability are somewhat more varied in nature, running the gamut from building and zoning restrictions, to homesharing bans, to increased impact fees, and at the top of the list, the elimination of rent control.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The elimination of rent control is particularly noteworthy, given the abundance of economic literature on the negative consequences of rent control, which BACEI acknowledges. However, while ending rent control would result in a small supply shock, this would be massively outweighed by the loss of affordable units. The conversion of a rent-controlled unit to market-rate doesn’t inherently mean the household in question will no longer have an affordable home, since household income must also be accounted for. As a proxy for this information, BACEI applies 10%, based on the percentage of renters paying between 25% and 29% of their rent in 1998, to the number of total rent controlled units to tabulate the number of affordable units that would be lost - 17,200.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/bay-area-think-tank-ranks-policies-that-help-or-hurt-housing-affordability/1515-svn_progress-renderings-2-page-002.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rendering of 1515 South Van Ness, a project with 25% Below Market Rate units bitterly opposed by some Mission District residents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Other harmful policies discussed are construction moratoria in the Mission district, including both a hypothetical indefinite ban on market-rate housing and the 18 month halt proposed by last year’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/Moratorium-on-new-Mission-District-housing-is-6609187.php&quot;&gt;Proposition I&lt;/a&gt;, which was soundly defeated by voters in November. However, if land use controls were changed to indefinitely prohibit market rate housing from being built in the Mission, it would result in over 11,000 households being unable to afford housing in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Inclusionary zoning requirements codified by this year’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/&quot;&gt;Proposition C&lt;/a&gt; also rank high on the list of measures that reduce housing affordability. The report notes that requiring developers to include 25% of units as BMR would increase the number of affordable units in &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; projects, but it would cause the overall housing supply to fall by 25% and end up raising prices by 3.5%. As a result, around 7,500 households would shift into an unaffordable housing situation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The report demonstrates the critical role played by policy in housing affordability, and may offer policymakers guidance on how to shape housing affordability legislation going forward, or at least provide the considerations necessary to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/sunset-district-small-businesses-rally-against-prop-m/">
    <title type="text">Sunset District Small Businesses Rally Against Prop M</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:ff6e053d-2c4e-3608-8711-023d2385f637</id>
    <updated>2016-10-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/sunset-district-small-businesses-rally-against-prop-m/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Business owners gathered with local politicians on a foggy corner in the Sunset District, brandishing signs opposing Proposition M, a charter amendment that could disperse the mayor’s economic policymaking powers if approved by voters.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, Supervisor Aaron Peskin &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/stakeholders-search-for-common-ground-in-land-use-debate/&quot;&gt;boasted&lt;/a&gt; to J.K. Dineen of the &lt;em&gt;Chronicle&lt;/em&gt; that the new commission Prop M would create, a full restructuring of the current Mayor’s Offices of Housing (MOH) and Economic and Workforce Development (OEWD), would have the power to streamline housing production. Supervisor Scott Wiener later countered that Prop M’s main sponsors, namely Peskin and Supervisor Jane Kim, had opposed his legislation to streamline approvals for 100% Below Market Rate housing projects.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Wiener, joined by Supervisor Katy Tang on the windy sidewalk in front of Uncle Benny’s Donuts, scarcely mentioned housing at today’s press conference. Tang had gathered supporters there to begin a “merchant’s walk” along commercial corridors in her District, to distribute literature and window signs in opposition to Prop M. Speaking to reporters, Tang decried the measure’s efforts to “recombine” two entirely separate offices under one commission with disparate appointments.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“This does not make sense. We need to do whatever it is we can to support our small businesses in the most effective and efficient ways possible, so please vote No on M.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We elect the mayor to manage the executive departments,” Supervisor Wiener added. “If the mayor does a poor job, or the agencies do a poor job, the mayor can get defeated in the election, and that’s why we elect a mayor. These measures—D, H, L, and M—are all designed to strip power away from the mayor, to make offices of the mayor weaker, and decentralize power to the point where no one is accountable to the voters for anything.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2FNoDHLM%2Fvideos%2F375235142819227%2F&amp;show_text=0&amp;width=400&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowTransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/judge-dismisses-berkeley-high-rise-lawsuit/">
    <title type="text">Judge Dismisses Berkeley High-Rise Lawsuit</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:50488533-f6a2-3c44-b94b-42e0772fc797</id>
    <updated>2016-10-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/judge-dismisses-berkeley-high-rise-lawsuit/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;East Bay news source &lt;em&gt;Berkeleyside&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/10/20/judge-tosses-out-legal-challenge-to-berkeley-high-rise/&quot;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; that a lawsuit filed against the proposed development at 2211 Harold Way, approved by the Berkeley City Council late last year, has been dismissed by Alameda County Judge Frank Roesch. Plaintiffs Kelly Hammargren and James Hendry, unable and unwilling (respectively) to bring legal counsel, were found lacking in substantive arguments to stall the development under terms of the California Environmental Quality Act (CEQA). The judge &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/2211-Harold-Way_Order-Denying-Petitions-for-Writ.pdf&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; that none of the 15 claims Hammargren brought were valid in undermining the authority of the project’s approved Environmental Impact Review (EIR).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Hammargren and Hendry provided the following objections to the project’s EIR, which the judge summarily dismissed as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Factually speaking, the record does not support this claim. &lt;em&gt;—Judge Roesch, in a response to one claim that essentially applies to all of them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The plaintiffs contended that developers had not adequately studied the effect of “extremely hazardous substances” on the nearby Berkeley City College and Berkeley High School campuses. Hammargren contended that CEQA required separate meetings with school officials to conduct such studies. Roesch disagreed, writing: “Ms. Hammargren’s suggestion that separate ‘school studies’ were required is unsupported by any authority,” and that the EIR had adequately analyzed impacts to neighboring buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Hammargren’s brief further argued that the city had surreptitiously avoided any environmental review regarding the schools because Harold Way had been improperly classified as “infill.”  This claim rested on the plaintiff’s assertion that infill development requires on-site affordable housing, whereas Harold Way will instead contribute $10.5 million to Berkeley’s Housing Trust Fund. Judge Roesch writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ms. Hammargren cites no authority for the proposition that a residential project may not be built unless it includes low income housing or that the building of market rate housing alone is in violation of CEQA or any other state statute or section of the municipal code. Her argument therefore lacks merit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;According to Hammargren, the EIR completely omitted any evaluation of earthquake safety on part of the project site. This categorically dismisses a significant part of the EIR. The plaintiff, Roesch writes, “is factually incorrect in her assertion that the issue of seismic impacts was ignored…The EIR reports that all fill soils will be removed from the site during excavation and that such removal will eliminate potential seismic hazards.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Plaintiffs argued that 2211 Harold Way exceeded downtown Berkeley’s 180-foot height limits by 5 feet. The judge found that the project was carefully designed to remain within the exceptions specified by Berkeley’s Municipal Code (BMC): “the project height of 180 feet plus five foot high parapet
complies with zoning requirements… Accordingly, the project does not violate the height limitations of the BMC (and in fact appears to have been carefully designed to be within the City’s height restrictions).”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A proposed alternative, according to Hammargren, was rejected by the City due to a finding of financial feasibility which she claims was based on an inaccurate reporting of land costs. “The record of findings indicates that financial feasibility was only one of several findings that supported City’s rejection of the Preservation Alternative. Even assuming, counterfactually, that financial feasibility was the sole reason City rejected this alternative, the July 2015' pro forma to which Ms. Hammargren refers was not the only information on which the City based its determination of financial infeasibility.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Hammargren claims that the EIR did not conduct a “mandatory” study of the project’s impacts on sewage infrastructure. According to the judge, the plaintiff “argues that the EIR does not contain any site-specific analysis of the project’s sewage impact. This is incorrect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The final claim the judge addresses contends that the nearly 60 year-old Hinks building, adjacent to the historically landmarked Shattuck Hotel, was improperly slated for demolition. Roesch writes that the Berkeley Municipal Code did indeed allow for demolition of certain historical landmarks. The City’s actions, including a decision by the Landmarks and Preservation commission, “entirely undercut Ms. Hammergren’s argument that the Hinks Building is historical landmark that may not be demolished.” Roesch continues: “The City has complied with the requirements under its ordinance to demolish landmarked building and Ms. Hammargren has made no argument that such findings were not properly made.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Hammargren and Hendry have 60 days to file an appeal, and have told &lt;em&gt;Berkeleyside&lt;/em&gt; that they have not yet decided if they will do so.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/stakeholders-search-for-common-ground-in-land-use-debate/">
    <title type="text">Stakeholders Search for Common Ground in Land-Use Debate</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:7e74110f-f0b1-3ea0-b068-565058b6a52d</id>
    <updated>2016-10-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/stakeholders-search-for-common-ground-in-land-use-debate/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On Monday evening, The Swedish American Hall was packed to the rafters with civic-minded San Franciscans. Hosted by Planning Commissioner Dennis Richards and Enrique Landa, the night’s debate featured a number of local ballot measures related to land use as understood by district supervisors, community activists, and other representative stakeholders. &lt;em&gt;BAMO&lt;/em&gt; reports the highlights (and lowlights) below.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prop M - Aaron Peskin Takes On...SF Chronicle Reporter J.K. Dineen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Aaron Peskin was slated to debate Supervisor Scott Wiener on Prop M, a measure to create a new commission to oversee two more new commissions (seriously), but scheduling conflicts for both parties got in the way. Instead, Peskin responded to questions from moderator J.K. Dineen, a reporter for the &lt;em&gt;SF Chronicle&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Peskin, no amateur rhetorician, started with an exercise in exclusivity: “If you think everything is working when it comes to housing in this city, don’t vote for Prop M.” The process today is too opaque, Peskin asserted, and excludes the community. Prop M would make the creation of new housing more transparent, and the D3 supervisor went as far as arguing that the bureaucratic measure would “streamline the process.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Interesting,” Mr. Dineen replied, prompting laughter from the venue.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly, the broader batch of measures DHLM came up, which are designed to pull power away from the mayor’s office. Peskin said we should vote yes on all of them, citing the Planning Commission as an example of a governing body that functions better when executive authority is limited. Lastly, Peskin didn’t miss a chance to take aim at Ron Conway, who has helped finance opposition to DHLM, and closed with a call to “Follow the Money”.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Scott Wiener arrived later in the night, facing J.K. Dineen’s attempt at “channeling” Aaron Peskin. Dineen asked Wiener how he responded to the notion that housing process happens in “dark, smoky rooms…” evocative of the “opaque” process Peskin described earlier. Wiener responded that measures to debilitate the mayor’s office, including D, H, and L, are “incredibly cynical” and not good government. An independent commission to oversee housing and development, such as the one proposed by Prop M, would slow down the construction of new housing, not speed it up as Peskin suggested.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Wiener also pointed out that supporters of Prop M had opposed his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Affordable-housing-legislation-goes-to-Supes-6504387.php&quot;&gt;legislation&lt;/a&gt; to remove conditional use requirements for 100% affordable housing developments, a proposal that would directly speed up the process of building affordable housing. The audienc seemed especially receptive to this point.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;BAMO&lt;/em&gt; awards this round to Supervisor Wiener.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/stakeholders-search-for-common-ground-in-land-use-debate/debate3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jane Kim (left), Tim Colen (right), Kim-Mai Cutler (far right)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prop X - District 6 Supervisor Jane Kim Makes a Case for PDR Against SFHAC Executive Director Tim Colen’s Call for More Housing, Period&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In the second round, moderated by Kim-Mai Cutler, Jane Kim made some fairly compelling points about the need to protect PDR space, a land use category that stands for “Production/Distribution/Repair” and covers things like auto repair, small manufacturing, and arts activities. Prop X would do two things: 1) require a conditional use authorization for demolition of a PDR space, and 2) require the developer to replace a portion of the space with PDR.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kim argued that her district has lost 970,000 square feet of PDR space in the past five years, which represents a substantial amount of middle-income jobs, especially for those without college degrees. Kim didn’t necessarily address the point that this would increase the cost of building housing, but argued that without government intervention, the market would dictate the building of market-rate housing and office space only, since those use-types command the highest profits. Arts and manufacturing spaces, like those covered by PDR, yield lower returns and would not be represented if it were left up to the market alone.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Tim Colen, Executive Director of SFHAC, rebutted that the city has already planned for the loss of PDR, quite literally, in its &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf-planning.org/sites/default/files/FileCenter/Documents/3991-EN_Final-EIR_Part-1_Intro-Sum.pdf&quot;&gt;Eastern Neighborhood Plan&lt;/a&gt;. According to Colen, the Mission and SoMa districts are pretty much “on schedule” in their projected loss of PDR space. Further, complex land use decisions should not be made by voters, particularly when no analysis of the PDR requirement has been performed. Prop X is “designed to restrict the construction of market-rate housing,” Colen argued, and would lead to underutilized sites like warehouses and parking lots remaining unproductive. A better model would be that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/100-Hooper-site-acquired-for-complex-to-house-6371561.php&quot;&gt;used by the City College of Arts at 100 Hooper&lt;/a&gt;, a hybrid development model with higher floors subsidizing ground floor PDR, rather than the developer.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kim acknowledged that the legislation could be amended by a two-thirds vote from the Board of Supervisors, and a BMR-like model with in-lieu fees or off-site development as options might come in trailing legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;BAMO&lt;/em&gt; acknowledges the need for some level of PDR protection, but recommends a No vote on Prop X.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/stakeholders-search-for-common-ground-in-land-use-debate/debate1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angelo King (left) and Calvin Welch (right), moderated by Joe Fitz Rodriguez (far right) - &lt;em&gt;courtesy: Brian Hanlon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prop O:  Angelo King Defends Hunter’s Point Development Against Calvin Welch Finger Wagging&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The most unexpected performance of the night came from someone who wasn’t even supposed to be there, with Prop O supporter Angelo King taking the place of Former Supervisor Sophie Maxwell of District 10.  King faced off with Calvin Welch in defense of Prop O, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfgov.org/elections/sites/default/files/Documents/candidates/Office%20Development%20in%20Candlestick%20Point%20and%20Hunters%20Point%20Legal%20Text.pdf&quot;&gt;somewhat complicated&lt;/a&gt; result of previous ballot initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Prop O must be understood in the context of the city’s 1986 ballot measure, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/S-F-law-blocks-tech-boom-expansion-5652707.php&quot;&gt;Prop M&lt;/a&gt;, which restricted the amount of approved office space in a year to 950,000 square feet. In 2008, Prop G passed, which “would establish city policy to encourage timely development” of Hunter’s Point. In line with Prop G, the city wants to move forward with redevelopment of the area, but in order to do so has to exempt the project from Prop M’s 950k sq. ft cap.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Welch argued that the area is that only 3 million square feet have been subject to environmental review, with the remaining 2 million getting a free pass at approval. Welch also voiced major concerns about the lack of transit to this area, pointing out the an additional 40,000 transit trips per day would be added as a result of the new office space. He called Prop O “the wrong measure in the wrong part of the world at the wrong time.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;King had strong rebuttals lined up. First, the developer (Lennar) is entitled to 3 million square feet of the land only, and there is no automatic trigger of the additional 2 million. This would require approval from the Office of Community Investment and Infrastructure. King further explained the transit issue as a chicken-and-egg problem, since transit won’t necessarily come before an area is developed. We wouldn’t expect SFMTA to build “five bus lanes to nowhere”. The project is a thirty-year plan, Angelo reminded Welch; it is not going to happen tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As a resident of the district himself, Angelo’s remarks were particularly persuasive, especially given Welch’s insistence that this project did not represent “community” development.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Calvin huffed and puffed, but it was Angelo who brought the house down Monday night.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/stakeholders-search-for-common-ground-in-land-use-debate/debate2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leah Pimentel (left) and Peter Cohen (right) - &lt;em&gt;courtesy: Brian Hanlon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prop U - Leah Pimentel Appeals to the Need for Middle Income Housing Opposite Peter Cohen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The city’s inclusionary housing program is designed primarily to reserve units for low-income residents, or those making around half of the area median income (“AMI”). Prop U would open the BMR system to middle income households, or those earning up to 110% of AMI.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Leah Pimentel, arguing in favor of Prop U, shared her personal middle class story in San Francisco, recounting holidays characterized by “over-time” and “time-and-a-half”. Prop U would give families like hers, who make “a little too much,” a chance to stay in San Francisco. Peter Cohen, an affordable housing organization director, countered that Prop U was not an “additive” program, but would instead take housing away from low-income households who need it the most. Cohen added that the city has offered middle income households relief in the form of down payment assistance from last year’s Prop A bond.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;BAMO&lt;/em&gt; sides with Peter Cohen on this one - Prop U is not good affordable housing policy.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/dark-money-from-subsidized-real-estate-faces-calls-for-investigation/">
    <title type="text">Housing Non-Profit Under Investigation for Dark Money Politics</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:c25038dd-fc22-3214-bb46-c04e661598e0</id>
    <updated>2016-10-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/dark-money-from-subsidized-real-estate-faces-calls-for-investigation/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last month, we &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/is-a-nonprofit-developer-laundering-money-to-local-campaigns/&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; on a city ethics complaint against John Elberling, director of the affordable housing developer TODCO Group, LLC. Elberling is accused of funneling money from his subsidized rental assets through another LLC, the Yerba Buena Neighborhood Consortium (YNBC), to fund political campaigns. In an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Pre-election-opening-for-Warm-Springs-BART-looks-9981990.php&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;em&gt;Chronicle&lt;/em&gt;, Elberling largely admitted to doing so, and argued that nothing illegal or unethical had occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Not everyone agrees with Elberling. Supervisor Mark Farrell released a press statement today, calling for a federal investigation into YNBC, labeled a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_money&quot;&gt;dark money&lt;/a&gt; shell entity” for contributing $375,000 to local ballot measure campaigns in 2016. YNBC’s election mailer was a driving force behind the campaign to pass Proposition C in June, an increase in Below Market Rental requirements for private development co-sponsored by Supervisors Jane Kim and Aaron Peskin.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Profiting from taxpayer subsidy and funneling those profits into local political campaigns is reprehensible,” Farrell said in his statement.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a press conference at &lt;em&gt;BAMO&lt;/em&gt; offices today, Tim Colen, Executive Director of the San Francisco Housing Action Coalition, reiterated the sentiment. “Who knows if it’s legal or not, but it stinks,” Colen said. “It is so frustrating to learn that housing units built by taxpayers, through clever financial engineering, is being used as a cash cow for political slush funds…to support political measures that are directly harmful to tenants,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/dark-money-from-subsidized-real-estate-faces-calls-for-investigation/todco1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@AbleDart&quot;&gt;Able Dart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Colen, joined by Supervisor Scott Wiener, insisted that the campaign funds should have been reinvested into existing tenants, and could also be used to build more affordable housing. YBNC’s funding mostly came from a profit earned when Elberling refinanced several TODCO properties,&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Elberling conceded as much in his interview with the Chronicle, remaining adamantly without remorse. After refinancing netted several million dollars, TODCO found itself with “a big surplus that we didn’t need for regular expenses, so we funded our ... Yerba Buena Neighborhood Consortium to do community advocacy”—specifically, by allotting at least $300,000 per year for campaign contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In this election cycle, YBNC has contributed $149,000 to the Proposition X campaign, a measure setting high requirements to preserve industrial space, spearheaded by Supervisor Jane Kim. $83,000 has gone to support Propositions D, H, L, and M, four ballot measures Supervisor Aaron Peskin has championed to create special elections for Supervisor vacancies (D), create a Public Advocate office (H), and reorganize existing executive offices in committees with supervisorial appointments (L and M).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“These four measures are a fraud and a scam,” said Tony Winnicker, and aide to Mayor Ed Lee who has taken a leave of absence to campaign against D, H, L, and M. “Now we know they are primarily funded by money that originated with taxpayers, intended to benefit affordable housing and low-income tenants,” he continued. “These measures have nothing to do with sunshine and reform.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The state’s Fair Political Practices Commission (FPPC) has opened an investigation in response to the complaint. Elberling insisted that everything he did was legal, and not a defrauding of taxpayers. In his estimation, the properties were originally financed by federal and state funding decades ago, which have since been paid off (indeed, yielding a net profit after refinancing).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In the coming days, the &lt;em&gt;Metropolitan Observer&lt;/em&gt; will be investigating tenant complaints filed with the San Francisco Department of Building Inspection regarding TODCO properties. We will continue to report as the story develops.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;You can watch the entire press conference below:&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2FNoDHLM%2Fvideos%2F373964636279611%2F&amp;show_text=0&amp;width=400&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowTransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/modular-high-rise-proposed-in-downtown-oakland/">
    <title type="text">Modular High-Rise Proposed in Downtown Oakland</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:afb1ed88-ce4a-3bcb-8900-27125c5683f7</id>
    <updated>2016-10-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/modular-high-rise-proposed-in-downtown-oakland/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Oakland-based development firm &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nautilusgrp.com/&quot;&gt;Nautilus Group&lt;/a&gt; will soon undergo the challenge of building the country’s second tallest modular apartment complex, a 350-foot building with 176 dwelling units at the 14th &amp;amp; Webster intersection in downtown Oakland. The mixed-use project, featuring office space and ground-floor retail typical of downtown developments, will receive a 20% density bonus for including on-site affordable housing, with rents price-indexed for middle- and/or low-income households.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Although &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.radurban.com/1433-webster&quot;&gt;renderings&lt;/a&gt; have already been released, the developer likely faces a long road ahead. A 32-story modular high-rise project at Atlantic Yards in Brooklyn has faced a litany of problems since its inception, including but not limited to competing lawsuits between the developer and contractor. Stalled for years, the B2 tower at Atlantic Yards is &lt;a href=&quot;http://citylimits.org/2015/08/31/documents-reveal-woes-at-pioneering-atlantic-yards-building/&quot;&gt;finally complete&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/modular-high-rise-proposed-in-downtown-oakland/1433webnow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;1433 Webster, current street view (source: Google Maps / &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/oakbuilt&quot;&gt;OakBuilt&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere in the world, there is more optimism regarding modular construction. For example, a 54-story tower was built in Chengshe, China &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/resources/idt-3cca82c0-af80-4c3a-8a79-84fda5015115&quot;&gt;in just 19 days&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/E-GfyucwJ-I&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;RAD Urban, a partner in Nautilus’s vertically-integrated business model, released a promotional video earlier this year boasting of “up to 50%” speedier construction with their pre-fabricated modular designs. Nautilus recently completed “Garden Village,” a much smaller &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2013/10/17/innovative-housing-with-rooftop-farms-set-for-southside/&quot;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; at the Dwight &amp;amp; Fulton intersection in Berkeley, featuring a rooftop garden and a total absence of private parking spots.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The project will be heard before Oakland’s Design Review Committee, a subcommittee of the Planning Commission, on October 26th.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A staff report from the City of Oakland is expected later in the week. This article will be updated accordingly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/open-letter-jane-kims-attack-on-gary-mccoy/">
    <title type="text">Open Letter: Supervisor Jane Kim's Attack on Gary McCoy</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:32874d99-94d3-3950-8d6c-943bafefa1ee</id>
    <updated>2016-10-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/open-letter-jane-kims-attack-on-gary-mccoy/" />
    <author>
      <name>Jonathan Bonato</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Dear Jane,&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It really troubles me that you would attack Gary McCoy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10154252742119219&amp;amp;set=a.283755944218.144513.569399218&amp;amp;type=3&amp;amp;theater&quot;&gt;calling him a liar&lt;/a&gt; and paid by Scott Wiener to say what he said in the Equality California advertisement.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I was asked if I would consider sharing my experience in advertisement on this issue, but I have agreed with Jennifer Friedenbach and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.beyondchron.org/sfs-best-worst-ballot-measures/&quot;&gt;Beyond Chron's viewpoint&lt;/a&gt; on Proposition Q, and even a few days ago, I donated money to Amy Weiss and the St. Francis Homelessness Challenge.  But now my trust is damaged after seeing the advertisement against Gary.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/open-letter-jane-kims-attack-on-gary-mccoy/mccoy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I've had plenty of political disagreements with Gary, I am progressive, he is moderate, but we both share a profound and common bond, in that we are both gay, recovering crystal meth addicts, HIV positive, who struggled to overcome homelessness, hopelessness, and unemployment.   That's why after workinghard and donating the $500 max to get Aaron Peskin elected, I reached out Julie Christensen after the last election, and told her Gary would make a great addition to the Shelter Monitoring Committee, of which I was Vice Chair at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I spoke to the Mayor's Office too, and was very happy when I learned that Gary was appointed by the Mayor to serve on the committee, as were other fellow progressive members. As a progressive, I value different viewpoints from my own, and I saw a great opportunity to bring Moderates and Progressives together on the Shelter Monitoring Committee, especially because we found ourselves with great moderate allies in the Board of Supervisors and on the Rules Committee, especially with Katy Tang who backed us 100% as we fought for and worked to address the plight of domestic violence victims in homeless shelters.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Jane Kim,  please apologize to Gary. Your actions have actually led me to reconsider my choice to vote no on Q. When our political leaders are unwilling to listen to real homeless people, and use us as pawns to score political points against their opponents, I find it hard to toe the progressive party line. Attacking a formerly homeless person, one who is gay, HIV positive, and a recovering addict, who has, after many years of struggle, managed to finally land a full time job with living wage and benefits, and sign a lease for an apartment just a few weeks ago - this is not acceptable to me.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Before today, I always believed whoever won would make a great State Senator.  Today, I am left thinking only Scott Wiener has the requisite decency, honesty and integrity to serve in the Senate. Even though I often disagree with Scott, at least I know he will always listen, be polite, and be honest about his viewpoints and how he arrived to such viewpoints. Even Tim Redmond has mentioned how courteous and respectful Scott Wiener is.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Jane, I hope you can apologize to Gary. Attack Scott all you want, but please don't attack formerly homeless people because they political viewpoints differ from yours. Please don't silence or lie about homeless people because their political views don't agree with your viewpoint.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Regards,&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Jonathan&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/lao-says-coastal-housing-shortage-hurts-california-workers/">
    <title type="text">LAO Says Coastal Housing Shortage Hurts California Workers</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:1732a37d-afab-347d-8878-5e52bf22d7ba</id>
    <updated>2016-10-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/lao-says-coastal-housing-shortage-hurts-california-workers/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Legislative Analyst Office’s is back with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lao.ca.gov/LAOEconTax/Article/Detail/212&quot;&gt;more findings&lt;/a&gt; on the impact of high housing costs, this time in relation to workers, job opportunity, and economic mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;According to LAO, California used to be a place where economic opportunity was shared across the state. Areas with lots of good jobs also had plentiful housing, so low-income workers could move to those places and access better, higher-paying jobs. Between 1940 and 1960, the state experienced a “convergence” of income, where incomes grew fastest where they were the lowest, and grew the slowest where they were already high. In other words, low income residents generally became better off economically, and the pay of higher-income households didn’t change much.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/lao-says-coastal-housing-shortage-hurts-california-workers/lao2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source&lt;/em&gt;: Legislative Analyst’s Office&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Over the past two decades, though, this trend has reversed. Higher income residents are actually moving in the opposite direction toward places with lower wages (but also cheaper housing). While this might be because households end up getting more out of their paychecks by moving to more affordable parts of the state, LAO finds this turns out not to be the case. Even after factoring in lower housing costs, migrating households are still worse off because lower wages more than offset those savings. Rather, LAO suggests, residents may leave simply because they cannot find housing in those expensive metro areas at all.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The LAO recommends the governor place checks on local authority when it comes to housing approvals, since many communities fail to fully account for the impact of their decision not to build adequate housing. But if Governor Brown’s attempt at a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/08/unions-against-gov-browns-as-of-right-housing-plan.html&quot;&gt;by-right housing solution&lt;/a&gt; is any indication, state intervention may still be a long way away.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-sleepwalking-in-the-tenderloin/">
    <title type="text">Op-Ed: Sleepwalking in the Tenderloin</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:d14e969f-2aaf-38b2-b6b5-385a29d8e113</id>
    <updated>2016-10-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-sleepwalking-in-the-tenderloin/" />
    <author>
      <name>Elvin Padilla</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article originally appeared on &lt;a href=&quot;https://tenderlion.org/about/&quot;&gt;Tenderlion.org&lt;/a&gt; and is reprinted here with permission from the author. It has been edited for clarity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The IFD Fizzle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It’s tough trying to sell something with the moniker &lt;em&gt;Infrastructure Finance District&lt;/em&gt;, or IFD.  IFDs are a way to capture the increase in local taxes so they can be reinvested in an area over a prescribed period of time. Tax increment financing was considered as one of the ways to pay the tab for the Central Market Economic Strategy &lt;a href=&quot;https://tenderlion.files.wordpress.com/2016/10/central-marketeconomic-strategy-november-2011.pdf&quot;&gt;(CMES)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The strategy was straightforward: We all can see the surge of investment in mid-Market coming and the commensurate surge in taxes collected by the city.  This is a way the city – having successfully attracted tech companies to the area – can reinvest and leverage those extra gains in the local community.  Everybody wins.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As director of the Tenderloin Economic Development Project, I lobbied for the passage of an IFD.  I made the rounds to my neighboring community organizations, many of which signed on, and gave a tax-increment 101 presentation to an audience of residents and other stakeholders at the Tenderloin Futures Collaborative, which at the time was facilitated by much-loved Tenderloin legend Reverend Glenda Hope.  But the IFD campaign fizzled.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I could not get the support of the Tenderloin Neighborhood Development Corporation (TNDC), the Tenderloin’s largest landlord.  IFDs did not provide funding for new construction of affordable housing, a deal killer for TNDC.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This struck me as unfortunate for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;•    The Tenderloin’s housing stock is already affordable and protected, much of it owned and managed by TNDC.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;•    TNDC residents would have been beneficiaries of neighborhood improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;•    IFD legislation did allow for funds to be used to build replacement housing, which was an opportunity to rebuild some fucked-up SRO hotels like, say, the notorious Warfield Hotel on the corner of Turk &amp;amp; Taylor, or the entire eastside of 100 Taylor Street for that matter (built for the housing needs of the late 1900s), into high-density, high-quality, mixed-income housing two blocks from the Powell Street BART/MUNI station.  The Warfield Hotel’s historic plaque doesn’t do shit for poor people or the city’s twenty-first century urgent need for more housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;•    In 2012 we voted for Proposition C to create a $1.5 billion dollar trust fund for affordable housing, so a much-needed war chest was already moving forward for housing. In comparison, nothing – zero – was available to invest in community facilities: homeless shelters; arts &amp;amp; education centers; recreation centers; parks; a new neighborhood YMCA; an SF community college campus; satellite libraries; streetscape improvements to improve public safety at several notoriously dangerous intersections; all these investments in community could have been paid for and/or catalyzed by an IFD.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that California based affordable housing developer Mercy Housing, directed by Doug Shoemaker, said yes.   Also saying yes were:&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://allstars.org/&quot;&gt;All Stars Project&lt;/a&gt;, San Francisco Bay Area; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linesballet.org/&quot;&gt;Alonzo King LINES Ballet&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://counterpulse.org/&quot;&gt;CounterPulse&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.demarillac.org/&quot;&gt;De Marillac Academy&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theintersection.org/&quot;&gt;Intersection for the Arts&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kunst-stoff.org/ksarts&quot;&gt;Kunst-Stoff&lt;/a&gt; arts &amp;amp; dance company; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lhtsf.org/&quot;&gt;Lorraine Hansberry Theater&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.luggagestoregallery.org/&quot;&gt;Luggage Store Gallery &amp;amp; 509 Cultural Center&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tlcbd.org/&quot;&gt;North of Market Tenderloin Community Benefit District&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncclf.org/&quot;&gt;Northern California Community Loan Fund&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfcamerawork.org/&quot;&gt;SF Camerawork&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ymcasf.org/locations/shih-yu-lang-central-ymca&quot;&gt;Shih Yu-Lang Central YMCA&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stanthonysf.org/&quot;&gt;St. Anthony’s&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kidsclub.org/find-a-club/tenderloin-clubhouse/&quot;&gt;Tenderloin Boys &amp;amp; Girls Club&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tedpsf.org/&quot;&gt;Tenderloin Economic Development Project&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uchastings.edu/&quot;&gt;UC Hastings School of Law&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vydc.org/&quot;&gt;Vietnamese Youth Development Center&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://youthspeaks.org/&quot;&gt;Youth Speaks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A pretty impressive line-up – arts, affordable housing, education, public health, business, nonprofit lending, youth development, social services – all represented here.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I couldn’t get ahold of Hospitality House to add them to the list.  Given that mid-Market/Tenderloin is the epicenter of San Francisco’s homeless population it would only be appropriate to dedicate a portion of captured tax funds to invest in whatever facilities could help meet their needs.  Each year, responses seem limited to service providers’ annual operating budget add-back requests that keep us as indentured servants and do nothing to change the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Perhaps at some point this status quo just became our norm and we no longer even see or question it: a kind of collective sleepwalking.  Except, of course, for poor families in the Tenderloin, they definitely still notice it because they have to live with it. They don’t get evenings and weekends off.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There’s little “active” left in the “activist,” it seems to me.  We are lulled to sleep by bi-weekly paychecks and the droning sound of the BART train at the end of each weekday as we head back to our comfortable homes in East Bay neighborhoods where the concentration of poverty in the Tenderloin is far, far away.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Kim wouldn’t support an IFD; perhaps she was getting pushback from other sources.  I remember her saying we had to be careful about improving the neighborhood, which pretty much sums up her entire tenure as district supervisor.  I don’t get how building neighborhood art centers or parklets or a community college are a threat against the backdrop of an enormous inventory of protected housing, much of which, by the way, is dangerously substandard and in need of rebuilding.   A perplexing Progressive paradox – over five years living and working in the Tenderloin and I still don’t see the progress in Progressive.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While Mayor Ed Lee initially championed an IFD only to deliver a disappearing act instead, I often think the IFD campaign failure is largely on me.  I made the naïve assumption that delivering a well-crafted letter – co-authored by the Tenderloin Economic Development Project and the Northern California Community Loan Fund – signed by numerous and influential stakeholder organizations would grab the attention of city hall and elicit a response.  It doesn’t work that way; what was needed was an organized political campaign – a machine – that worked the chambers in city hall.  I was a newbie and didn’t know how to work the politics.  One dude getting his neighbor nonprofits – however impressive they may be – to sign a &lt;a href=&quot;https://tenderlion.org/2015/03/06/cbos-letter-to-supervisor-kim-and-mayor-ed-lee/&quot;&gt;petition&lt;/a&gt; doesn’t cut it.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Witness what &lt;a href=&quot;http://arts4bayarea.nationbuilder.com/allocation_of_hotel_tax_fund&quot;&gt;Arts for A Better Bay Area&lt;/a&gt; is doing to build support for &lt;a href=&quot;http://bettersf.com/&quot;&gt;Proposition S&lt;/a&gt;, a super important moment for restoring arts funding and improving services for homeless families.  That’s how you bring important initiatives from concept to reality.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-prop-ds-illusion-of-local-democracy/">
    <title type="text">Editorial: Prop D's Illusion of Local Democracy</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:55dd8213-bd63-37fe-b5b1-ec560b819c4d</id>
    <updated>2016-10-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-prop-ds-illusion-of-local-democracy/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A recent op-ed in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;San Francisco Examiner&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tells us that “Prop D is all about democracy,” which is pretty punchy as far as headlines go, in a kool-aid kind of way. Warning us against a present imbalance of power and overreach by City Hall insiders in certain district supervisorial seat replacements, the piece insists that Prop D will correct this imbalance and restore constitutional principles by giving power “back” to voters.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But Prop D isn’t about improving local democracy at all, and voters already have a say in the situation it applies to. What Prop D is trying to “fix” is the relatively uncommon circumstance of responding to a vacant Supervisor Seat, by supposedly shifting power away from the mayor and to voters in that district.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The way it works now, if a supervisor leaves his or her seat - as is likely to happen this November after Scott Wiener or Jane Kim wins the State Senate race - the Mayor is responsible for appointing a new supervisor, who can then run in the next general election. Prop D would change this to allow the Mayor to appoint only an interim Supervisor, and create a special election to vote in the new supervisor. The interim appointee by the mayor would not be allowed to run in this special election, although they could run in the next general election.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At first glance, that change seems to make sense. Why should the mayor get to select a district supervisor, rather than district residents themselves? Doesn’t that just open the door for political favoritism or some shady mayor motives?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Not really. If voters don’t like the mayor’s appointment, they can vote them out come election-time. And they have. Two of the last three mayoral appointees - Julie Christensen of District 3 and Christina Olague of District 5 - lost in the subsequent general elections. The supposed benefit of incumbency doesn’t seem to be an issue here.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;If interim appointee doesn’t have to face voters, it would be &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; likely that they will put the mayor’s interests first. For the time they hold office, the appointee will answer to the mayor with no accountability to voters. Will this necessarily lead to some negative outcome for the district at issue? No, but if the goal of this measure is to increase accountability for a district leader, this seems like the wrong way to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Moreover, special elections generally get very low turnout, which means the results skew...well, they skew in some non-representative direction, essentially.  Compared to a general election, like the one you would vote in for a vacant supervisor seat now, special elections are actually less democratic. Again, if the goal here is more democracy, this change won’t get us there.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The current system works, and doesn’t pose any actual threat to democracy. We already elect supervisors in vacancy situations.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Prop D would just add a costly, unnecessary election with low voter participation and create more problems than it would solve - which is hard to avoid when the measure creates its own problem.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
