<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Bay Area Metropolitan Observer</title>
  <id>urn:uuid:52c4ddef-40d4-3bc8-bbd3-d91037b58706</id>
  <updated>2016-10-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/" />
  <link href="http://sfbamo.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <author>
    <name></name>
  </author>
  <generator uri="https://github.com/ajdavis/lektor-atom" version="0.2">Lektor Atom Plugin</generator>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/arce-discusses-transit-and-housing-at-30th-and-mission/">
    <title type="text">Arce Discusses Transit and Housing at 30th &amp; Mission</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:81077869-6af6-3b06-85f9-69c4e0ad1fba</id>
    <updated>2016-10-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/arce-discusses-transit-and-housing-at-30th-and-mission/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Joshua Arce, a civil rights attorney and native of the Mission District, has ambitious plans for the area's southwestern fringe. With almost no mention of his campaign for District 9 Supervisor, he has announced plans for a broad scope of infrastructure improvements for the area south of Cesar Chavez Street, including a new BART station at 30th &amp;amp; Mission. Last night, Arce gathered before a small but mixed crowd (ideologically and otherwise, as it turned out) to present his plan in more detail and field concerns from the public.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Now dubbed the Mission South of Cesar Chavez Sustainable Neighborhood Plan, Arce’s goals are hardly new: his presentation began with a historical timeline of transit proposals in the neighborhood, most recently including plans for a BART station that were abandoned after a gloomy fiscal study in 2003. But this new plan, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/joshua-arce-proposes-bart-station-housing-south-of-cesar-chavez/&quot;&gt;unveiled&lt;/a&gt; several months ago with the support of State Assemblymember David Chiu and BART Director Nick Josefowitz, accounts for the many shortcomings that undermined older proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/arce-discusses-transit-and-housing-at-30th-and-mission/slide5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Housing aside, the plan’s most beneficial innovation is ultimately a fiscal one. Construction of the new BART station would cost $200 million, less than half of the $500 million projected in 2003—and tunnel boring would occur underground, causing no disruption to traffic on Mission Street.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/arce-discusses-transit-and-housing-at-30th-and-mission/slide2a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Two design features are responsible for these savings: first, excavation would only have to account for 50% of the hill incline than previously estimated; second, BART would no longer consider expensive “pocket tracks” to repair trains at the station. Even though boring under Mission Street would cost more than tearing up an entire mile of the street, which the 2004 proposal estimated would last for 11 months, the overall cost is lower.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/arce-discusses-transit-and-housing-at-30th-and-mission/slide2b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Arce’s ambitions go beyond transit, including plans to build dense, transit-oriented affordable housing around the station. Many vacant lots near the 30th &amp;amp; Mission Safeway had been identified as “opportunity sites” to build a combination of Below Market Rate (BMR) units, and market-rate construction to finance the subsidies. Unsurprisingly, this drew the ire of some neighbors who insisted that anything below 50% or 100% Affordable Housing could ease the city’s catastrophic displacement crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Before the presentation even began, I had the distinct pleasure of hearing local landlord Spike Kahn lecture &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.me/gwynethborden&quot;&gt;Gwyneth Borden&lt;/a&gt;, a black tenant and transit advocate, about the “gentrifying effects” a new BART station would have. The same landlord, whose campaign against the “Beast on Bryant” project earned a place on our list of &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/top-10-bay-area-nimby-moments-of-2016/&quot;&gt;Top 10 NIMBY Moments&lt;/a&gt; this year, has previously asserted that &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/08/big-bucks-spent-in-district-9-race/&quot;&gt;“No housing is better than gentrified housing.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When fears of gentrification were voiced during the presentation, Arce was not unprepared for criticism. He made particular note of London Breed’s recent Neighborhood Preference Ordinance, recently &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfist.com/2016/09/22/hud_breed_willie_kennedy.php&quot;&gt;approved&lt;/a&gt; by the federal government after a tense stalemate, whichallocates preferential lottery slots in BMR dwelling units for applicants living near the project. The Department of Housing and Urban Development approved Breed’s plan only for implementation in neighborhoods seeing the most displacement of long-term residents, the Mission chiefly among them. With 1900 units built in the area, Arce argued, Breed’s legislation could help stem displacement where new subsidized housing may not otherwise help locals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/arce-discusses-transit-and-housing-at-30th-and-mission/slide1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Amid frequent check-ins on the score of the ongoing Giants game, Arce faced a deluge of criticism from a relative minority of concerned citizens, mostly focused on traffic impacts and the loss of a “chill” and “quiet” environment relative to the rest of the Mission. “We don’t want to be 16th Street,” one 30-year resident exclaimed. The woman told Arce she was there on behalf of her 91 year old neighbor, who could not walk down the hill to attend. “This needs to consider the needs of those who are mobility-impaired,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Arce remained steadfast in his assurance that the presentation was simply a “conversation” and that no plans had been set in stone. Borden added, as a candidate for BART’s Board of Directors, that BART did not plan to fund anything beyond core infrastructure maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yet Arce also remained clear, despite some residents’ disdain for adding density to the Mission corridor, that the current status quo was the least attractive option. “The easiest thing to do here is to do nothing. We need to think about what will happen if we do that. Will the situation get worse, or will it get better?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Arce additionally noted that his campaign had refused to receive any donations from real estate developers, in order to “negotiate the best deals” for affordable housing. The comment was undoubtedly an implicit jab at his opponent Hillary Ronen. Ronen, who has raised nearly twice as much funding as Arce, received &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/08/big-bucks-spent-in-district-9-race/&quot;&gt;$2,700 from registered lobbyists&lt;/a&gt;, including one representing the developer for the “Beast on Bryant” project. When some members of the public urged a greater proportion of subsidized units, he typically responded that his goal was to have as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Borden again chimed in with qualified optimism regarding the city’s growth. “Unless we build a moat around the city, people aren’t going to stop coming here,” she said. “As much as we want to focus on what’s impeding our quality of life &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;, we also need to plan long-term...The city hasn’t planned for growth, and until that changes, each cycle is going to hit us even harder.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Speaking from her experience as chair of the Golden Gate Restaurant Association, Borden noted that retail revenues had been down across San Francisco, regardless of lost parking or new development. The presentation noted local retailers’ concerns that the influx of new high-income residents had failed to correlate with increased consumer spending or even more foot traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;One landlord in the audience seemed to contend that the character of San Francisco’s newcomers may ultimately represent a net loss for local retail. “I have these tenants, and they’re all rocket scientists who went to MIT. They don’t know where to find a hardware store. They order everything online, commute to their jobs out of town, and only stay here to drink on weekends.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Arce’s response drew muted laughter: “What cannot be said of them is that they aren’t rocket scientists.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Other local planners and architects insisted that developing the area need not disrupt the “quality of life” in the area if designed accordingly. “There are many neighborhoods in Tokyo that are far more dense than this one, and they’re so calm, I mean—you can hear the birds sing,” one man remarked.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many criticisms were met with the same tentative optimism: “this is why we’re having this conversation,” Arce said until it virtually became his mantra. But the response also drew him back to the night’s most prominent theme: is the status quo the best option?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/arce-discusses-transit-and-housing-at-30th-and-mission/slide3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Indeed, some attendees immediately shouted “no” when Arce reached a point on his final slide: &lt;em&gt;Does the community still want BART?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Arce confirmed in a brief interview that he would be open to different plans if they proved to be a better option than “if we do nothing.” Other options may come to include a Bus Rapid Transit corridor, or a BART/MUNI transfer station.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Everything and nothing is on the table. Ultimately, everyone in attendance seemed to leave with a satisfied sense of having their input weighted against all options, including nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned 30-year resident, attending for her mobility-impaired neighbor, had bigger plans that night. “I gotta go around the corner and cast my vote for Hillary,” she said to me as we exited the venue.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;(One can only assume she meant Clinton.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/wiener-talks-housing-condoms-soda-on-reddit-ama/">
    <title type="text">Wiener Talks Housing, Condoms, Soda on Reddit AMA</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a4625f28-4c77-3779-988a-eb4194195dea</id>
    <updated>2016-10-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/wiener-talks-housing-condoms-soda-on-reddit-ama/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Scott Wiener took to the popular internet forum Reddit today to answer questions from anonymous users in a series of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/politics/comments/5709cf/hi_reddit_im_san_francisco_supervisor_scott/?st=iu63tdkp&amp;amp;sh=eae38fc6&quot;&gt;“Ask Me Anything”&lt;/a&gt; interviews sponsored by the SF YIMBY Party. (Readers will continue to see advertisements for these interviews on the &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt;, but we will continue to summarize them for readers who may not have the time to follow them live.) Wiener primarily focused on outlining his differences with Supervisor Jane Kim, with whom he is deadlocked in a bitter race for State Senate, but also responded to questions about his relationship with former Congressman Anthony Weiner (there is none).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco’s Proposition V, a sales tax increase on soda distribution, offered a prime opportunity to lash out at Kim’s corporate donors. In response to a question about the soda tax’s exemptions (e.g. milk, beer, diet soda) Wiener declared: “Her campaign is basically being funded by the soda industry - to date, the soda industry has poured neatly a quarter million into mailers promoting her. Her campaign consultant is also the consultant for the soda industry, and he directs where the soda industry money goes.” Citing evidence to back the policy, such as increased diabetes risk and a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.latimes.com/science/sciencenow/la-sci-sn-who-soda-tax-20161011-snap-story.html&quot;&gt;WHO recommendation for soda taxes worldwide&lt;/a&gt;, seemed almost an afterthought to his prolonged Kim-bashing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The signature issue in San Francisco politics—and, not incidentally, of this publication as well—took center stage: housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;One Redditor identified as a tech professional and native to Wiener’s supervisorial district asked about the issue in perhaps the most nuanced and even-handed form possible: “What specific policies would you pursue in Sacramento to best balance our recent economic resurgence with the impacts that insane cost of living has had on marginalized communities?” Unlike many inquiries about the housing crisis we’ve seen, this question specifically focused on the given context of the city’s current economic resurgence, and how best to “balance” growth with emergent inequality. Wiener seemed to agree: “the past 5 years have been completely predictable,” the Supervisor noted.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Characteristically, Wiener responded in terms of policies Supervisor Kim had opposed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Jane Kim has repeatedly proposed policies that kill off housing while opposing policies that could spur more housing and more affordable housing. Jane Kim co-authored the Mission Housing Moratorium, while I opposed it. Jane Kim opposed the 7,500 unit Park Merced project (west side housing, with a rail line through it, family sized as well), which I supported. Jane Kim opposed the Affordable Housing Density Bonus program (you get two extra floors in height in exchange for higher percentage of affordable housing), which I supported. And, Jane Kim opposed the Governor's by-right proposal to make it easier to get housing approved. I supported that proposal on the condition that it be amended to, for example, protect rent-controlled housing from demolition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mercifully, not all of Wiener’s policy positions served as platforms for attacking his opponent. The Supervisor answered a question about California’s Cap and Trade policies for carbon emissions and continued GDP growth without once mentioning Kim. “We need to continue to de-carbonize our transportation sector. That means more transit, more no and low-carbon vehicles - with strong and equitable incentives to shift our fleet away from carbon,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Wiener has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/supervisor-scott-wiener-proposes-new-subway-tunnels-throughout-city/&quot;&gt;written&lt;/a&gt; extensively on the need to expand BART throughout western San Francisco, which, due to slow MUNI service, remains functionally as remote from San Francisco’s Civic Center as downtown Walnut Creek.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A brief argument ensued over Wiener’s opposition to Proposition 60, the state ballot measure that would require adult film actors to wear condoms on set. The anonymous interrogator, labeled “forever a troll” by another Redditor, harshly criticized Wiener’s preference for standard practices including regular STI testing and PrEP, a drug that prevents HIV transmission.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“At no point have I ever opposed condoms…Condoms helped save our community,” Wiener wrote. “We must continue to make condoms easily available, and I continue to support that. But we should also not pass laws that contradict current public health, scientific approaches to preventing HIV - approaches that, yes, include condoms but also include other prevention techniques, including PrEP” The Supervisor also shrugged off accusations that he had any connection to Gilead, the pharmaceutical conglomerate that manufactures PrEP.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Other issues that did not bring up Jane Kim included maintenance of bike lanes (Answer: “Our city needs a culture change around double parking”) and police accountability (“You can support the police while also supporting reform”).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Marjan Philhour, candidate for District 1 Supervisor, will participate in the next SF YIMBY-sponsored AMA forum on October 20th.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/housing-advocates-oppose-prop-m-commission/">
    <title type="text">Housing Advocates Oppose Prop M Commission</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:4388400b-b283-3df4-8cb6-f284936f7638</id>
    <updated>2016-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/housing-advocates-oppose-prop-m-commission/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At noon today, a cavalcade of non-profit developers, tenants, and laborers held a press conference to announce their staunch opposition to San Francisco’s Proposition M… right here at &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; HQ. Proposition M would create two new departments to oversee Housing and Economic Development programs in the city, which critics have decried as needlessly bureaucratic and anti-democratic.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Tim Colen, Executive Director of the San Francisco Housing Action Coalition, underscored the importance of the meeting with a simple comment: “only professionals and political gadflies” would have the time to monitor yet another layer of oversight to the already-byzantine process of approving new housing construction in the city. In his estimation, the unelected commission would have the power to make recommendations—even contradictory ones—without any vetting process, which would slow down much-needed housing production. Several other speakers self-identified as “professional gadflies” in qualifying their opposition to Prop M.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Nonprofit developer John Stewart delivered a biting coup-de-grace to the assault on Prop M. The ballot measure, in his view, was designed for a problem that did not exist: lack of community input. “For our Hunters View project, we had over 100 community meetings,” Stewart said. “We are now in the process of developing a project on Broadway. There are six working community groups that we are dealing with, and they all have opinions. We listen to them. Sometimes the feedback is really good, sometimes it’s not, but they’re there. The notion that we need more sunshine, that these deals are going on covertly in the dark, &lt;em&gt;is crazy.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2FNoDHLM%2Fvideos%2F368789926797082%2F&amp;show_text=0&amp;width=400&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowTransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/top-10-bay-area-nimby-moments-of-2016/">
    <title type="text">Top 10 Bay Area NIMBY Moments of 2016</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:099f4847-c8ac-3540-bc3b-9def33d4496c</id>
    <updated>2016-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/top-10-bay-area-nimby-moments-of-2016/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After covering SFHAC’s “Housing Heroes” award ceremony in &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/sfhac-honors-heroes-with-haughty-hors-doeuvres/&quot;&gt;delicious detail&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;BAMO&lt;/em&gt; felt that it was only appropriate to give recognition to both sides of the housing conversation. Today, we are proud to present the region’s Top 10 Displays of NIMBYism this year.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 1) Susan Jaffe Speaks Fondly of the McDonald’s She’s Never Set Foot In&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Watching treasured San Francisco shops and restaurants shutter is never easy, especially if you have a long history in this city. But then there’s, you know, McDonald’s. The fast food location on 3rd and Townsend &lt;a href=&quot;http://hoodline.com/2016/10/3rd-townsend-mcdonald-s-goes-dark-in-preparation-for-demolition&quot;&gt;in the process of being replaced&lt;/a&gt; with much needed high density, transit-proximal housing, which is pretty tough to chalk up as a loss -- unless you are Susan Jaffe. In a shameless Facebook post, Susan laments the change as the destruction of one of her childhood memories. In fact, the golden arches of SoMa were so special to Susan that &lt;em&gt;she literally never even went there&lt;/em&gt;. “I'm a vegetarian,” Susan explains exasperatedly in a Facebook comment. “I don't eat there.” Susan goes on to stick the rhetorical landing, telling her opponent that he doesn’t understand what is sentimental to her. We join Susan’s interlocutor in pleading ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/top-10-bay-area-nimby-moments-of-2016/susan1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/top-10-bay-area-nimby-moments-of-2016/susan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) Mission Resident Lucy Admits We Need Affordable Housing But Protests 100% Affordable Housing Complex for Seniors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/top-10-bay-area-nimby-moments-of-2016/1296shotwell.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;1296 Shotwell St. rendering&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last year, Supervisor David Campos asked San Francisco to pass Prop I, which would temporarily ban all new housing in the Mission District unless the units are 100% affordable. An extreme proposal, and it didn’t pass. But apparently even when housing is 100% affordable, and explicitly set aside for an economically vulnerable segment of the population, residents of the Mission and Bernal Heights still find reason to oppose it.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A proposal at 1296 Shotwell for 94 units of permanently affordable senior housing failed to meet the standards of its future neighbor, Lucy, &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/10/neighbors-double-down-against-mission-district-affordable-housing/&quot;&gt;who insisted the project be reduced in size&lt;/a&gt;, despite the fact that this concession would eliminate affordable units. Lucy acknowledged that “every unit counts”, but with the usual NIMBY caveat that one more affordable housing project “would not solve the problems of the city.” In a rare moment of self-awareness, Lucy declined to provide her last name to &lt;em&gt;Mission Local&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) Brisbane Woman Stands up for People Who Fear Becoming a Minority in Their Own Home&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Fox News somehow missed this story, but we didn’t. The city of Brisbane is considering whether or not to approve a development proposal for offices and housing on its little swath of bay-adjacent land, which would be totally fine with Brisbane except for the part where they have to let people live there. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.ci.brisbane.ca.us%2Fspecial-council-meeting-to-discuss-brisbane-baylands-09-29-2016&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;sntz=1&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNEvlPHK_BXpMwSlr3IvDImKJC3UPw&quot;&gt;At a city council meeting in September&lt;/a&gt;, local Brisbanians contemplated the implications of housing, which are basically apocalyptic in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It really doesn’t matter why Brisbane is not going to build housing on the baylands,” this woman tells us, because apparently they don’t believe in reasons in Brisbane.  “Some don’t want to be a minority in their own home - who would?” she says around the 1h17m mark. Who would, indeed, white Brisbane lady?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4) Millionaire Homeowner in Berkeley Complains about Housing for People That Aren’t Her&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/top-10-bay-area-nimby-moments-of-2016/nimby1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Being a retired Berkeley homeowner is hard. You have to helplessly watch your property value go up all the time, fight the glare of glittering views of the bay, and constantly toil through the philosophical conundrum of whether or not Philz Coffee is a chain. How does one manage? Well, one way to ease the stress is going to city planning hearings and eulogizing your first-world problems to anyone who is paid to listen.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This woman, who owns a house worth over a million dollars but pays property taxes based on an assessed value of about 20% of that amount, spoke at a Berkeley City Council meeting this past July against three new homes, which she said would &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hanlonbt/status/784140878541496320&quot;&gt;“set a dangerous precedent” in the neighborhood.&lt;/a&gt; Sharing is scaring, right?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5) Peter Cohen, Director of an Affordable Housing Organization, Opposes Affordable Housing Initiative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In one of the most head-scratching policy oppositions in San Francisco this year, a measure put forward to increase the amount of affordable housing through a density bonus program ended up getting challenged by members of the affordable housing community itself. Yes, we were also shocked. The proposal would allow developers to add three stories to a building irrespective of zoned height limits, but under the condition that all the extra units are affordable. More density, more affordability, and at no cost to taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sounds like an awesome deal (it is), but Peter Cohen, Director of the affordable housing nonprofit Council of Community Housing Organizations (CCHO), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/SF-housing-density-plan-meets-opposition-6810769.php&quot;&gt;came out as one of the loudest opponents of the bill&lt;/a&gt;. Cohen said it was too much of a giveaway to private developers, which seems to completely miss the fact that it is actually a giveaway to middle-income families. We admit this one doesn’t technically qualify as NIMBYism in the literal sense, but Mr. Cohen doesn’t technically qualify as an affordable housing advocate, either.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6) Man Who Can Walk to Fremont BART Explains How Important Cars Are&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Hugh Vassar, who would like you to know that he has purchased not one but two single-family homes in Fremont, doesn’t think building housing near BART will reduce people’s use of cars. How does Hugh know that? Because he lives right next to BART, &lt;a href=&quot;https://fremontca.viebit.com/#K7J3x1kL3QTQ&quot;&gt;and he drives all the time&lt;/a&gt;! Even as a frequent BART commuter, Hugh “never got rid of any cars” (is he a collector?), which means the future residents of the proposed BART-adjacent housing development he opposes won’t either. We would explain to Hugh that increasing density and walkability doesn’t happen overnight, and the development is a really good start, but he is already speeding away from us.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7) Environmental Attorney Stu Flashman Fights Green, Eco-friendly CalTrain Project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/top-10-bay-area-nimby-moments-of-2016/caltrain_baby_bullet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Stu Flashman, who is not a character in a Marvel comic but a real-life land use and environmental attorney, represented Atherton in its fight against CalTrain’s electrification plan, a plan the Sierra Club called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sierraclub.org/sites/www.sierraclub.org/files/sce/loma-prieta-chapter/cool-cities-action/12.13.12%20-%20Article%20-%20Caltrain%20electrification%20project%20lauded%20by%20Sierra%20Club.pdf&quot;&gt;one of the best transportation projects of the year&lt;/a&gt; back in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The plan in question is to replace CalTrain’s diesel engine trains with electrified trains, in order to increase operating efficiency, accommodate more riders, and significantly reduce air pollution. Stu argued that the environmental review didn’t take into account the cumulative effects of an electrified CalTrain and the high speed rail, since apparently twice as much mass transit probably means twice as much pollution. Except electrifying CalTrain &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.caltrain.com/Assets/Caltrain+Modernization+Program/Documents/PCEP+Fact+Sheet+May+2015.pdf&quot;&gt;has enormous environmental benefits&lt;/a&gt;: taking cars off the road with 619,000 less vehicle miles traveled and reducing annual greenhouse gas emissions by 176,000 metric tons of CO2.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Stu Flashman and Atherton &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.almanacnews.com/news/2016/09/28/atherton-loses-lawsuit-over-caltrain-electrification-project&quot;&gt;ultimately lost the lawsuit&lt;/a&gt;, but they didn’t lose a place on this list.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8) Berkeley Resident Kelly Hammargren Confuses NIMBYism with Valid Legal Argument&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kelly Hammargren has spent more than two years fighting a proposed housing project at 2211 Harold Way, including a legal battle which might have made more headway by now if Hammargren actually had a lawyer. The project she’s opposing, a 300-plus unit building next to a BART station, has been in the works since December 2012. Although more than 30 community meetings having been held since the project’s application, Hammargren eventually decided to step it up to the big leagues by going to court.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for her, a judge is supposed to consider legal arguments, and it seems Hammargren didn’t really have any. At &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/08/29/court-considers-challenge-to-berkeleys-2211-harold-way-project/&quot;&gt;a hearing in August&lt;/a&gt;, the judge had to ask Hammargren to stick to legal arguments and not make political speeches, ultimately denying her motion. Without any mention of her lawsuit, Hammargren has exhorted Berkeley students to support her flagrant NIMBYism because, you know, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailycal.org/2016/09/16/harold-way-project-mired-problems/&quot;&gt;historic views&lt;/a&gt; or something.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9) Spike Kahn Doesn’t Want Any New Properties in the Mission Unless She Owns Them&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/top-10-bay-area-nimby-moments-of-2016/bbryant.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &quot;Beast&quot; on Bryant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Mission housing proposal dubbed the “Beast on Bryant” by opponents is more of a building than a Disney villain, but when you’re a NIMBY, nouns are relative and the dictionary is a capitalist manifesto. In any semantic case, Spike Kahn has been leading the charge against the housing proposal on 2000-2070 Bryant, a 300-plus unit building with a portion of affordable units. It’s such an inoffensive project that &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/9/15/12931964/beast-on-bryant-loses-appeals-lawsuit&quot;&gt;even David Campos supports it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But here’s where things get prickly for Spike. While Spike Kahn has spoken passionately against this housing project “destroying the neighborhood” because of all its moneyed implications, or something, she conveniently leaves out the fact that she owns rental properties and is totally killing it in on AirBnB. Yeah, the beast-slayer owns &lt;a href=&quot;http://datagovus.com/san-francisco-business.php?id=1027901-05-151&quot;&gt;numerous properties&lt;/a&gt; in San Francisco and regularly AirBnBs her home. Take a look at her &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airbnb.com/users/show/30614&quot;&gt;user profile&lt;/a&gt;, and go ahead and ask her for a discount on your nightly price too, since affordability is so important to Spike.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10) Jean Quan's Activist Daughter Sticks it to Developers by Demanding More Parking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Fighting for the little guy is important, especially when the little guy is a car. Just ask Lailan Huen, daughter of former Oakland mayor Jean Quan, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/05/oakland-housing-wood-partners-gentrification-quan.html&quot;&gt;who is leading the call for parking-related concessions from Wood Partners on one of its development proposals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The project at issue is a 262-unit residential proposal that will, ironically, replace an existing parking lot located walking distance from several BART stations. In addition to calling for increased affordability percentages, which will likely require millions of dollars in subsidies, Huen and her followers want 25 parking spaces or a $50,000 payment to fund parking. Hint: the housing might be more affordable if it didn’t require so much parking.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to our Top 10 NIMBYs! You earned it—at everyone else’s expense.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-youth-power/">
    <title type="text">Dispatches from the Vote16 Campaign: Youth Power</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:2cd0ad06-b2c0-3a37-aac7-cfcac2de98b6</id>
    <updated>2016-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-youth-power/" />
    <author>
      <name>Cami Doo</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The vice presidential debate on Tuesday, October 4 took place in Farmville, VA, where a  16 year old led once a historic student strike..&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Barbara Rose Johns Powell was born in New York City in 1935, according to the Moton Museum’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.motonmuseum.org/biography-barbara-rose-johns-powell/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. She lived during the time of Jim Crow and her school in Prince Edward County lacked many resources, including science laboratories.. When Johns confronted her teacher about this, her teacher indifferently dismissed the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Johns became determined to organize a strike. She planned to “make signs and ... give a speech stating [their] dissatisfaction and ... march out [of] the school.” Johns’s strike caught the attention of two NAACP (National Association for the Advancement of Colored People) lawyers and was later filed in a federal courthouse. This case was influential in the Brown v Board of Education of Topeka, which proclaimed the “separate but equal” law unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As a 16 year old, Barbara Rose Johns influenced one of the biggest cases in America that pushed our nation towards inclusiveness and equality.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Her legacy lives on in the Yes on F campaign today. Meanwhile, one prominent argument against Prop F is that teens will just vote the same way as their parents. The statistical rebuttal is that 44% of teens voted a different way as their parents in the Scottish independence referendum. The logical reasoning is that influence isn’t a one-way street; it goes both ways. Teens impact their parents as much as their parents shape their lives, and teens are capable of thinking independently (why else would there be so many stereotypes of the “rebellious teen?”).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As part of the Youth Empowerment Academy , we celebrate Barbara Rose Johns and want to build on her legacy of empowering youth.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When I presented in front of the New Avenues Democratic Club, Hene Kelly, a former DCCC member and Democratic Party activist, noted how youth, in one night, were able to change 5 Supervisors’ minds to put Vote16 on the ballot.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Club members also mentioned how seeing young people excited made them excited again as well. Our contagious passion for civic engagement is spreading faster than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/tenants-union-prints-election-mailers-with-sweet-sweet-soda-money/">
    <title type="text">Tenants Union Prints Election Mailers with Sweet, Sweet Soda Money</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:2caf297c-2167-3152-a259-c619ae73c09b</id>
    <updated>2016-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/tenants-union-prints-election-mailers-with-sweet-sweet-soda-money/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The American Beverage Association is not happy about Proposition V, San Francisco’s proposed tax on sugary sodas. Campaigns on both sides of the bay are portraying soda taxes as a “grocery tax,” because the proposed legislation would levy a sales tax increase on distributors rather than consumer-facing transactions. Technically, a retailer could disburse the increased cost across all merchandise in the store.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Campaign finance disclosures show that the No On V committee, sponsored by the American Beverage Association California PAC, has spent $10 million to garner public opposition against the measure. No On V has also paid for several organizations’ slate cards to be mailed to voters citywide, including $40,000 donated to the San Francisco Tenants Union, and $5,000 to the Harvey Milk LGBT Democratic Club.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Oddly, although the Tenants Union mailer endorses Tenants Together director Dean Preston for District 5 Supervisor and urges voters to reject the soda tax, Preston himself expressed support for the tax in a District 5 &lt;a href=&quot;http://sanfrancisco.granicus.com/TranscriptViewer.php?view_id=74&amp;amp;clip_id=26261&quot;&gt;debate&lt;/a&gt; hosted by the League of Women Voters.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Preston joined the Tenants Union, along with homeowners’ groups such as the Haight-Ashbury Neighborhood Council and Telegraph Hill Dwellers, in &lt;a href=&quot;http://hoodline.com/2016/01/activists-fear-rezoning-plan-will-reduce-rent-controlled-housing-despite-assurances&quot;&gt;opposing&lt;/a&gt; last year’s Affordable Housing Bonus Program. Opponents claimed that the density bonuses the bill would provide for more affordable housing units could allow for the demolition of rent-controlled apartments, even after the Board of Supervisors amended the proposal to avoid such situations. Preston &lt;a href=&quot;http://hoodline.com/2016/01/activists-fear-rezoning-plan-will-reduce-rent-controlled-housing-despite-assurances&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; neighbors as being “alarmed” that a rezoning on Divisadero allowed a project to scale up from 16 to 60 dwelling units.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last year, Preston also spearheaded a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/999050313480342/&quot;&gt;campaign&lt;/a&gt; to halt the construction of several condominium projects on Divisadero Street, arguing that market-rate housing “will be completely unaffordable to our neighborhood.” Given these claims, it may be worth noting what is in fact affordable for Preston himself.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Preston purchased his current home across from Alamo Square in 1999 for $880,000 in cash. Though its current estimated value is $2.8 million, its assessed value for tax purposes is $1.1 million due to statewide caps on property taxes enacted under 1979’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lao.ca.gov/Publications/Report/3497&quot;&gt;Proposition 13&lt;/a&gt;. It is &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TenantsUnionSF/status/735249477565452288&quot;&gt;unclear&lt;/a&gt; whether or not the Tenants Union considers California’s tax structure to be a relevant factor in statewide economic inequality.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The open secret of Big Soda money funding countless campaigns throughout the city, including campaigns that support the soda tax measure, will be an ongoing story.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/lafayette-officials-organize-against-saranap-village-development/">
    <title type="text">Lafayette Officials Organize Against Saranap Village Development</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a2d12478-9a26-3f03-b3f0-caa3b4644b8e</id>
    <updated>2016-10-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/lafayette-officials-organize-against-saranap-village-development/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Homeowners opposing nearby development is nothing new—it’s why this news source exists, after all. Remarkably, some homeowners appear to have colluded with Lafayette city officials to oppose new housing construction, possibly on taxpayers’ dime. According to an investigation of public records conducted by this paper, residents assisting in organizing against the Saranap Village project include City Manager Steve Falk, Planning and Building Director Niroop Srivatsa and Parks, Trails and Recreation Director Jennifer Russell.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/lafayette-officials-organize-against-saranap-village-development/saranapnow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Current view of the Saranap Village site, in contrast to artist's rendering above&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Situated in an unincorporated area between Lafayette and Walnut Creek, the developer Hall Equities Group has already downsized the project’s residential portion by 22% and halved its retail component. The three city officials in the investigation all live within a mile of the site.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Planning Director Srivatsa said via email to a Bay Area News Group reporter, “I would prefer not to be referred to as Lafayette’s planning director” when speaking about the project. Earlier press shows Srivatsa speaking against the project as a member of the Saranap Homeowners Association. Emails also show City Manager Falk and Parks Director Russell encouraging residents to circulate a petition on the neighborhood social media platform Nextdoor. City staff unsuccessfully lobbied the Walnut Creek City Council to comment on the project’s environmental review process.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/lafayette-officials-organize-against-saranap-village-development/saranapmap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lafayette city officials' proximity to Saranap Village site&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; developed an interest in the potential misuse of city resources after we began wondering how the Saranap Homeowners’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.saranap.org/sv/project-background.html#fnd&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; could include such detailed renditions of the project, which they deem “too tall” for the surrounding area, unless professional urban planning software had been used.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We’ve already reduced the proposal from the original 235 units, eventually down to 160,” said Deborah Karbo, Vice President of Hall Equities Group. “It’s likely we’re not done yet.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;City officials could be found to be in violation of California Government Code &lt;a href=&quot;http://codes.findlaw.com/ca/government-code/gov-sect-8314.html&quot;&gt;section 8314&lt;/a&gt;, which reads in part:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;(a) It is unlawful for any elected state or local officer, including any state or local appointee, employee, or consultant, to use or permit others to use public resources for a campaign activity, or personal or other purposes which are not authorized by law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-leandro-marina-development-faces-hurdles-despite-approval/">
    <title type="text">San Leandro Marina Development Faces Hurdles Despite Approval</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:156435ae-5908-3d15-a05e-d30d2ae9a551</id>
    <updated>2016-10-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-leandro-marina-development-faces-hurdles-despite-approval/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The East Bay suburb of San Leandro may see a revitalized marina as early as next year, as a multiphase mixed-use project by Cal-Coast Development nears the end of its preliminary planning stage. Monarch Bay’s 40 acres of apartments, retail, office space, and amenities has been approved by the San Leandro City Council, and will soon be reviewed by the San Francisco Bay Conservation and Development Commission (BCDC). As of 2011, the state agency requires new construction to plan for withstanding rising sea levels due to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Cal-Coast’s most immediate plans include 150,000 square feet of office space, a 468-space parking garage, two restaurants, and a kayak rental facility. A residential component would not be included until the second phase, with several four-story buildings providing 160 rental units and 61 condominiums. An average of 1.5 parking spaces per residential unit is planned, with at least 587 additional public parking spaces planned for the shoreline. San Leandro &lt;a href=&quot;https://sanleandro.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?ID=2285006&amp;amp;GUID=B3C57382-78E9-4041-98FB-AE0CB9011EE8&amp;amp;Options=&amp;amp;Search=&quot;&gt;amended&lt;/a&gt; its general plan for the area last year to accommodate the project’s mixed-use components in its zoning code.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Resistance to the project has coalesced behind a lawsuit filed by the Coalition for the San Leandro Shoreline against the city and the developer. The coalition is led by the neighboring Marina Inn. Opponents cited fears of displacing local residents and losing views of the Bay when speaking to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbaytimes.com/2016/09/29/san-leandro-shoreline-project-could-break-ground-next-year/&quot;&gt;East Bay Times&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/san-leandro-marina-development-faces-hurdles-despite-approval/sanleandro-shoreline.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;2013 master plan for the area, conceived jointly by the City of San Leandro and Cal-Coast Development (courtesy: Cal Coast Companies, LLC)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ed Miller, a representative for Cal-Coast Development, said he had personally never been involved in a project with such a long process, totaling over 8 years and 78 public hearings, with a local citizens’ committee providing community input. City Council had approved a similar plan &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mercurynews.com/2012/04/03/san-leandro-approves-plan-to-move-toward-marina-development/&quot;&gt;four years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It’s a frivolous lawsuit under CEQA, but it has no validity under CEQA,” Miller said regarding the lawsuit. “They’re using criteria like view corridors, which are not covered [under the California Environmental Quality Act].”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Miller alleged that the lawsuit was economically motivated, rather than out of any concern for environmental impacts. He based this claim on the fact that The Marina Inn has 18 years left on its lease, but is required to have at least 35 years to apply for refinancing in order to remodel or sell the property. “Our project would be providing a completely different hotel class,” Miller added, suggesting that potential hoteliers such as Hyatt would not create competition for The Marina Inn.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Regarding the proposed office space, Miller said Cal-Coast would not be leasing offices until they found a tenant, but the developer is currently “in talks with a potential big tenant.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Representatives for the Marina Inn could not be reached for comment.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/small-businesses-oppose-new-bureaucracy-under-prop-m/">
    <title type="text">Small Businesses Oppose New Bureaucracy Under Prop M</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:9719ca0d-5f35-3365-b654-9e61b317426a</id>
    <updated>2016-10-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/small-businesses-oppose-new-bureaucracy-under-prop-m/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Opponents of several San Francisco ballot measures have coalesced to portray the referendum legislation as “&lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;umb, &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;armful, and &lt;strong&gt;L&lt;/strong&gt;ots of &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;oney.” Widely viewed as an effort by the Board of Supervisors’ “progressive” faction to dilute the power of Mayor Ed Lee, a group representing small businesses held a press conference in The Castro today to voice their disapproval of Proposition M in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Proposition M proposes a charter amendment to create a new independent Commission of Housing and Development to have full oversight of the newly created Department of Economic and Workforce Development and Department of Housing and Community Development. Their functions are currently under the Mayor’s Office of Housing (MOH) and Office of Economic and Workforce Development (OEWD), which would cease to exist if Proposition M passes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Local urban planning think-tank SPUR &lt;a href=&quot;https://spurvoterguide.org/sf-nov-16/prop-m-housing-and-development-commision/&quot;&gt;describes&lt;/a&gt; Propositions D, H, L, and M as “piecemeal moves to chip away at the definition of roles, in particular to weaken the office of the mayor,” a persistent pattern since San Francisco’s adoption of a new city charter in 1995. SPUR’s voter guide primarily focuses on the proposed commission’s unchecked power to make recommendations on development agreements to the Board of Supervisors, especially with surplus land transfers. But these objections were hardly mentioned at today’s press conference.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Reporters gathered at Local Take, a small shop for locally sourced arts &amp;amp; crafts, were greeted by rousing speeches from Steve Adams, Vice President of the Castro Merchants Association, and Henry Karnilowicz, president of the Council of District Merchants. Speakers focused on the harm to small businesses an additional layer of oversight would create. The commission’s stated mandate of regulating housing production was hardly even mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“As anyone who lives near a commercial corridor knows, small businesses form the backbone of a community,” Adams said. He went on to praise the local flavor of commercial districts as far apart as Visitacion Valley, Noe Valley, and Taraval in the Sunset District.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“OEWD helps young people achieve their dreams,” said Derek Tam, representing the Chinatown Merchants Association. “I came here as an immigrant from Hong Kong. This is my first time running a business. The OEWD helped me with every step of the process, from raising capital to permitting.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Tony Winnicker, a former aide to Mayor Lee, stood in front of the group of speakers, taking pictures of the business owners posing with “No on M” signs. Winnicker &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Mayor-s-adviser-will-work-to-defeat-4-ballot-9211454.php&quot;&gt;abruptly left&lt;/a&gt; the mayor’s office on an unpaid leave of absence to lead the joint campaign against D, H, L, and M.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“This measure would create an additional layer of oversight over housing and small business growth, with no accountability to the voters,” Winnicker said. “The mayor gets three appointments, the Board of Supervisors appoints three, and the Controller appoints one. So we would have an independent commission, with no requirement that anyone have any experience with economic development. It’s ludicrious to claim that this would help create more housing in the midst of our crisis-level shortage.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What, in his view, were the perceived justifications for Prop M?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The people behind this measure don’t want more affordable housing,” Winnicker insisted, “they want to slow down growth. They want the city to remain frozen.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I pressed Winnicker on the issue of small businesses. If so many local business owners had come out to oppose Prop M and defend the Office of Economic Development, was the Prop M campaign attempting any sort of rebuttal? “No, they haven’t even tried to claim that it will help small businesses,” he said. “It’s almost like they just saw the word ‘development’ and thought, ‘that sounds good, let’s throw that in there’—because for many, &lt;em&gt;development&lt;/em&gt; has a negative connotation, and they’re eager to slow it down.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/dissecting-the-false-dichotomy-chatting-california-with-nancy-skinner/">
    <title type="text">Dissecting the False Dichotomy: Chatting California with Nancy Skinner</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:3e4de59d-c426-36dc-b405-82cb4151fd62</id>
    <updated>2016-10-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/dissecting-the-false-dichotomy-chatting-california-with-nancy-skinner/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a fan of Nancy Skinner ever since I saw her speak in a debate in support the idea of raising gas taxes. In a region crippled by underfunded transit services, it’s easy to overlook that highways are in fact our best-funded form of “public transit,” particularly when taxes on gasoline have remained &lt;a href=&quot;http://greatergreaterwashington.org/post/11871/inflation-not-bike-sharing-is-why-the-gas-tax-isnt-enough/&quot;&gt;below inflation&lt;/a&gt; for decades, but Skinner gets it. Her opponent for State Senate in District 9, Sandre Swanson, seemed to take a stance against them purely out of a blanket opposition to regressive taxation.
California, as many Californians know, is a complete mess when it comes to money.
Rather than approaching Skinner under the disingenuous guise of “objective” journalism, I decided to embrace my position as a fan-boy (I voted for Skinner in the primary election) and get to deeper questions about what California &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, and what we can become.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Even if she weren’t &lt;a href=&quot;http://skinner4senate.com/&quot;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt; for office, Skinner’s resume is storied enough for a hardcover book. During her time on the State Assembly, she penned successful bills to &lt;a href=&quot;http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billNavClient.xhtml?bill_id=200920100AB999&quot;&gt;reduce&lt;/a&gt; juvenile incarceration sentences, &lt;a href=&quot;http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billNavClient.xhtml?bill_id=200920100AB560&quot;&gt;incentivize&lt;/a&gt; the use of solar energy, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billNavClient.xhtml?bill_id=201320140AB48&quot;&gt;strengthen&lt;/a&gt; the ban on assault weapons. In the 1980s, Skinner sat on Berkeley’s City Council as the first student to have won elected office in the city.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When the &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; interviewed Skinner by phone, we elected to focus on her broader experience and long-ranging perspectives on California politics, rather than particular aspects of her current campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This interview has been shortened and edited for clarity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SFBAMO: Hi Nancy, thanks for taking the time to speak with us. Since you’re aiming to return to the State Legislature, I’d like to open by discussing some of Governor Brown’s recent proposals. First there was his “by-right” permit streamlining that failed to garner bipartisan support, but then more recently, Brown &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/news/article/In-S-F-talk-Brown-says-he-won-t-refight-Prop-6555024.php&quot;&gt;mentioned in a talk&lt;/a&gt; that he wasn’t willing to put up the fight to reform Prop 13 and CEQA.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Skinner:&lt;/em&gt; You’re kidding. What did he say?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Something along the lines of, “Reforming CEQA is the Lord’s work, but the Lord’s work doesn’t always get done.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Well that’s a real shame. In these last few years of his term, &lt;em&gt;we need him&lt;/em&gt;. Politically, he has nothing to lose, and it came about during his first governorship.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So aside from that, there’s his by-right proposal from earlier this summer. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/08/unions-against-gov-browns-as-of-right-housing-plan.html&quot;&gt;A lot has been written&lt;/a&gt; about how CEQA negotiation was a main obstacle to getting labor unions to support it. What can be done to get any sort of reform through this thick web of alliances we have in place?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Permit streamlining is one way, but it’s not the only way. We need to have serious talks about zoning and what its purpose was. Now that we’re talking about Black Lives Matter, how our criminal justice policies, sentencing, and incarceration rates have so damaged the black community—many [zoning policies] were designed for exactly that purpose. It goes back to the neighborhoods that used to have covenants that prevented Jews, Hispanics, Asians, African-Americans from being able to purchase property. At the same time you had redlining which the federal government backed, which prevented many of those groups from even getting a loan. We already know that much of our housing policies had racist intent.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Through the Fair Housing Act, we’ve begun to try to change that, but I think now we have to look at the whole notion of single-family zoning. If we dedicate large amounts of land to single-family zoning, when we have a housing shortage and crisis, we are explicitly assuring that the highest-cost housing is going to be there. If we look at the data around income and wealth, it will primarily benefit more high-income people, and the majority of high-income people in our country tend to be white.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;So we have to re-look at all of these policies through what their purpose was, and also, what do we want from a neighborhood? I think what we want from a neighborhood is: the ability to work and shop and get our childcare and education, and everything else we need, in close proximity. Some level of single-family zoning helps prevent that.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You mentioned in your interview with the &lt;em&gt;East Bay Express&lt;/em&gt; that Berkeley reformed its council elections after you helped spread some affordable housing around the city. Could you tell us a little more about that?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Berkeley’s district elections came about because the city council back in ’85—when I sat on it—was incredibly fortunate to be awarded some HUD money for permanently affordable scattered-site housing. We were very happy about it because it would be housing that would not be concentrated in one site, and could spread equity throughout the city. We fully embraced it. Then we started holding public hearings.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Each of the sites had no more than around 8 units. We were mostly picking sites we already had access to, whether city parcels or school district parcels.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In the course of the public hearings, some clever folks saw the opportunity to grab back power, started meeting with neighbors, and proposed district elections. The neighbors who opposed the housing jumped right on it.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The way district lines were drawn, those of us who were seated members of the council, three of the districts forced two incumbents to run against each other. They literally drew the district line at my house—now, I didn’t own the house, I was a renter—at Grant and Virginia. Grant is a small street, and they could have drawn it at Martin Luther King Way, but no, they drew it at Grant. It just shows the depth of what some people will do to stop development of any sort.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berkeley provides a pretty interesting case study of that dynamic. As I understand it, what we now know as the “progressive” coalition in town formed out of urgent pressure for rent control and tenant protections in the early ‘70s. While that remains true to this day, some outside observers have difficulty understanding how this grew to include anti-development stances, paradoxically, as a way to preserve rent controlled housing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Well, back in 1973, there was an initiative in Berkeley called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=djSlK1tuwjkC&amp;amp;pg=PA152&amp;amp;lpg=PA152&amp;amp;dq=berkeley+neighborhood+preservation+ordinance&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=17_EG48w9L&amp;amp;sig=O5_MzgzuVUoWERDJ15r_J-Gtsjk&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwiwvZO9lcLPAhUO-GMKHannAkUQ6AEIRDAG#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=berkeley%20neighborhood%20preservation%20ordinance&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;Neighborhood Preservation Ordinance&lt;/a&gt; (NPO). Before that, Berkeley had few restrictions on tearing down property. With the campus expanding and housing pressures growing, as well as BART opening, all of a sudden you had people buying up houses in South Berkeley, knocking them down, and putting in what some people considered ugly units, stucco apartments. There needed to be some design review standards, demolition control, some process, but the NPO, in hindsight, went really far. It wasn’t that there were big developers looking to build in Berkeley, but a lot of smaller owners.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At the time there was a wing of the Democratic Party on the council that was pro-Vietnam War, didn’t mind houses being torn down, opposed rent control—it created what in hindsight looks like a funny alliance. You had tenant activists, student activists, anti-war activists, neighborhood preservationists, Grey Panthers, all coalesced together. First they formed an organization called the April Coalition, which became Berkeley Citizens’ Action. Over time, BCA was not so opposed to development—they were opposed to big developers, suspicious of the profit motive, but they still acknowledged the need for new housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As there started to be interest by developers to invest in urban areas, and interest by the city to allow it, now you have these coalitions where some progressives say “there’s too much construction in Berkeley, developers are going wild,” while other people like myself say “no, we need units, we have great transit…we need to build more housing! If we don’t, no one’s going to be able to live here.” That is something that many progressives feel very strongly about. I think it’s a false dichotomy for some to claim that more housing is anti-progressive.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In contrast, there was a legitimate objection to development on Berkeley’s waterfront, on what is now Eastshore State Park. Not only does it have a liquefaction zone, but everyone deserves access to the gorgeous waterfront. This is where these things get tricky. There were progressives all throughout the town totally opposed to development there, but somewhere along the way, that nuance of good development and bad development got lost.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let’s take up the different but related topic of transportation. You developed quite a record on the assembly of pushing for renewable energy sources, particularly solar energy. How do you see yourself extending that towards transportation, which as we now know is the biggest source of Greenhouse Gas Emissions?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I used to create methodologies for counting carbon with &lt;a href=&quot;http://archive.iclei.org/index.php?id=10829&quot;&gt;Cities for Climate Protection&lt;/a&gt; [which Skinner founded in 1993], and we’ve known since we did California’s first state inventory, that the electric sector before we adopted renewable portfolio standards, was pretty low-carbon compared to other states. It’s still worth it to get carbon entirely out of the energy sector, but we knew since the early ‘90s that the majority of our carbon emissions come from transportation. It’s just a harder sector to get at, because in the energy sector, you’ve got a few actors; in transportation, you have millions of residents making transportation decisions every day.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I’ve always supported a carbon tax. Cap and trade is a little bit less efficient than a straight carbon tax, and I’m actually a fan of a carbon tax rebate. It helps address the inequities that cap and trade doesn’t. If we can design a revenue measure that gives us the ability to improve infrastructure, that could also be a price on fuel that could discourage the use of fossil fuels, then that’s a good thing. So far, the legislature has not been able to get the vote.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you think that mostly has to do with the critics saying a gas tax would be regressive?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There’s ways to design a tax so it’s less regressive. For example, sales taxes as currently implemented are pretty regressive, whereas the income tax on the ballot in Prop 55 is progressive.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This brings us to the broader issue of California’s fiscal problems. On the one hand, we have Proposition 13 limiting how much property tax gets collected, while on the other, Proposition 98 mandates a threshold for education funding. Is the problem, then, that generally Californians will commit to pay for progressive causes, but not agree to pay for it themselves?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Right. We have to choose between funding our schools and funding affordable housing? That’s not a legitimate choice.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you support Senator Loni Hancock’s proposal to reform Prop 13 with a split roll?&lt;/strong&gt; [Skinner is running to replace Hancock in SD09. &lt;em&gt;-Eds.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Absolutely. I’ve voted on it in the past. We had it before us in committee and it passed, but never got to the floor. I think we’re at the point where Californians are beginning to accept that there are some flaws in Prop 13.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In 2008, we had the provision from Prop 13 that California’s budget be approved by a two-thirds vote. As we got more and more Democrats, Republicans would negotiate by holding up the budget. During the recession, voters finally approved a majority vote budget.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Since you mentioned the Black Lives Matter movement, I wanted to wrap up with a question about that. The &lt;em&gt;East Bay Express&lt;/em&gt; was quick to bring up your numerous endorsements from police unions. How would you reassure someone suspicious of that?—since, you know, regardless of your other policy stances, one could certainly jump to conclusions…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;My record in the Assembly, and prior to that, was often opposed by police chiefs. Believe it or not, the bill I carried to require that all rape kit evidence was tested and put into databases, was opposed by police chiefs. The bill that would have adjusted the way that investigations of police misconduct worked, making some parts of the process publicly transparent, &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; large entities opposed that—but I voted yes. I think my history shows that I will be a strong partner with all our law enforcement agencies to improve public safety and put justice back in the criminal justice system.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be a partner with law enforcement in ways that are discriminatory, or lessen public safety. The last thing I’d say is that the misconduct we are seeing in videos constantly in a number of our police departments, and [the Celeste Guap scandal] with the young woman from Richmond, is so awful. I strongly support DA Nancy O’Malley’s efforts to prosecute the officers involved. But it’s a handful. Even if you look at officers that draw a gun, again, it’s a handful. I want those officers weeded out, I want them prosecuted, but we can’t take those examples and say all law enforcement is that.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Well that’s about all I had prepared for now. Thanks again and good luck at the ballot box!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Thank you, take care.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/supervisor-stonewalls-no-on-b-arguments/">
    <title type="text">Supervisor Stonewalls &quot;No On B&quot; Arguments, SF Libertarians Allege</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:dfac637b-9bd2-3cf3-87ba-e0b265a232c9</id>
    <updated>2016-10-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/supervisor-stonewalls-no-on-b-arguments/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco voters have received their ballot handbooks in the mail, and many have noticed that it’s awfully big and heavy. One reason is that there are record &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.beyondchron.org/sf-politics-skips-summer-break/&quot;&gt;25 local measures&lt;/a&gt; on the ballot, along with another 17 state measures and sundry races for public office. Adding to this are the various citizen- and committee-submitted ballot arguments for and against measures. In the case of local measures, there are both officially chosen representative arguments, plus a plethora of paid arguments.  It looks like there will be at least a small kerfuffle over one of those arguments, if correspondence we received from the San Francisco Libertarian Party is any indication.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The City’s Libertarians are opposing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwjD387f98HPAhVLyWMKHYYsAnYQFggcMAA&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fvoterguide.sfelections.org%2Fen%2Fcity-college-parcel-tax&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNH3IvynHlVVZ_5HykIN18v0jDzbFg&amp;amp;sig2=AB8Zq-cRyYDF7LofwZ17jA&amp;amp;bvm=bv.134495766,d.cGc&quot;&gt;Prop B&lt;/a&gt;, the extension of the parcel tax for City College. We may not necessarily agree with their principles, but certainly they’re entitled to express their opinion via the ballot handbook, either by submitting an entry for the randomly selected official argument, or a paid argument. Apparently, they were blocked from doing either, due to the action (or inaction) of Supervisor Aaron Peskin.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;According to the email the &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; received from Aubrey Freeman, SFLP chair:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a recent meeting of ours, one of our members offered to write an opposing argument to Prop B for submission to the DOE (Department of Elections) for the “free” lottery on August 18.  About a week prior to the deadline, we called the DOE for clarification on the pre-empting process, whereby members of the Board of Supervisors get first dibs at being the official opponents of ballot measures… Much to our surprise, we noted that Supervisor Aaron Peskin had pre-empted the opposing argument to Prop B… we decided not to submit our member’s solid argument (listed above) on August 18, and we would decide after the lottery what to submit as paid arguments the following Monday.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To our utter shock, when the DOE ran the lottery (and it really is random—they literally put crumpled pieces of paper in a jar), John Arntz, the Director of the DOE, announced that that no argument was submitted against Prop B and moved on to the next one.  What happened to Peskin’s opposing argument?  We checked with the DOE the next day, and they confirmed that Peskin was the official opponent but had in fact submitted nothing…&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;… There was no question about submitting the above argument as a paid argument… Three days later we received a call from the DOE.  In reviewing all the documents received for the paid arguments, they discovered that Prop B is actually a “district” measure, not a regular ballot measure, and as such no paid argument can be accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It gets worse. As it turns out, according to the DOE, because Prop B is considered to outside the scope of City government (the Community College District answers to the State), not only are there no paid arguments, but also Peskin, being a City official, was never entitled to submit an argument pre-empting any others in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It’s certainly possible that this was just a bureaucratic snafu. The problem is that Peskin’s associates have a history of playing tricks with the ballot handbook. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.planetizen.com/node/67821&quot;&gt;Back in 2013&lt;/a&gt;, one of Peskin’s ward heelers, Jon Gollinger, created a similar stir with ballot arguments against a measure that he sponsored in the June 2013 election – which, ironically was also designated Proposition B. The Board of Supervisors later passed an ordinance to prevent that sort of thing from happening again, but apparently, that doesn’t apply to State District measures.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/leno-expands-liquor-licenses-in-san-francisco/">
    <title type="text">Leno Expands Liquor Licenses in San Francisco</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:d52257df-7564-37cc-b72c-323568cc0e97</id>
    <updated>2016-10-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/leno-expands-liquor-licenses-in-san-francisco/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After the end of prohibition, the state of California restricted the number of liquor licenses it granted to one per 2,000 residents in a county. Many San Francisco licenses have been grandfathered in since that time, with over 1,000 licenses far exceeding the 418 allowed by law. Local businesses trade existing licenses in a steeply inflated secondary market. State Senator Mark Leno negotiated the issuance of five new liquor licenses to San Francisco County in &lt;a href=&quot;http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billTextClient.xhtml?bill_id=201520160SB1285&quot;&gt;SB-1285&lt;/a&gt;, a bill signed by Governor Jerry Brown last week.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The new licenses will be targeted toward outer commercial districts where restaurants may not be able to afford $300,000 for a license—instead, startup costs will require a much lower $13,800 application fee for a non-transferable license. Eligibility is directed at commercial corridors in the Excelsior, Visitacion Valley, Bayview, and the Sunset, rather than already-booming districts such as Hayes Valley or the Mission.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The new licenses are intended to increase business opportunities in neighborhoods that have seen relatively little growth amid the city’s vast employment gains. Ben Van Houten, Business Development Manager for nightlife at the Office of Economic and Workforce Development, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/news/2016/09/30/sf-new-liquor-licenses-jerry-brown-abc-restaurants.html?ana=RSS%26s=article_search&quot;&gt;told&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;em&gt;Business Times&lt;/em&gt;: “there are corridors without a single restaurant with a full liquor license, and others with only a few, when you have tens of thousands of residents.” His office initially asked for 28 new licenses, and plans to continue lobbying the State Legislature for more.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Should the number of applicants exceed the five new licenses available, the licenses will be issued in a lottery system. San Francisco will issue its first new liquor licenses in 77 years in September 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/caltrain-electrification-to-proceed-after-atherton-lawsuit-fails/">
    <title type="text">Caltrain Electrification to Proceed After Atherton Lawsuit Fails</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:83f0bc17-5ccb-38ae-804d-1b46721b9de9</id>
    <updated>2016-09-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/caltrain-electrification-to-proceed-after-atherton-lawsuit-fails/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Nearly two years since Atherton sued the Peninsula Corridor Joint Powers Board over the Caltrain electrification project, a ruling has come in favor of the project, validating the environmental impact report that was at issue.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Peninsula Corridor Electrification Project (PCEP) is part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.caltrain.com/projectsplans/CaltrainModernization/Modernization/PeninsulaCorridorElectrificationProject.html&quot;&gt;Caltrain’s Modernization Program&lt;/a&gt;. The plan is designed to improve Caltrain system performance, reduce noise, improve air quality, and is expected to accommodate increased system ridership through its improved service operations. An electrified Caltrain is scheduled to be operational by late 2020 or early 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Atherton’s basis for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.almanacnews.com/media/reports/1423535501.pdf&quot;&gt;lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; was inadequate completion of the Environmental Impact Report, specifically claiming that it failed to address the cumulative impact of both the electrification project and the high speed rail project also slated to run through the corridor. In its complaint, Atherton disputed the “standalone” nature of the electrification project, citing proposed Caltrain compatibility with the high speed rail, as well as shared funding, as indicative of a blended system that would require additional environmental study.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Judge Barry P. Goode of Contra Costa County Superior Court ultimately rejected this claim. Siding with Caltrain, he stated the two projects were independent of one another, and that even if the High Speed Rail Project “never take[s] a step forward”, the electrification project could still be implemented successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Stuart Flashman, a land use and environmental attorney who represented Atherton in the suit, has battled many infrastructure projects in the Bay Area. Earlier this year, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mercurynews.com/2016/04/06/cupertino-city-council-groups-initiative-could-raise-neighborhood-building-height-limits-to-45-feet/&quot;&gt;Flashman fought a ballot initiative&lt;/a&gt; in Cupertino that asked voters to approve a new housing and commerical development, effectively raising height limits from 30 feet to 45 feet. Flashman also sits on the Rockridge Community Planning Council (RCPC), and has frequently voiced traffic and parking concerns in response to several projects in the Rockridge neighborhood, including the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/shall-we-shop-at-safeway-or-safeway/Content?oid=2967148&quot;&gt;renovated Safeway&lt;/a&gt; on College Avenue.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Flashman also &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.westsideobserver.com/news/rogers.html&quot;&gt;represented litigants&lt;/a&gt; in an unsuccessful appeal to prevent housing construction in San Francisco's Parkmerced neighborhood (nearly 9,000 units in total, of which up to 3,200 units would be rent-controlled).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Adina Levin, the Project Director at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.greencaltrain.com/about/&quot;&gt;Friends of Caltrain&lt;/a&gt;, was thrilled with the ruling.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Caltrain electrification is a popular, highly beneficial, essential, and long-awaited project. It will help more people use sustainable transportation and relieve congestion, and it is critical to Peninsula corridor cities ongoing transit-oriented development,” she told the &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt;. Levin described the lawsuit as “a vain attempt to defend against high speed rail by crippling our region's transportation and land use goals is baffling...We are glad to see this lawsuit dismissed so definitively.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Besides easing traffic congestion, there are numerous environmental benefits cited for the project. According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.caltrain.com/about/MediaRelations/news/Caltrain_s_Board_Approves_Electrification_Design-Build_and_EMU_Contracts.html&quot;&gt;Caltrain’s website&lt;/a&gt;, an electrified system will improve regional air quality by up to 97% and reduce greenhouse gas emission by 176,000 metric tons of CO2, taking more than 619,000 daily vehicle miles off the region’s roadways by 2040.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-media-coverage/">
    <title type="text">Dispatches from the Vote16 Campaign: Media Coverage</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:2eb1ed96-2bdf-3330-b3e2-459bd0b86630</id>
    <updated>2016-09-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-media-coverage/" />
    <author>
      <name>Cami Doo</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yes on F’s media coverage right now consists of this column and the SF Chronicle’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/opinion/editorials/article/Voting-should-remain-a-privilege-for-adult-9206099.php&quot;&gt;editorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After reaching out to major and local newspaper outlets, Yes on F’s media team received no response from most. KQED’s Matthew Green emailed Celi Tamayo-Lee, Generation Citizen’s Youth Empowerment Academy coordinator, requesting to make a Yes on F film and to interview two students. Green manages the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ww2.kqed.org/lowdown/&quot;&gt;Lowdown&lt;/a&gt;, a news education site that covers politics aimed at students.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Green and Dayton planned to film our Sept. 8 meeting and Sept. 18 canvassing event. Fallout Pictures’ Todd Dayton served as the videographer, and the video is scheduled to come out mid-October.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Oliver York, a 17-year-old Lick-Wilmerding senior who has helped in organizing the campaign, was chosen to do an interview. On the basis of being an aspiring journalist, I was asked to fulfill the second interview.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;York and I were interviewed in the hallway of the WeWork building, where Generation Citizen has a conference room for Yes on F.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The interview started with typical questions, such as “Tell me about yourself” and “Why are you part of this campaign?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;More specific questions followed, including “What would you vote for if you could vote,” and, “If Prop F passes, do you think a lot of 16 and 17 year olds will be going to the polls or will it take a long time?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In response to the second question, I replied that it depends. The change proposed by Prop F will be rolled out November 2018, but the Board of Education still has to reform curriculae to prepare high school voters.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The goal is not just to get 16 and 17 year olds to the polls and to give an opportunity to youth who are passionate about actively engaging in their community; it’s also about increasing voter turnout. Of course, I think that 16 and 17 year olds, whether or not they support Prop F, will be eager to voice their opinions through casting ballots.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After the meeting, Green and Dayton filmed us canvassing in the Sunset District. Unfortunately, most voters were too distracted by cameras pointed at their houses. After the cameras left, I got my first “yes.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But what’s important isn’t my experience with interviews and cameras; it’s that Yes on F deserves more media attention. There are so many unique aspects of this campaign: it is a youth-led, proactive step to promote more civic engagement in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/regional-decision-will-be-made-locally-brisbane-mayor-says/">
    <title type="text">Regional Decision Will Be Made Locally, Brisbane Mayor Says</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:238203e5-7c02-327a-aaba-91a98fed29f2</id>
    <updated>2016-09-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/regional-decision-will-be-made-locally-brisbane-mayor-says/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The small town of Brisbane, directly south of San Francisco, has been forced to reckon with its own self-perception as a tight-knit, insular community. Recent efforts to build an entirely commercial project with no residential component at the vacant Brisbane Baylands site has drawn the ire of politicians from all sides of San Francisco’s political aisle.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At last night’s City Council meeting, housing advocates from San Francisco Housing Action Coalition (SFHAC) and Grow SF crowded the small chambers to support a proposal by developer United Paragon Corporation (UPC) to include over 4,000 residential units with office development. Mayor Cliff Lentz, hot off the heels of a media firestorm that erupted after he &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/nevius/article/Brisbane-pushes-huge-development-without-housing-9237957.php&quot;&gt;implied&lt;/a&gt; San Francisco should shoulder the residential burden, was cautiously welcoming of all in attendance, including news cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Mayor insisted that he had been misquoted in the San Francisco &lt;em&gt;Chronicle&lt;/em&gt;, and that he had merely been paraphrasing different proposals for the Baylands site. Many older residents placed blame for the controversy squarely on UPC, which owns the land: “Let’s be very clear, we are not proposing only office space,” one speaker insisted; “the developer is.” But such statements are discrepant with UPC’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/brisbane-postpones-decision-on-baylands-project/&quot;&gt;actual proposal&lt;/a&gt;, in which 4,434 residential units would help offset the costs of cleaning up the toxic soil on the 684-acre former industrial site, now an informal landfill.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“This is a very routine, perfectly normal process,” said Tim Colen, a former geologist Executive Director of SFHAC. Colen pointed to recent development plans on Treasure Island as evidence of other sites where soil has been decontaminated to accommodate residential development.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Colen also blasted the traffic study in the proposal’s Environmental Impact Report, which the council was meeting to evaluate. “This measures Level Of Service, while the state of California is rapidly shifting to measuring Vehicle Miles Traveled. It’s a measure of how much a project could increase carbon emissions.” Indeed, while the traffic analysis showed that even leaving the land vacant would result in increased traffic congestion, Colen noted that the proposal with housing next to the Bayshore Caltrain station would have half the amount of greenhouse gas emissions as the strictly commercial alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Representatives from both Supvervisors Scott Wiener and Jane Kim, deadlocked in a bitter State Senate race, delivered statements in support of building housing on the Baylands. Lawmakers on both sides of the county border have &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/nevius/article/Critics-go-to-town-on-Brisbane-plan-s-hostility-9393510.php&quot;&gt;raised&lt;/a&gt; the question of possible annexation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many Brisbane residents were irked by the notion that “outsiders” had come to demand regional cooperation. “I think you should allow Brisbane locals to speak first,” one resident told the council.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Councilmember Lori Liu took a cautiously skeptical view of the regional vs. local tension when addressing the city’s environmental consultant. “When we say ‘the community,’ what do we mean exactly?” She asked. “Do we mean just in Brisbane, the entire Bay Area, or the broader region as a whole?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mayor Lentz made the seemingly paradoxical remark that, although developing the Baylands was “a regional decision,” he considered it Brisbane’s responsibility to make the decision at the local level, because “that’s the way the law is.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When reached via email, UPC Director of Development Jonathan Scharffman offered the following comment: “I respect Brisbane’s pride in its heritage and its small-town character. However, if the City’s wants to deliver a world-class sustainable development for the Baylands site, housing must be part of the plan.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Brisbane will be holding a series of hearings on the site’s Environmental Impact Report, and will not hold a decisive vote until May 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/governor-signs-bill-for-teacher-housing/">
    <title type="text">Governor Signs Bill for Teacher Housing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:e21007ae-3923-34ee-8aec-a5f3d8c9e66b</id>
    <updated>2016-09-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/governor-signs-bill-for-teacher-housing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Governor Jerry Brown signed more than 50 bills on Tuesday, including one allowing school districts to build affordable housing for school districts. &lt;a href=&quot;https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billTextClient.xhtml?bill_id=201520160SB1413&quot;&gt;SB1413&lt;/a&gt;, introduced by Senator Mark Leno (D-San Francisco), intends to stem the displacement of teachers and other school employees due to soaring housing costs. Previous efforts to harness the existing pipeline of housing production to help teachers, namely those &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfist.com/2016/02/02/campos_introduces_legislation_to_pr.php&quot;&gt;spearheaded&lt;/a&gt; by Supervisor David Campos, were &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/opinion/editorials/article/Housing-protection-for-teachers-is-ill-advised-6802223.php&quot;&gt;admonished&lt;/a&gt; for incurring risks of violating federal law and disincentivizing landlords from renting to teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The region’s educators mostly find themselves too highly paid to qualify for subsidized housing, but not wealthy enough to afford market-rate housing under current scarcity conditions. Leno’s bill would enable school districts to lease land for affordable housing construction, and allow housing projects for teachers to qualify for federal funding.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“When high quality teachers can’t afford to live where they work, the entire community suffers,” Senator Leno said via email. “Governor Brown’s approval of SB 1413 will help school districts directly address the housing affordability challenges facing teachers and reduce high turnover rates.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/sfhac-honors-heroes-with-haughty-hors-doeuvres/">
    <title type="text">SFHAC Honors Heroes With Haughty Hors D'oeuvres</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:89ce3cee-6628-39e1-9453-3d173e40f18f</id>
    <updated>2016-09-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/sfhac-honors-heroes-with-haughty-hors-doeuvres/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night, the San Francisco Housing Action Coalition (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfhac.org/&quot;&gt;SFHAC&lt;/a&gt;) honored two “Housing Heroes” at their annual ceremony. This year’s honorees were Kim-Mai Cutler, &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2014/04/14/sf-housing/&quot;&gt;firebrand journalist&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Land_value_tax&quot;&gt;Georgist&lt;/a&gt; stalwart of the YIMBY coalition, and Supervisor Katy Tang, who spearheaded last year’s controversial &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hoodline.com/2015/11/city-planners-push-plan-for-more-density-affordability-across-sf-neighborhoods&quot;&gt;Affordable Housing Bonus Program&lt;/a&gt; (AHBP).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Under Tang’s leadership, the Board of Supervisors &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/7/13/12173076/affordable-housing-density-program-sf&quot;&gt;passed&lt;/a&gt; a three-story density bonus for 100% Below Market Rate housing construction, while incumbent property owners &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hoodline.com/2016/01/activists-fear-rezoning-plan-will-reduce-rent-controlled-housing-despite-assurances&quot;&gt;allied&lt;/a&gt; with myopic anti-gentrification groups to fight the rest of the bill’s provisions (almost entirely an implementation of already-existing state law). Meanwhile, Cutler’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2015/11/03/prop-f/&quot;&gt;exposées&lt;/a&gt; of California’s neofeudal land-use regime helped shape the discussion around housing affordability in the Bay Area to include a focus on the rising prices of existing real-estate, not just new construction.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As a representative of &lt;em&gt;BAMO&lt;/em&gt; and the SF YIMBY Party, I jumped at the chance to attend and be around &lt;em&gt;literal&lt;/em&gt; “developer shills”—an absurd epithet often thrown our way which, ironically, is entirely accurate of SFHAC. The nonprofit’s many industry members provide little to no funding for the &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; and affiliated operations, but those elbows were just waiting to be rubbed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In his introductory remarks, SFHAC’s outgoing Executive Director Tim Colen reminisced on past award ceremonies, one of which was held “at a tiny little bar in SoMa.” As a fan of greasy potato-based food served at dive bars, I briefly wished this had been the case that night.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The ceremony was scheduled from 6-8pm, exactly the range of time when my routine mandates dinner. Rather than schmooze with the assortment of real estate insiders filling up the ballroom, I focused my attention on the snacks. Uniformly tuxedoed waiters wandered the room, bearing neatly arranged hors d’oeuvres on varnished wooden trays. I teamed up with Corey Smith, SFHAC’s Community organizer, and made sure to sample each one, surprised both by excellence and mediocrity.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As Corey corroborated, the night’s biggest surprise was the outstanding excellence of the miniature vegan Mu-Shu rolls. My biases should be laid bare here: I can’t resist a good starchy delicacy, and am particularly enraptured by all sorts of buns and noodles made with rice flour. (Prepackaged udon noodles remain a weekly staple on my grocery list.) The ardent omnivore in me was eager to scoff at a vegan dish, but like many vegan pastries I’ve tried in the past, they turned out to be the best snack of the night. Ingeniously tied together with a knotted string of green onion, whatever savory plant protein lay within perfectly contrasted with the sweet plum sauce in the dipping bowl. Much to the waiter’s annoyance, I’m sure, I chased those trays down for second and third helpings. Naturally, I forgot to take pictures of the best dish.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As ad hoc “Asian fusion” slowly dominates my Bay Area diet—I’ve been known to throw udon noodles into curries and chili stews—I soon found myself turning my back on, even spitting upon my roots.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/sfhac-honors-heroes-with-haughty-hors-doeuvres/crabcake.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mini-crabcakes: an insult to parsley, inferior to red snapper&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Amateur litigator Brian Hanlon, founder of the suburb-suing nonprofit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carlaef.org/&quot;&gt;CaRLA-EF&lt;/a&gt;, insisted on seeing me sample a miniature taco. The very idea of it made my ancestors weep: a hardshell tortilla no larger than an olive, pre-folded, held half a bite’s worth of astonishingly dry pulled-pork and a tiny sliver of red onion. Benito Juarez, Frida Kahlo, and Emperor Moctezuma himself cursed me from their graves.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;My home state of Maryland prides itself on its crabcakes and not much else, save for maybe the highly processed, red-dyed salt &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Bay_Seasoning&quot;&gt;condiment&lt;/a&gt; sometimes sprinkled onto crab meat. It’s unclear where the crab for these miniature crabcakes came from, but in my humble opinion the dish would have been better served by imitation crab, i.e. red snapper. In what should ideally be a delicate balance between starch and protein, starch won an uncontested victory. A trivial amount of grease was all that prevented these bites from disintegrating into crab granola in my mouth.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A far more successful iteration of this concept came in the form of Caesar salad bites, an adorable fingerful of heavily-salted iceberg lettuce served in a thimble-shaped crouton.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/sfhac-honors-heroes-with-haughty-hors-doeuvres/hha2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iceberg lettuce and Caesar dressing in a crouton bowl: disruptive innovation in the miniature salad needspace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It’s impossible to tell when exactly the idea of miniaturized entrees replaced hors d’oeuvres of a naturally small size as the snack of choice for fancy cocktail parties. Is it the result of a sublimated craving for tacky freezer foods such as “bite-sized” pizza bagels, which the image-conscious bourgeoisie can only gorge on in secret? Or is it just the logical progression of gourmet consumerism making a mockery of itself?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Here’s where the parallel between the food and the developers become clear: the real-estate market responds to demands on a very short-term timescale. So does shitty food. When the Bay Area forcibly &lt;a href=&quot;https://diva.sfsu.edu/collections/sfbatv/bundles/218071&quot;&gt;downzoned&lt;/a&gt; its quaintest neighborhoods’ capacity to house a growing population, developers had little incentive to fight for long-term gains, opting to bake themselves into the labyrinthine bureaucracies of local fiefdoms to build what little they could.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Think I’m exaggerating? You should have eavesdropped on the conversations I heard.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We tell our clients that getting permit approvals in San Francisco is easy—relative to, I don’t know…”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Nowhere, really.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Right, exactly—unless you know the right people, grease the right cogs, let us shepherd them through.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Byzantine permitting processes don’t ensure better housing gets built; it merely guarantees that future tenants will bear the cost for these “shepherds” in the form of higher rents.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It’s no wonder housing gets approved mostly through a “pay-to-play” system in this city. Supervisor Malia Cohen found herself in hot water recently for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/pay-play-comment-costs-supervisor-vote-potrero-hill-development/&quot;&gt;joking&lt;/a&gt; about it, much to the chagrin of Supervisor Aaron Peskin, who along with Jane Kim, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/news/2016/06/24/sf-supervisors-aaron-peskin-residential-develop.html&quot;&gt;negotiated&lt;/a&gt; deals to exempt certain developers from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/supes-to-propose-charter-amendment-on-development/&quot;&gt;Proposition C’s&lt;/a&gt; 25% affordable requirement in exchange for withholding opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Another nameless interlocutor mentioned that at least 100,000 people drive into the Bay Area through the Altamont Pass every day for work. Though impossible to verify, examples abound of low-income &lt;a href=&quot;https://ww2.kqed.org/news/2015/03/28/long-commute-to-silicon-valley-increasingly-the-norm-for-many/&quot;&gt;workers forced to commute&lt;/a&gt; from distant, car-dependent exurbs from Tracy to Stockton and Manteca. San Francisco’s Sierra Club chapter finds itself &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@leighabeckman/no-the-sf-sierra-club-is-not-being-threatened-by-real-estate-interests-7b81eb36dc05&quot;&gt;opting for sprawl&lt;/a&gt; over shadows, rather than advocating for the dense infill development near transit that is necessary to curb carbon emissions from cars, as its national chapter &lt;a href=&quot;http://vault.sierraclub.org/sprawl/community/smartgrowth.asp&quot;&gt;recognizes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What on earth could explain this crowd of developers and their lobbyist cronies expressing such pent-up contempt for the property owners their predecessors so thanklessly served?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Above all, investors want certainty, just like I wanted the certainty of finding the taste and texture of crab when biting into a crabcake. For now, neither gets their wish. Even when a project offers lower returns to subsidize low-income housing units, in exchange for lower risk of a protracted permitting process, neighborhood activists demand more, financial feasibility be damned.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Incredulity abounded in the crowd over why anti-gentrification groups in the Mission focused all their attention on preserving the Mission’s built environment—“in amber,” someone said—as a metonym for its cultural environment, rather than directing their ire at the exclusive suburbs that ensure most production occurs in formerly affordable neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It’s a travesty that Palo Alto has only added 10,000 people since the seventies,” someone said. “Absolutely criminal. They should be sued for violating the Fair Housing Act. But where’s the political will for it? It’s busy blocking Google buses in the city.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But when the economy booms and there’s a surge of demand, migrants flock from areas of fewer opportunities, whether in this country or the rest of the world. Any kid with a computer can spend a year learning how to code and find a job in the Bay Area. I did—even though none of the jobs I worked at required me to write code, the wildly exaggerated coding experience on my resume gave me an advantage. (What is a Github? I still don’t really get it.) The real estate cabal I found myself drinking with and eavesdropping on will build the housing for them, no matter how much anyone screams about the evils of capitalism. If they can’t build in a wealthy low-density neighborhood where the influx of tech workers would be normal, then they’ll build in a more vulnerable community that didn’t zone future generations out because it couldn’t afford to: ergo, Rockridge and Elmwood, with their history of covenants and single-family zoning, see virtually none of the growth that is threatening to erode the diversity of Chinatown and West Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After Cutler and Tang received their awards, and Tang shared her award with city staff, they returned to their seats directly in front of mine. “Good luck getting the rest of it through,” Cutler said to the Supervisor, evidently referring to the AHBP. “Oh my god, I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt;,” Tang replied.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Capitalism won’t die tomorrow. I’m skeptical any momentum for such a thing could coalesce before the polar ice caps are fully melted, though we owe it to unborn children to hope for the best. On the other hand, there is more than enough political will to house the nouveau-riche in towering fishtanks casting shadows over multi-million dollar craftsman homes in white suburbia, with plenty of car-free options for getting around.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;If you want to eat the rich, it helps to have them living nearby. If you want to eat their food too, well, for me all it took was promising them I’d make fun of it.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover photo courtesy of Rob Poole, SFHAC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/a-jazzy-kickoff-for-propositions-j-and-k/">
    <title type="text">A 'Jazzy Kickoff' for Propositions J and K</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:03895079-f920-3320-8c36-c77853a8f68f</id>
    <updated>2016-09-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/a-jazzy-kickoff-for-propositions-j-and-k/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A crowd gathered on the front steps of city hall, brandishing bright blue and yellow signs. Across the street, homeless San Franciscans slept in the plaza, and another crowd had formed to watch a soulful funk/reggae band. The civic-minded crowd, kicking off the campaign for &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfgov.org/elections/sites/default/files/Documents/candidates/Homeless%20Fund-%20Legal%20Text.pdf&quot;&gt;Propositions J&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfgov.org/elections/sites/default/files/Documents/candidates/General%20Sales%20Tax%20Legal%20Text.pdf&quot;&gt;K&lt;/a&gt;, preferred to call the music “jazz” for alliterative purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Welcome to our Jazzy Kickoff,” Mayor Ed Lee exclaimed, pausing to make sure the crowd picked up on his allusion to the campaign’s proposition letters. Lee spoke briskly about the need to maintain a reliable sales tax revenue stream to fund homelessness amid the city’s housing crisis, and to keep people moving amid worsening traffic gridlock. He stood flanked by many of San Francisco’s political elite, among them Supervisor Mark Farrell and Department of Homelessness and Supportive Housing Director Jeff Kositsky.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/a-jazzy-kickoff-for-propositions-j-and-k/jk2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, business as usual in Civic Center Plaza&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I’m proud of the efforts San Francisco has made in helping our homeless population,” Kositsky said during his turn at the dais. The director insisted that the $50 million per year the ballot measures would allocate to homelessness were critical to help and house the city’s approximately 3,500 living on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;All hands in sight shot upward when Kositsky worked the crowd: “Raise your hand if you’re here to end homelessness in San Francisco!”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A similar call went out to all transit riders when several public transit advocates took the stage. If passed, the measures would allocate over $100 million per year to fund MUNI improvements and subsidies for low-income riders.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Nicole Ferrara, Executive Director of Walk San Francisco, honed in on the urgency of J and K. “Every street in the Tenderloin is a high-injury corridor,” she said, asserting that the city spent more in treating injuries from motorist collisions than preventing them. Ferrara proceeded to lead the crowd in a dual cheer: “We need K!—To get J!”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Indeed, several speakers pointed to the inherently confusing nature of the ballot referendum system to underscore the need to pass both measures: “J is how the money gets spent; K is &lt;em&gt;the money&lt;/em&gt;!” In other words, Proposition J allocates funds for homeless services and transit improvements, but if the 0.75% sales tax increase under Proposition K fails to pass, there would be no additional revenue funding those services.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After the cheer, the crowd coalesced on city hall’s granite steps for a group photo (into which this author was drafted) before quickly dispersing into the sunny afternoon. Some walked to their offices; others boarded buses; many others less fortunate, in all likelihood, had nowhere to go.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/four-decades-later-lao-analyzes-impacts-of-prop-13/">
    <title type="text">Four Decades Later, LAO Analyzes Impacts of Prop 13</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:fb75a44d-f9eb-3f65-8f7a-6363d1a971a8</id>
    <updated>2016-09-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/four-decades-later-lao-analyzes-impacts-of-prop-13/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last week, the Legislative Analyst’s Office (LAO) issued &lt;a href=&quot;http://lao.ca.gov/Publications/Report/3497&quot;&gt;a report&lt;/a&gt; on California’s Proposition 13, a 1979 ballot measure limiting property taxes. The independent agency studied its effects on homeownership, tax revenue, and local government land use decisions nearly four decades after its passage.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Prop 13’s stated purpose was to bring property tax relief for homeowners. According to the LAO study, Prop 13 did have this effect for &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; homeowners, while increasing costs for other households. High-income homeowners earn the highest amount of tax relief, as high earners tend to own larger and more expensive homes, and essentially have more market value on which to accrue savings. However, the report does find that due to Prop 13, households in the same city or even same neighborhood face vastly different tax burdens, even on homes that have the same market value, and often even across similar age and income groups.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Prop 13 almost immediately depleted tax revenues, causing local governments to seek other funding sources to make up for the shortfall, namely sales, hotel, and utility taxes. It does not appear to have deterred the creation of new businesses, even though new businesses face a higher tax burden than their incumbent competitors. Moreover, reassessments (which reset the tax rate) are performed at the same rate for residential and commercial properties.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;With respect to local land use decisions, the LAO report finds that Prop 13 may have slowed the formation of new local governments, which now serve more residents than prior to the passage of Prop 13. The study also looks at the impact of Prop 13 on zoning decisions made by local governments, sampling 73 cities of similar size and populations with different tax revenue makeup (i.e. property tax versus sales tax) to evaluate any differences. It found that cities with higher property taxes did not tend to rezone for more housing, nor did cities with lower property taxes tend to rezone for less housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When developers seek to build new properties, the costs associated with that new development must be offset in other ways by local governments who can no longer solely rely on property taxes. Impact fees are one way to do this, and pose minimal political challenges as they do not require voter approval. However, impact fees raise the cost of construction, which in turn increase home and rental prices.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;California is not alone in imposing these fees; nearly half of states have them. However, according to this study, California’s fees were almost three times as high as the average across all the states in the survey. The report makes only brief mention of renters, positing that “landlords facing slower increases in their property tax bills may be less inclined to increase rents.” Due to the uncertainty of this effect, however, the LAO was unable to quantify those benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The final question posed by the study, and implicitly baked into the measure’s aim itself: Does Prop 13 increase homeownership?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The LAO finds the Prop 13 reduced homeownership costs for some households, namely retirees on fixed incomes in certain parts of the state. But in coastal California, it has not. Since Prop 13 required local governments to raise fees on home builders, costs for new young buyers have gone up, leading to a significant reduction in their homeownership rates. Prior to Prop 13, households ages 35 to 45 made up nearly two-thirds of all homebuyers. Now they make up less than half. Meanwhile, the share of Californians who are homeowners at all has remained largely unchanged, suggesting that households aged 45 and older have made up for the losses of younger aspiring homeowners.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While calls for Prop 13 reform have increased as of late, Governor Jerry Brown &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/news/amp/In-S-F-talk-Brown-says-he-won-t-refight-Prop-6555024.php&quot;&gt;recently stated&lt;/a&gt; he is not interested in fighting that battle. Brown, who vehemently opposed the bill when it was proposed in 1978, rejects proposals for a “split roll,” which would allow commercial properties to be assessed more frequently than they are currently, arguing that its implications are more complicated than proponents acknowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-mateo-to-consider-74-homes-near-hillsdale-caltrain/">
    <title type="text">San Mateo to Consider 74 Homes Near Hillsdale Caltrain</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:11e31337-197f-391d-8e22-6ddef73e6b28</id>
    <updated>2016-09-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-mateo-to-consider-74-homes-near-hillsdale-caltrain/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At 7:30 PM tonight, the San Mateo Planning Commission will be reviewing permit applications for Hillsdale Terrace, a mixed-use development of 74 condos and 14,000 square feet of ground-floor retail within walking distance of the Hillsdale Caltrain station.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Owner LFG Properties are seeking to replace the underutilized site, formerly home of Taxi’s Hamburgers, with a five-story building that would implement the state density bonus law to include more affordable housing. LFG could legally receive by-right approval if they applied for a 35% density bonus, with 6 out of 67 dwelling units reserved for low-income households. But the property owner is seeking to build higher, proposing 74 units with 8 reserved for renters making &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; low incomes—effectively a 51% density bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The city's &lt;a href=&quot;https://cosm.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?ID=2842806&amp;amp;GUID=AC22E852-5976-49B7-AF09-6E4463B53198&quot;&gt;staff report&lt;/a&gt; recommending approval describes the proposed condo project as a “gateway” leading from El Camino Real to the quieter residential neighborhoods along 28th Avenue. The report also notes that developers will be contributing funds for landscaping the El Camino Real median between 27th and 28th Avenues, as well as improving crosswalks.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While some neighbors have &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smdailyjournal.com/articles/lnews/2016-09-27/planning-commission-gets-hillsdale-terrace-projecthigh-density-housing-sought-for-taxis-site/1776425168922.html&quot;&gt;complained&lt;/a&gt; of traffic congestion and excessive height, the transportation advocacy group Friends Of Caltrain are strongly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.greencaltrain.com/2016/09/san-mateo-planning-reviews-mixed-use-housing-across-from-hillsdale-caltrain/&quot;&gt;in support&lt;/a&gt; of the project. Adina Levin, Project Director of Friends Of Caltrain, shared the following statement via email: “This building is in a superb, transit-rich location, supporting the city's longstanding plans for the rail corridor and El Camino Real. We encourage and hope the city will move ahead with the well-established, effective strategies that provide much-needed housing and affordable housing, and take advantage of the great location.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Under the current proposal, the new building would provide 171 parking spaces, eight more than required by the city.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/white-house-urges-zoning-reform-for-housing-affordability/">
    <title type="text">White House Urges Zoning Reform for Housing Affordability</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:c0adbd7a-63e9-3479-b5a5-c430822b49e5</id>
    <updated>2016-09-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/white-house-urges-zoning-reform-for-housing-affordability/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&quot;We can work together to break down rules that stand in the way of building new housing and
that keep families from moving to growing, dynamic cities.” A quote from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spur.org/&quot;&gt;SPUR&lt;/a&gt;? A real estate lobbyist? Your libertarian cousin? Guess again: that was President Barack Obama.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The White House released a “Housing Development Toolkit” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/whitehouse.gov/files/images/Housing_Development_Toolkit%20f.2.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; today urging cities to reduce zoning regulations and increase their housing stock to ease increasing trends of economic segregation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The diagnosis is stated plainly: “In just the last 10 years, the number of very low-income renters paying more than half their income for rent has increased by almost 2.5 million households, to 7.7 million nationwide, in part because barriers to housing development are limiting housing supply.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Correlated with a drastic increase in local zoning and permitting regulations in American municipalities from 1970 to 1990, the paper notes a commensurate divergence in home prices and construction costs. While the cost of construction has remained relatively stable in the same time period, home prices skyrocketed. The paper suggests this growing gap is due to “land use restrictions that make developable land much more costly than it is inherently…and unnecessarily slow permitting processes.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/white-house-urges-zoning-reform-for-housing-affordability/potus1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The paper’s “toolkit” includes a number of wide-ranging policy recommendations, including by-right development, which failed to gain support in the California legislature earlier this summer. Other efforts to improve housing production, including the  elimination of minimum parking requirements, have recently been enacted in &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-modernizes-parking-regulations/&quot;&gt;Oakland&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/SevenDays/archives/2015/10/05/berkeley-councilmember-lori-droste-proposes-reforms-to-prioritize-affordable-housing-over-parking&quot;&gt;Berkeley&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The White House did acknowledge that there was a complex history to localized Not In My Back Yard attitudes, often motivated by concerns over human welfare. “Not all barriers to housing development have negative impacts,” the report notes, citing efforts that “can increase the supply of well-located affordable housing, address externalities such as environmental impacts associated with development, create better connections between housing options accessible to transit, and support the fiscal health of states and localities. But the accumulation of even well-intentioned land-use policies can restrict housing availability; create uncertainty for developers and limit private investment; exacerbate the imbalance between jobs and housing; and induce urban sprawl.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last week, Governor Jerry Brown alluded to these very restrictions at a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/news/article/In-S-F-talk-Brown-says-he-won-t-refight-Prop-6555024.php&quot;&gt;meeting&lt;/a&gt; of the Urban Land Institute in SF’s Moscone Center. The veteran politician extolled the virtues of judiciously picking one’s battles, and for him, addressing the shortcomings of the California Environmental Quality Act was not a top choice. “Reform of CEQA is the Lord’s work,” Brown said, “but unfortunately the Lord’s work doesn’t always get done.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/study-finds-rampant-ceqa-abuse-in-southern-california/&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; found that 99% of CEQA litigation in Southern California targeted infill development of multifamily residences, rather than greenfield development in rural areas commonly associated with urban sprawl. As for maintaining a balance of market-rate and permanently affordable housing, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/&quot;&gt;study by this paper&lt;/a&gt; confirmed San Francisco Controller Ben Rosenfield’s warnings that too high of a requirement could hinder the net production of housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Although growth is certainly happening in high-demand cities, the White House makes the case that this growth is not being distributed equitably, and can harm lower-income communities of color the most. “When new housing development is limited region-wide, and particularly precluded in neighborhoods with political capital to implement even stricter local barriers, any new development tends to be disproportionally concentrated in low-income communities of color, causing displacement and concerns of gentrification in those neighborhoods, raising market rents within neighborhoods experiencing rapid changes while failing to reduce housing cost growth region-wide.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Longer commutes from exurbs to job centers are only the beginning of an ongoing cascade of inequities that arise when growth is concentrated in areas such as The Mission or South Berkeley, for example, while affluent neighborhoods such as North Berkeley or Telegraph Hill remain virtually untouched.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-canvassing/">
    <title type="text">Dispatches from the Vote16 Campaign: Canvassing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:668f2fbb-3c7d-3e87-93f7-0098b1ea2a2c</id>
    <updated>2016-09-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-canvassing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Cami Doo</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cami Doo is a junior at St. Ignatius College Preparatory and a special correspondent to the Metro Observer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Canvassing and phone banking are essential parts of any campaign, and Yes on F has just started last weekend in the Richmond District.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A group of eight high school students from Lowell, St. Ignatius, and City Arts and Tech gathered at the Velo Rouge Cafe on Saturday morning. This was the first official door-knocking event of the campaign, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ngpvan.com/&quot;&gt;miniVAN&lt;/a&gt; system (the app for the Voter Activation Network)  had not been completely set up yet.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Celi Tamayo-Lee, the campaign’s adult coordinator, handed out paper lists and pens. Fighting against the cold wind, each pair of partners scrambled to organize the papers in order of streets. At least half of the group’s members were canvassing for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A practice round, with one person acting as the canvasser and the other a voter, helped calm nerves. After a cheer of “Vote16,” the group dispersed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As I rang on the first doorbell, my partner and I exchanged anxious glances. My hand trembled as I gripped the script in the other. Then the door was opened, revealing a friendly woman's face.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Except for a few fumbles, we smoothly started a conversation. I wasn't a first-timer to canvassing, but this was my first time directly interacting with a voter on behalf of Vote16.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The conversation went well, ending with the voter saying that she would vote yes on F.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The best experience, however, came from a Republican who said that she would support us.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;She empathized with the “Why 16” argument, saying that “life gets in the way,” so it would be better to form voting as a habit earlier. Also, she added, sixteen year olds are more open to different perspectives, as they are still trying to form their beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The other Republican I convinced asked, “Why didn't this happen earlier?” and said to his two-year-old son, “You're going to be able to vote in fourteen years!”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/head-of-homeless-services-talks-brass-tacks-in-reddit-ama-forum/">
    <title type="text">Head of Homeless Services Talks Brass Tacks in Reddit AMA Forum</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:324e07c3-db7a-3793-9301-70a6282499e6</id>
    <updated>2016-09-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/head-of-homeless-services-talks-brass-tacks-in-reddit-ama-forum/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As director of the newly-minted Department of Homelessness and Supportive Housing, Jeff Kositsky arguably has the most challenging job in San Francisco. Though the Department for the most part remains in preliminary planning stages, Kositsky made a gesture of “radical transparency” yesterday by answering questions from anonymous users on Reddit, using the site’s popular &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/sanfrancisco/comments/541co2/hi_reddit_im_jeff_kositsky_and_im_the_director_of/?st=itg33n9v&amp;amp;sh=4ba60852&quot;&gt;“Ask Me Anything”&lt;/a&gt; forum style on the r/sanfrancisco page.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kositsky’s optimism and ambition weathered hardballs from even the most cynical of critics. He cited San Francisco among the top three cities he thinks are addressing homelessness the best, alongside Houston and Salt Lake City. “There are not more homeless people/capita in SF than in other similar cities,” he wrote as a preemptive answer to questions he anticipated. “It is more visible here because most services are in the central part of the city.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Several answers underscored both an excessive stigma on mental illnesses, and a paucity of services tailored to addressing those needs. Reddit user Gorakos noted in their question: “It seems that that subpopulation only ever receives emergency care but has nowhere to go but back to the streets following an exit from the hospital/police station/shelter.” Kositsky replied that Direct Access to Housing programs (DAH) showed great promise for curbing the cycle of poverty among the mentally ill, pairing permanent housing with on-site services. “They look and feel no different than the market rate housing around them and are way cheaper than folks coming in and out of the public health system, jail, etc,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kositsky also pointed to future plans of a navigation center for mental health issues, as well as leveraging new MediCal funds to increase mental health services. Kositsky’s predecessor Bevan Dufty had championed the opening of the first “navigation center” in the Mission District, which combines shelter beds with storage for possessions and services for both singles and families. Dufty abruptly quit his post earlier this year, later &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/mutual-respect-admiration-dominates-bart-director-race/&quot;&gt;citing&lt;/a&gt; disagreements on the clearing of homeless encampments near Super Bowl City.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Director repeated in many answers that one of his top priorities was consolidating 13 databases into one data system for tracking the city’s homeless population and the services they needed. Kositsky told the Reddit user Acccounttt that he expected a timeline of 12 months to quantify the effectiveness of current homeless services. At this time, the city holds over 400 contracts with 76 different organizations to provide services for the homeless. Though he could not disclose the vendor for the department’s new data system, he promised a “real time dashboard on our website” upon its implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most strikingly, Kositsky urged respondents to move past the narrative of scapegoating the tech industry for the homelessness and poverty in the city. When one user asked him how tech companies could “improve their reputation,” he responded: “I do not believe any particular sector can be blamed for homelessness. The federal government stopped investing in affordable housing in any meaningful way in 1978. There are also some perverse incentives in the way our real estate market works.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Regarding the “perverse incentives,” Kositsky elaborated in another answer: “Homelessness is a failure of our real estate market to meet the needs of low-income individuals. Interesting that the biggest housing subsidy program is the mortgage interest tax deduction.” In other words, federal policy has been subsidizing middle class homeownership for decades, while leaving homeless services scrambling for grants and local sales tax initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many major tech companies, he noted, and contributed much-needed funding, labor, and expertise to the new department. Aside from donating and volunteering, Kositsky added, “about 5 tech companies sent senior engineers to our offices to help us make the final decision on the SAS [Statistical Analysis System] product we are using for our new database. Poor vendor had the hardest interview ever.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kositsky’s ambition is not only to efficiently track the city’s progress, but to take that progress as far as possible by &lt;em&gt;solving homelessness.&lt;/em&gt; In response to a question about “measurable effects,” Kositsky plainly stated: “[e]nd veterans homelessness by 2019, reduce street homelessness by 50% in 2019, end family homelessness by 2020.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Reddit user raldi responded by setting a reminder for themselves to check back on December 31st, 2018: “How’d he do?” San Franciscans of all walks of life will be asking the same question in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by Hyunha Kim, Courtesy:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfpublicpress.org/news/2016-06/how-media-coverage-on-homelessness-falls-short-and-what-reporters-can-do-about-it&quot;&gt;San Francisco Public Press&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/breed-succeeds-in-western-addition-housing-project/">
    <title type="text">Breed Succeeds in Western Addition Housing Project</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:4b8b2ec0-d986-36a5-8489-0846a81f152c</id>
    <updated>2016-09-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/breed-succeeds-in-western-addition-housing-project/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;These past few were likely among the most nerve-wracking in Supervisor London Breed’s career. After facing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/Feds-reject-housing-plan-meant-to-help-minorities-9146987.ph&quot;&gt;pushback&lt;/a&gt;p at the federal level against her Neighborhood Preference Ordinance, the Supervisor &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/breed-vows-to-fight-for-neighborhood-preference-ordinance/&quot;&gt;resisted amid rumors&lt;/a&gt; that her opponents had been conspiring with local representatives of the Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD). This week, HUD &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/news/article/Federal-agency-OKs-preferences-at-new-SF-senior-9238463.php?cmpid=twitter-mobile&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that they would allow neighborhood preference to determine the lottery for the Willie B. Kennedy apartments, although they still opposed the legislation overall.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Breed held a press conference this morning in front of the Willie B. Kennedy apartments in the Western Addition to announce the favorable ruling. The lottery for senior housing units in Willie B. Kennedy had been postponed pending HUD’s decision. Now nearby seniors will have drastically improved chances of winning a subsidized apartment, which Breed views as essential to stemming the loss of San Francisco’s black population. (The city’s African-American population has dwindled to around 5%, while also comprising  over 50% of jail inmates.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Passed unanimously by the Board of Supervisors last year, the law gives preference to residents within the supervisorial district (or within a half-mile radius otherwise) in the lottery for Below Market Rate units. Breed lobbied federal officials, including Representative Nancy Pelosi and Senator Diane Feinstein, and flew to Washington, DC with housing officials from Mayor Ed Lee’s office to meet with HUD representatives in defense of her legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Breed also published an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/powdered-milk-moving-vans-fight-affordable-housing/&quot;&gt;op-ed&lt;/a&gt; today in the San Francisco &lt;em&gt;Examiner&lt;/em&gt; excoriating her opponents for criticizing her record on affordable housing. The supervisorial campaign by millionaire homeowner Dean Preston is supported by local tenant groups, which Breed notes were unwilling to help residents of public housing when her own family faced eviction. Supervisor Breed, who was raised in the projects that once stood across from Willie B. Kennedy, noted that her place of residence had just been sold after the landlord’s death.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Even a San Francisco Supervisor who lobbied federal officials in her efforts to curb displacement faces an uncertain future in her city.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/toxic-soil-scandal-halts-hunters-point-development/">
    <title type="text">Toxic Soil Scandal Halts Hunters Point Development</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:5ccdf373-dea0-3da9-8e95-a88defdeeff6</id>
    <updated>2016-09-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/toxic-soil-scandal-halts-hunters-point-development/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Developers at Lennar Urban received a crushing blow to their plans to develop 12,000 new homes and office space at the Hunters Point Shipyard, from none other than the Environmental Protection Agency. The EPA ordered the Mayor’s Office of Housing and the U.S. Navy to halt the transfer of land in the former shipyard after soil tests conducted by Tetra Tech were found to have been falsified.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The former naval yard housed a military research facility for nuclear weapons, leaving behind deadly radioactive soil when it closed in 1994. After two decades of cleanup and even some new apartments filling up with tenants, the Navy has admitted that its contractor, Tetra Tech, took soil samples from a clean site and passed them off as samples from the once-contaminated shipyard. The accusations were &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nrc.gov/docs/ML1604/ML16042A074.pdf&quot;&gt;corroborated&lt;/a&gt; by the U.S. Nuclear Regulatory Commission. Indeed, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/9/22/13013980/hunters-point-radiation-epa&quot;&gt;Curbed SF points out&lt;/a&gt;, Tetra Tech quite literally covered up the dirt.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The federal agency’s understandable caution still provoked concern among city officials struggling to mitigate effects of the regional housing shortage. Mayor Ed Lee and Supervisor Malia Cohen, whose district encompasses Hunters Point, sent a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scribd.com/document/324834306/9-19-16-Mayor-Lee-Sup-Cohen-Hunters-Point-Shipyard-Letter?content=10079&amp;amp;ad_group=Online+Tracking+Link&amp;amp;campaign=Skimbit%2C+Ltd.&amp;amp;keyword=ft500noi&amp;amp;source=impactradius&amp;amp;medium=affiliate&amp;amp;irgwc=1&quot;&gt;letter&lt;/a&gt; to the EPA requesting a (“confidential if necessary”) briefing so they could understand just how long an investigation of Tetra Tech’s soil analysis could take. The 12,000 total units now stalled in the pipeline make up more than 10% of San Francisco’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://archives.sfexaminer.com/sanfrancisco/leveling-sf-housing-field-could-take-100000-new-units/Content?oid=2703869&quot;&gt;estimated housing need&lt;/a&gt;. Currently, plans call for 1,400 new homes to be completed by 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For the thousands of people struggling to find a home in San Francisco, the EPA’s delay spells a stark choice between commuting from distant suburbs, or risking a miniature Chernobyl in their own back yard.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/democratic-central-committee-considers-new-rule-to-handicap-grassroots-organizing/">
    <title type="text">Democratic Central Committee Considers New Rule to Handicap Grassroots Organizing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:9578c32d-0a8c-3f2b-a46a-05329d9de0dc</id>
    <updated>2016-09-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/democratic-central-committee-considers-new-rule-to-handicap-grassroots-organizing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The June 2016 election of the San Francisco Democratic County Central Committee was one of the most expensive in its history, with a record breaking $2.3 million reported spent. However, illustrating the adage that “money don’t vote,” the big spenders’ candidates &lt;a href=&quot;http://48hills.org/2016/06/07/lessons-june-7-election/&quot;&gt;mostly failed to win seats&lt;/a&gt; on the committee.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Reporting by the Reform slate friendly blog &lt;em&gt;48 Hills&lt;/em&gt; decried outsized spending on the Progress slate &lt;a href=&quot;http://48hills.org/2016/05/27/1-million-tech-real-estate-money-pours-june-sf-election/&quot;&gt;by a few donors&lt;/a&gt; - $25K from Ron Conway; $21K from Robert Rosania, developer of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2015/03/the-monster-in-the-mission-makes-its-case/&quot;&gt;“Monster in the Mission”&lt;/a&gt;; $50K each from Google; Facebook; Evan Williams, the founder of Medium; and $30K from Kevin Systrom, founder of Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Having swept the election, two members of the Reform slate, Petra DeJesus and Pratima Gupta, now seek to prevent large donations by amending SF Democratic Party by-laws to prevent donations to candidates in excess of $500. The amendment exempts the candidates themselves from this limitation. The proposed amendment reads,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Section 5:  LIMITS ON CONTRIBUTIONS TO CANDIDATES FOR THE SF DCCC.&lt;br&gt;
No person &lt;em&gt;other than a candidate&lt;/em&gt; shall make, and no campaign treasurer for a candidate committee shall solicit or accept, any contribution which will cause the total amount contributed by such person to such candidate committee in an election to exceed $500.” (emphasis added)
&lt;a href=&quot;https://d3n8a8pro7vhmx.cloudfront.net/sfdemocrats/pages/13/attachments/original/1474328101/SFDCCC_10-day_Notice_Agenda.pdf?1474328101&quot;&gt;See page 19 for full resolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A DCCC member who declined to be named said, “It is ludicrous to say we should have contribution limits and then allow famous (or already rich) people to run - people who don't have to raise a dime to win.” For niche elections like the Democratic County Central Committee, elections are won and lost because of name recognition, which favors established incumbents. 12 of the 24 newly elected DCCC members are current or former Supervisors.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“This resolution would cripple an actual grassroots campaign for the DCCC,” claims Sonja Trauss, local organizer and co-owner of this paper. “A grassroots candidate, with no name recognition, has to canvass heavily in order to win. Time a candidate spends asking for money is time not spent asking for votes. One $5,000 donation saves the candidate from having to ask 10 people for $500, or, more likely, 100 people for $50 each. I wouldn’t argue with a resolution prohibiting actual large donations - $50,000 at a time. Limiting the contributions to small donations protects the people that are introducing the amendment - incumbents.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Another agenda item to watch on Wednesday is Chairperson Cindy Wu’s appointment of a new SF DCCC member due to a vacancy. Leading up the the June DCCC election, a rumour circulated that the DCCC was going to be stacked with high-profile elected officials who, after winning handily without spending any money, would vacate their seats and allow the new chair to replace them with a Democrat of the chair’s choice. The identity of the outgoing DCCC member is not yet known. If it does turn out to be a high profile elected, the rumor will be on its way to being substantiated.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The next DCCC meeting will be held on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfdemocrats.org/meetings&quot;&gt;September 28th, 7pm at 455 Golden Gate Ave.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-modernizes-parking-regulations/">
    <title type="text">Oakland Modernizes Parking Regulations</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:abc3d0e2-b692-3617-b048-44c726013a8b</id>
    <updated>2016-09-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-modernizes-parking-regulations/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night, the Oakland City Council voted unanimously to upgrade its parking requirements for the first time in over 50 years. Oakland last revised its parking requirements for new development in the downtown area back in 1965. Councilmember Abel Guillen celebrated on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Abel_Guillen/status/778454029898612736&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, writing, “Hello 21st Century.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;City staff &lt;a href=&quot;https://oakland.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?ID=2825408&amp;amp;GUID=CA5A731F-E886-4E19-ADBC-EF00056A817C&amp;amp;Options=&amp;amp;Search=&quot;&gt;recommended&lt;/a&gt; the update in accordance with the 1996 Transit First Policy, as well as Oakland’s current Climate Action Plan.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The changes will affect Downtown Oakland most drastically, replacing the previous 1.25:1 minimum parking-to-housing ratio with a 1.25:1 maximum for parking—no minimum. There is an exception for senior housing, which would receive by-right approval to provide one parking space for every four dwelling units. Commercial space is now limited by a maximum of one parking space for every 300 square feet of ground-floor retail.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There are many more nuances to this legislation, including allowances for car-sharing services such as Zipcar. We recommend this summary on local blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://oaktownacorn.com/2016/09/20/reducing-parking-for-increased-affordability/&quot;&gt;The Oaktown Acorn&lt;/a&gt; for the full scoop.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-why-vote-at-16/">
    <title type="text">Dispatches from the Vote16 Campaign: Why Vote at 16?</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:7da21500-9efc-3240-a7b4-4dfc8c11bcc2</id>
    <updated>2016-09-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-why-vote-at-16/" />
    <author>
      <name>Cami Doo</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cami Doo is a junior at St. Ignatius College Preparatory and a special correspondent for the Metro Observer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco’s Proposition F, commonly called &lt;a href=&quot;http://vote16sf.org/&quot;&gt;Vote16&lt;/a&gt;, is a ballot measure that seeks to expand voting rights to 16 and 17 year olds in local and school board elections.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This campaign began in January 2015 when the Youth Commission passed a resolution urging the Mayor and Board of Supervisors to lower the voting age to 16. Two months later, , four Supervisors proposed a charter amendment. Fast forward to May 2016, the Board of Supervisors voted 9-2 to add Vote16 to the November 2016 ballot.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This effort is spearheaded by the Youth Empowerment Academy (YEA) and Generation Citizen’s Celi Tamayo-Lee The YEA includes youth ranging from ages 13 to 17 as well as a few adults. Generation Citizen is a nationwide non-profit organization whose goal is to instill long-term civic engagement into young students, and the YEA was born from the SF Youth Commission’s Civic Engagement Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Along the way, the campaign has collected many important endorsements. The San Francisco Democratic Party (DCCC), Nancy Pelosi, and all the Board of Education commissioners stand beside Yes on Prop F.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Prop F’s goal is to increase SF’s historically low voter turnout.  In fact, voter turnout in SF was 29% in Nov. 2013, 53% in Nov. 2014, and 45% in Nov. 2015. Other countries, on the other hand, enjoy a 80-90% voter turnout.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This non-partisan measure hopes to re-energize the electorate’s excitement about voting with a phenomenon known as the “trickle-up effect.” This effect will spread voter participation to parents and peers, increasing turnout all around (McDevitt and Kiousis 2006).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sixteen year-olds are embedded in their communities. 18 is a transitional age; students are moving elsewhere and do not prioritize voting. At 16, however, students can have informed discussions about the election with their teachers and parents. Therefore, when they go to the polls, they should be educated on all perspectives of the ballot issues.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Prop. F is certainly not a panacea for our low voter turnout, but it is a promising step in strengthening our democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-rejecting-bart-bond-would-throw-commuters-under-the-bus/">
    <title type="text">Editorial: Rejecting BART Bond Would Throw Commuters Under the Bus</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:0658c3ba-ab20-3786-b4ee-21985143e73e</id>
    <updated>2016-09-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-rejecting-bart-bond-would-throw-commuters-under-the-bus/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday of last week, the &lt;em&gt;East Bay Times (EBT)&lt;/em&gt; published an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbaytimes.com/2016/09/13/editorial-reject-barts-3-5-billion-bond-measure-east-bay-times/&quot;&gt;op-ed&lt;/a&gt; opposing Measure RR, a $3.5 billion bond to finance regional BART improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This was an absurd position to take. BART’s weekday ridership has increased by 30% over the last 5 years, now averaging &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/BART-can-t-keep-pace-with-rising-crush-loads-6192950.php&quot;&gt;420,000&lt;/a&gt;. Without sufficient funding, this high demand has faced increasingly frequent train delays, breakdowns, and packed trains. During rush hour trains, commuters are often forced to let several trains pass by before boarding.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Funds for capital improvements are needed yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;East Bay Times tells a boldfaced lie when claiming that up to a third of the bond revenue could go toward offsetting labor costs, rather than system upgrades and improvements. Doing so would violate California &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/cgi-bin/displaycode?section=gov&amp;amp;group=16001-17000&amp;amp;file=16720-16727&quot;&gt;state law&lt;/a&gt;. BART legally cannot use bond funds for anything except for acquisition of capital assets, or grants or loans related to those specific costs.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;BART projects capital needs of $9.6 billion over the next ten years. It has $4.8 billion already lined up, and would use the $3.5 billion bond revenue to cover part of the shortfall. BART is about 50% covered on capital funds needed, and needs taxpayers to help out with the rest. The full $3.5 billion in bond revenues must, by law, go to capital expenditures, i.e. system upgrades and improvements. BART cannot reach into the bond revenue bucket to pay its employees. Calling this “offsetting labor costs” is a pretty big stretch. Put another way, even if BART holds on to $1.2 billion for operating revenues, it would still have a $3.5 billion capital expenditure shortfall. This whole discussion of labor costs is irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As for the timing and tax burden property owners will face as a result of the bond issuance, BART has been forthright and clear about the bond repayment timeline.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;EBT&lt;/em&gt; argues that BART is misleading voters about the bond repayment timeline, since bond payments will actually be spread out over 48 years, and the text of the measure just refers to 30-year bonds. If you don’t look further into it, you might assume the tax will be paid over 30 years. But BART isn’t hiding this timeline at all. This information is included in the text of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acgov.org/rov/elections/20161108/documents/BondMeasureRR.pdf&quot;&gt;the measure itself&lt;/a&gt;, and is publicly available on its website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;BART anticipates that each bond will be paid off within 30 years &lt;em&gt;after it is issued&lt;/em&gt;, but BART won’t issue all of the bonds at the same time. Why borrow money before you need it? Instead, BART projects it will issue the $3.5 billion in bonds in equal installments every two years for eighteen years as the funds are needed to rebuild the aging system. This means that, from start to finish, &lt;em&gt;BART estimates property owners could be helping BART pay off the bonds for 48 years&lt;/em&gt;. (Emphasis added.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Issuing the bonds as needed is actually far more economical than issuing all at once, and is exactly the kind of forward thinking we want from our transportation agencies. By issuing bonds as needed, taxpayers will not have to pay additional interest on bonds that are not yet being used.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;East Bay Times&lt;/em&gt; tells us the tax in question would require property owners to shell out not the $37, $42, and $52 annually initially promised (per city), but potentially twice that. In fact, the total bill could even go up to &lt;em&gt;four&lt;/em&gt; times the anticipated amount, up to $150-200 annually.. 
This might possible in a technical sense; the maximum annual interest rate permitted by law is 12%. However, BART’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bart.gov/sites/default/files/docs/BART%20%243%205%20Billion%20GO%20Bond%20Measure%20Tax%20Analysis%20%284%25%20AV%20Growth%20Assumption%29%20Summary%20FINAL%20WEBSITE%20POSTING%208%2019%2016.pdf&quot;&gt;internal estimates&lt;/a&gt; peg the rate at 5%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What basis does &lt;em&gt;EBT&lt;/em&gt; have for assuming this rate would more than double? Interestingly, the only evidence that backs up the 4x tax claim by the &lt;em&gt;East Bay Times&lt;/em&gt; op-ed is a link to another &lt;em&gt;East Bay Times&lt;/em&gt; article, a page &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbaytimes.com/2016/09/07/borenstein-bart-%E2%80%A6e-original-claim/&quot;&gt;which no longer exists&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Even if the paper’s speculative math were correct, the worst case scenario of this measure is that the people in the Bay Area who own some of the most valuable real estate in the country would have to contribute something like $12-16 a month toward a critical regional service (rather than the forecasted $8-12 per month).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To that point, we all know that a huge driver of our funding gap arises from &lt;a href=&quot;http://lao.ca.gov/Publications/Report/3497&quot;&gt;Proposition 13&lt;/a&gt;, a statewide ballot initiative passed in 1978 that capped property taxes at its assessed value at the time of the sale, with increases limited to 1% each year. Without this necessary funding from corporate landowners and wealthy homeowners, our regional services have gone chronically underfunded. The cumulative impact of this measure nearly four decades later has proven disastrous for many services, including education and transit.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The cap on property taxes has forced the state to rely on nickel-and-dime fundraising strategies, such as increases in the sales tax, income tax, parcel taxes, and bonds to fund many public services. Most of these funding tactics are regressive in nature, putting an additional financial burden on lower-income residents.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Arguing that “BART needs to earn our trust” after past financial blunders is not a grudge we have the luxury of holding. The Bay Area is not going to stop growing. Urban think tank SPUR estimates that at the current rate of ridership growth, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/think-tank-calls-for-second-bart-transbay-tube/&quot;&gt;BART’s capacity will be exceeded by 2024&lt;/a&gt;. Wagging our finger at BART for past mismanagement will not solve our regional mass transit deficiencies.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The bond measure requires the creation of an independent audit committee, comprised of six professionals from various backgrounds, including public accounting, engineering, and project management. Skepticism toward the audit committee’s effectiveness should not undermine the clear need to fund improvements for BART.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Is it possible that BART will not perfectly maximize use of this revenue? Of course. That is a risk with any use of taxpayer money. If you are frustrated about “platinum” labor contracts afforded to BART employees, fine. But trying to stick it to a station agent by withholding tax money for capital improvements doesn’t change the station agent’s salary.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The loser of not passing the BART bond measure isn’t BART - it’s all of us. The BART Bond would benefit everyone, from those commuting on BART to those driving through lighter traffic, grateful that others are taking public transportation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/chinatown-activist-rose-pak-dies-at-68/">
    <title type="text">Chinatown Activist Rose Pak Dies at 68</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:8a39c267-db86-355d-8e99-10db452878dd</id>
    <updated>2016-09-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/chinatown-activist-rose-pak-dies-at-68/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco is in mourning after Chinatown’s iconic political activist Rose Pak passed away in her home on Sunday morning. Ms. Pak, who grew up in Macau and Hong Kong as a Chinese refugee, relocated to San Francisco in 1967, and was involved in the city’s inner political circles ever since. At the mayor’s request, the city’s flags have been lowered to half-staff in her honor today.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As the only Cantonese-speaking reporter for the San Francisco &lt;em&gt;Chronicle&lt;/em&gt;, Pak covered Chinatown with assiduous discipline. Her career as an activist came to dominate the neighborhood after she championed efforts to save Chinese Hospital, a medical facility serving lower-income residents who mostly spoke Cantonese.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Pak was also instrumental in bringing San Francisco’s current Mayor Ed Lee to power. After she lobbied for his appointment to the administration of Mayor Art Agnos, Lee remained an important figure in local politics, and Pak successfully pushed for his appointment as interim mayor to replace Gavin Newsom. She subsequently led the “Run Ed Run” campaign to convince Lee to run for a successful reelection bid.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The relationship between the two &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/A-gravely-ill-Rose-Pak-on-life-death-and-her-6456189.php&quot;&gt;soured&lt;/a&gt; when Lee appointed Julie Christensen over Pak’s chosen favorite, Cindy Wu, to replace David Chiu as Supervisor of District 3. In retaliation, Pak encouraged former Supervisor Aaron Peskin to run for the position, successfully ousting the appointee and rebalancing the Board of Supervisors in favor of the “progressive” faction.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though often labeled a “power broker,” Pak was fond of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/news/article/Rose-Pak-SF-political-powerhouse-dies-9230594.php&quot;&gt;saying&lt;/a&gt;, “if I were white, they’d call me a civic leader.” Pak will be missed dearly for her ribald conversational style and convivial demeanor. You can watch a sample of her fiery speaking style below:&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8KkvLOUZcnk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/">
    <title type="text">Local Profiles: Oakland's Ratskin Records</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:3de522cb-f5d2-3d5e-ae22-e1031c8c5bdd</id>
    <updated>2016-09-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When I returned from vacation in Mexico this January, I rolled my luggage straight to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ratskin.org/&quot;&gt;Ratskin Records&lt;/a&gt; anniversary party in West Oakland. The legendary Bastard Noise played a devastatingly loud set, true to their name, that could be heard with perfect clarity around the block. I finished a bottle of heavily discounted tequila I’d brought straight from the Distrito Federal with several friends, including Mike Daddona, the local impresario who had organized the mini-festival. Since then, he’s released at least ten new albums, hosted a visual art exhibition, and organized several dozen concerts.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;All in his spare time. “I do it to stay sane,” he says sometimes. “I’m not sure I’d know how to stop.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/ratskin1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Michael Daddona, head of Ratskin Records, assembles cassette albums in his home office (edited per subject's request)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Ratskin brand carries some clout in Oakland. The avant-garde, the macabre, the lurid or confrontational musicians especially know, just by word of mouth, “not just &lt;em&gt;anybody&lt;/em&gt; gets on Ratskin.” The catalog has been expanding all while repping almost exclusively the best of the East Bay: the lusty dance-pop icon &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/maya-songbird-writes-music-for-the-wild-and-weird/Content?oid=4647422&quot;&gt;Maya Songbird&lt;/a&gt;, feminist-noise reggaetón duo &lt;a href=&quot;https://ww2.kqed.org/arts/2016/05/04/wrecking-the-patriarchy-with-oakland-reggaeton-duo-las-sucias/&quot;&gt;Las Sucias&lt;/a&gt;, and mystical hip-hop crooner Tyler Holmes are just some examples of local acts the label has touted lately, all who do much more than just make weird noises by turning knobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RDlTgY5n5_c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3974232074/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ratskinrecords.bandcamp.com/album/maya-songbird-queen-of-darkness-ep&quot;&gt;MAYA  SONGBIRD &amp;quot;QUEEN OF DARKNESS&amp;quot; EP by Maya Songbird&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Voltage Drop, the monthly “industrial danceclub” concert series, effectively functions as press releases for new Ratskin releases, with a smattering of unaffiliated but much-revered artists as well. In the coming weeks, Daddona announced with a rare sense of cheer, he’d be hosting “five fucking incredible friends, out-of-this-world talented, like nothing else out there.” Tyler Holmes debuts his new cassette album &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ratskin.org/releases/rsr067.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Invisible Island&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the Legionnaire Saloon on September 30th. On October 15th, the not-even-remotely-secret Oakland Secret Gallery will host a quadruple release party with Maya Songbird, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ratskinrecords.bandcamp.com/album/slanted-square-three-sides-released-oct-15&quot;&gt;Slanted Square&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/best-tape-loop-manipulator/BestOf?oid=1921316&quot;&gt;Loachfillet&lt;/a&gt;, and Mike’s own industrial noise project Malocculsion.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mike lives in the McClymonds neighborhood of West Oakland, a triangular area bounded by San Pablo, Peralta, and West Grand Avenues. He shares a two-story loft with three roommates, each bedroom separated from shared space with curtains. Still, the oasis of a living room emerges in the middle of several shelves of records and tapes, which stored both his personal collection and his business. The room itself speaks to his endless productivity: next to his desk, there are approximately eight cassette-dubbing machines stacked on top of each other, forming a chain through which he is constantly recording copies of his releases.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&quot;I'll put in tapes while I'm cooking dinner, cleaning the house, sitting around, or doing chores. I can pretty much work on the label whenever I'm home,&quot; he remarked. His living room, in other words, is a small pressing plant.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;He took out a record and started spinning some shrieking black metal from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gzJecjdXXfI&quot;&gt;Gorgoroth&lt;/a&gt;, which made his visibly stressed and jittery roommate sigh and exclaim, “this is such calming music. I feel so relaxed now. Thanks, guys.” A deeply unusual atmosphere of sound came to life in the living room, the trickle of rapidfire trap-beats from the window curdling through the bass-heavy metal riffs.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/mcclymonds.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sunset in West Oakland's McClymonds neighborhood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For its quiet suburban appearance, McClymonds feels much more dense and vibrant than comparably whiter, wealthier districts such as Rockridge. Mike’s neighbors, almost all black, were out on the sidewalks, blasting music out of their cars, or otherwise soaking up the sunset. For all the groceries and amenities readily available in more upscale suburbs, West Oakland’s food desert has the culture and mixed-use density those suburbs lack. Large warehouses adjoin single-family (yet often multi-household) homes, apartments, and parks. Underground music and art spaces flourish in the area’s once-cheap industrial spaces, many landlords being eager to cash in by turning a blind eye to the legal grey area of non-residential zoning.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Artists move to industrial spaces where they can be loud late at night,” former McClymonds resident Max Allstadt told me once. “You can divvy up the square footage with more roommates to split the rent, and neighbors don’t freak out if you cut sheet metal with a saw at 3 A.M.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The neighborhood is both one of opportunity, drawing flocks of migrants for decades, and also limited opportunity, serving as an obvious reference point when discussing the region’s crippling social inequality. Daddona himself moved here for opportunity, from rural Connecticut. “I lived in a tiny town with nothing going on, so one day I just packed up and left. There were other reasons too, that I don’t want to discuss.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;West Oakland became a primarily black neighborhood after postwar industry boomed, attracting floods of African American migrants seeking work in the Port of Oakland and nearby manufacturing hubs. While segregationist &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2014/05/the-racist-housing-policy-that-made-your-neighborhood/371439/&quot;&gt;redlining&lt;/a&gt; prevented Oakland’s black population from moving north, a period of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=The_Rise_and_Fall_of_Seventh_Street_in_Oakland&quot;&gt;“urban renewal”&lt;/a&gt; decimated the community’s economic stability. First, the construction of the 980 freeway isolated West Oakland from the rest of the city, and then entire city blocks were razed for the construction of BART and the massive Post Office. Very little is left of the once-flourishing 7th Street Business District, though traces of the subsequent resistance by the Black Panthers remain in plain sight, primarily in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://qilombo.org/&quot;&gt;Qilombo&lt;/a&gt; community center.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It’s apparent, even in the most insular of the micro-subcultures that inevitably blossom here, that the demographic transition known as “gentrification” occurred before, or concurrently with, the inflation of real estate prices better known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.law.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/stanford-law-policy-review/print/2014/01/mangin_25_stan._l._poly_rev_91.pdf&quot;&gt;“reverse filtering.”&lt;/a&gt; That is, even the most recent transplant, in a warehouse party full of white college-aged carpetbaggers, knows how to allude to some nostalgic Shangri-La past that is rapidly receding.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I thought I had prepared with my most trustworthy stock question for an artist, intended to give a platform for a long, descriptive history of their work. “Did you think when you started this label, you would have expected to be where you are now?” Boom. Perfect. Surely this would prompt him to tell the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;His candor disarmed my clumsy cleverness. “Mm, yeah, I didn’t really think anything, really. We just did it.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Okay, so that didn’t work,” I admitted after an awkward pause. “Just tell me how you started, and, you know, we can go from there.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The “we” refers to his former band Sabreteeth, which technically started the imprint on their own with only minimal input from Daddona at first. They sound somewhat like a more punk-sounding forefather to current band Coral Remains (nee Styrofoam Sanchez), all featuring macabre visuals, psychedelic costumes, and pummeling industrial drumbeats. Coral Remains, a trio of Mike, his roommate JSon, and former roommate Ryan King (a.k.a. Bonus Beast), are notorious for littering the floors of venues across the country with audience-involved Styrofoam-smashing antics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=4123571802/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ratskinrecords.bandcamp.com/album/styrofoam-sanchez-empire-underwater&quot;&gt;STYROFOAM SANCHEZ &amp;quot;Empire Underwater&amp;quot; by Ratskin Records&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ratskin.org/thirteenseconds.html&quot;&gt;Triskaidekaphobia&lt;/a&gt; compilation CD in 2008, the imprint expanded into releasing other artists' material: specifically, 215 artists, each presenting a 13-second song. By the time Styrofoam Sanchez released their monolithic LP/DVD/comic book album &lt;em&gt;Empire Underwater&lt;/em&gt; in 2014, Ratskin was a very different beast. Mike had long since taken over operations after the first handful of Sabreteeth recordings, and his visual art on most album covers was more prevalent than any music he recorded himself.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It was never intentional, Mike insists. It’s as though he didn’t think about what he was doing until he was well into the process of running a record label. “It was just a fun, kind of absurd project. After that, it was mostly other people’s music. It just sort of happened. All of a sudden, I realized, ‘wow, so many of my friends are so talented and so hardworking.’ It just made sense to help them out as much as I could.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What strikes me so often about artists who move to the Bay Area, just as much as those who were born here, is their instinctive yet consciously irrational drive to do so. They just do what they do because they have to, full stop.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To Mike, it’s even “therapeutic.” It occurs to me if so many people are willing to take a financial loss to find purpose through the help of therapy, it seems odd that it is far less taboo to criticize the logical utility of art than that of psychological counseling. Perhaps we recognize it would be rude to interrogate those who seek “treatment” to get “better,” whereas artists and audiences both know that their madness is the treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/ratskin5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent Ratskin releases from Black Dog, Coral Remains, and Black Spirituals, respectively. (courtesy: M. Daddona)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But just to humor myself, I press a bit more on the question of the label’s financial stability. For example, how do his choices of material affect his overhead costs? “There are some things I like about tapes—mostly that they’ll probably last a lot longer than the CD-R….In a lot of ways, I feel like it doesn’t really matter. If we could afford to put everything out on vinyl, we would, but we’re not at that point. Hopefully one day.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Every question from then on became a springboard for some optimistic goal. Mike alludes to upcoming efforts to expand into book projects, one-time art installations, and whatever else he might find worth sharing. The label co-presents the aforementioned monthly DJ night, “Voltage Drop,” at the Legionnaire Saloon in Uptown Oakland. Each party typically features one or two future or upcoming Ratskin-affiliated artists, with a collection of free physical mixtapes available for early bird arrivals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The label itself has ballooned into a planned twenty-album backlog. “There are ten upcoming releases I have confirmed and can announce, and there’s ten I can’t mention just yet.” For a well-established label with multiple paid employees, this isn’t a stretch; for a one-man operation that intentionally takes a loss (with the eventual goal of breaking even, I’m assured), it is an insane amount.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Given this surge in productivity, I questioned an earlier remark he made that the label was guided by an effort to give voice to those who might not always feel comfortable or confident. Had he ever had to actively convince someone to publicize their music?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Well, look—you can’t book everyone, and you can’t release everyone. The label is there as a resource for artists, document works I think should be documented, and push people to do projects they might not feel fit in anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“People like to keep all these secrets in music, and guard their craft, because if you figure out their trick, then they worry that their whole shtick will break down.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“You mean, everyone will realize it’s not that hard, and they can do it too?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, exactly. And that’s good. I mean, I love punk and I love conceptual art, but I also hate punk and I hate conceptual art. I’m just trying to take what’s good out of different artistic movements and…well, archiving is what I’m doing, not even documenting.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At first it doesn’t occur to me what the difference could possibly be. Again, the intentional-yet-intuitive idea comes to mind. Does documenting mean you plan to do it, while archiving is more of a rote act?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In Ratskin’s case, the “archiving” in itself stands out as a deliberate art. At times, he says, it has merely been a matter of a prolific live performer not having access to recording equipment. He calls subsequent relationships a “collaboration,” and it’s in many ways an entry into a deeply connected musical family. Artists on the Ratskin catalogue often cross-promote, tour together, share the stage on local bills&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On the same desk where he cuts covers for new tapes, he has two final remaining copies of a 10-cassette box set, sealed with a piezoelectric contact microphone, with twenty artists each splitting a side of a five-minute tape. He’s almost done making copies for the final box.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/ratskin4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;10-cassette box set sealed with a contact mic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The constant work-in-progress, on a lizard-brain good-vibes level, simply feels like a much better deal for both the consumer and the producer, even though he makes a net loss at press time. An economist reading this might shake their head in disbelief—or maybe it’s just aspiring artists’ concerned parents.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To put it into economic terms, these artists tend not to care if they make a return on capital investments. The transaction itself is the profit. Monetary profit is a far lower priority than the exponentially growing payoff of helping other artists along their way.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There are some artists for whom he is confident he has done his part to help, and have moved beyond any semblance of “needing him.” Oakland’s blistering, explosive free-jazz duo Black Spirituals was recently praised by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/09/24/arts/music/review-black-spirituals-a-duo-that-defies-categories.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rolling Stone&lt;/em&gt;, the latter giving a nod to their Ratskin tape &lt;em&gt;Black Interiors&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Everyone should have their own label,” he adds. “All of the bands I was inspired by did just hack-job shows, driving for hours to play to twenty people… If every Ratskin artist could tour and get paid for every show they played, that would be a great thing. I’m just lucky to have so many talented friends, and that’s the only reason I do the label. All the real work is done by the artist, and I’m just here to contextualize this.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though he is modest about this contextualizing, it’s far from insignificant.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In person, Mike is never shy about Ratskin’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imposemagazine.com/music/ratskin&quot;&gt;principled efforts&lt;/a&gt; to support marginalized communities. He was reticent at first, in light of my newfound status as “the press” asking questions, to go into detail again. It didn’t take long for him to open up on the subject, though, given that Ratskin explicitly foregrounds black and brown voices in the music scene, many being native to the Bay Area.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It was inevitable, really, two straight white dudes sitting on a couch listening to metal, while the sounds of his black neighborhood and their very different music choices poured in constantly. “Sure, I’m a gentrifier,” he says when I bring up the subject. “I mean, look around you. Of course I’m part of this neighborhood changing. But also, these are my friends. We talk to each other, we hang out, share things, like regular human beings. All it takes to not be a bad gentrifier is, you know, just don’t be a fucking idiot.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Indeed, before the interview began in earnest, we passed around a blunt with some neighbors and shot the shit. We were a bit sluggish and dazed when the interview started. After half an hour or so, it didn’t feel right to close ourselves off like that, so we turned off the music and recording equipment, opened the front door, and rolled another one.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It should be easy to not be a “fucking idiot,” but that doesn’t mean it’s not hard work sometimes. The proof is in the bags under Mike’s eyes. On days when he does contracting work, he gets up before 5 A.M. to cross the Bay Bridge before rush-hour traffic. The irregular hours make it easier to be involved in nightlife on the weekends, and tour across the country for a few weeks at a time. When he’s home, he’s dubbing tapes, booking concerts, or recording music.  The spools keep spinning the tape, spinning over and over to stave off the madness.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-candidates-talk-quality-of-life-and-regional-growth-in-forum/">
    <title type="text">Palo Alto Candidates Talk Quality of Life and Regional Growth in Forum</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:bb00e3af-03fd-3a8f-a605-3b1a82739f99</id>
    <updated>2016-09-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-candidates-talk-quality-of-life-and-regional-growth-in-forum/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Palo Alto is the epicenter of entrepreneurship in Silicon Valley, but it has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/opinion/editorials/article/Palo-Alto-decides-it-has-too-much-of-a-good-thing-9200819.php&quot;&gt;too many jobs&lt;/a&gt;. That at least is the tenor of the Peninsula city’s civic mood, where a moratorium on new office development coincides with fierce &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/tweets-from-the-front-palo-alto-city-council-coverage/&quot;&gt;controversy over apartments&lt;/a&gt; near Caltrain with less than one parking spot per resident.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Eleven candidates for city council in Palo Alto gathered in the main chambers of city hall for a moderated &lt;a href=&quot;ttp://www.paloaltoonline.com/news/2016/09/16/council-candidates-make-their-pitches-at-palo-alto-forum&quot;&gt;forum&lt;/a&gt; on September 14th, in which infrastructure and fiscal responsibility dominated what generally amounted to a contest of optimism. Liz Kniss is the only sitting councilmember seeking reelection in this cycle. Young or old, incumbent or newcomer, each couched their plans for addressing Palo Alto’s housing and transportation woes in terms of enduring, positive progress.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Palo Alto native and sitting Planning and Transportation Commission chair &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.votefine.com/&quot;&gt;Adrian Fine&lt;/a&gt; spoke of aiming for a “21st century approach” to transportation, and others joined in his suggestion that Autonomous Vehicles may soon change the paradigm around transportation planning, parking, and traffic. (Fine, a native of Palo Alto, studied city planning at the University of Pennsylvania.) Leonard Ely III, an older candidate, made the further suggestion that the entire Bay Area should consider merging its transit agencies to reduce the cost per person.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Palo Alto’s ratio of jobs to housing is estimated at 3-to-1, with effectively half of its peak population commuting in and out from increasingly distant places. The city’s housing shortage recently came under national scrutiny after Planning Commissioner Kate Downing publicly announce her departure, opting to raise her high-earning dual-income family in the relatively more affordable city of Santa Cruz.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gregtanaka&quot;&gt;Greg Tanaka&lt;/a&gt;, former chair of the Planning Commission, was keen on connecting transportation with the region’s soaring housing costs. He spoke of a need to “minimize impacts through smaller units” and encourage “multiple transportation modalities,” sharing optimistic goals in spite of his hardships as a small business owner struggling to retain rent-burdened employees.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Incumbent Liz Kniss joined others in the forum expressing more caution over the city’s growing pains. “I fear driving down the street one day and seeing only multi-million dollar homes,” Kniss lamented, urging attendees to support more affordable alternatives. (Palo Alto’s median &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zillow.com/palo-alto-ca/home-values/&quot;&gt;home price&lt;/a&gt; is currently $2.4 million.) Referring to the imbalance of office space and housing in the city, Stewart Carl added, “We cannot possibly build that much living space in Palo Alto without compromising our quality of life.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Greer Stone, one of the younger candidates, was quick to parry with positive policy goals of greater housing density and improved public transit. “Let’s build housing near jobs,” he said straightforwardly at one point, “to get people out of their cars.” This idea received pushback from Lydia Kou, who called for the construction of more parking garages along with increased VTA bus service.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Curiously, Stone’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.greerstone.com/&quot;&gt;campaign website&lt;/a&gt; echoes the concerns of several older candidates. His platform reads, in part: “Overdevelopment threatens the continuing success of our schools, impact on traffic, parkland preservation, pollution, parking, and retail. We must balance the need for additional housing with the concerns of the surrounding neighborhoods and the collateral impact on schools, traffic, pollution, and public services.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Current Planning Commission chair Adrian Fine took the most risk in balancing optimistic policy with cold, hard reality. “I grew up in a compassionate place,” he said when the candidates recounted their favorite aspects of living in Palo Alto. “As our teachers, our nurses, our firefighters find it increasingly hard to live here, we risk losing some of that compassion.” Other candidates were quick to pounce on the negative angle, insisting that their community still retained plenty of compassion.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When I reached Fine by phone, my first question was simply a clarification: what did he mean by compassion?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“My compassionate community was a place where I’d clean my neighbor’s car, or where the man down the street had been my mother’s professor. As we’ve seen a reduction in our income, age, and cultural diversity, while becoming a global center for technological innovation, we’ve lost a lot of that.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Fine constantly alluded to a bedrock of principles underlying his campaign, independent of specific policies. “I don’t care about building or not building—the issue is the community values that we share. Issues like diversity, creativity, the environment. If we believe in those, there are some choices we need to make. In order to support a diverse community, we need to have more housing options and we need to invest in transportation.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;His answers came as a rapidfire list of concrete ideas bound tightly to platitudes, like hydrogen bonding with oxygen. The conversation became increasingly candid after that.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We need to make sure that future generations can live out and foster those values,” he reiterated. “I graduated with slightly under 400 students from my high school twelve years ago. There’s now about five of us left in Palo Alto. That’s not normal. So it’s not really about the buildings—that’s the last step, actually.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What, then, did he see as the first steps?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“In Palo Alto, we built the Oregon Expressway, and we have huge parking lots. Now we’re coming to the conclusion that, gosh, we built our city for cars, there’s a huge environmental and social cost to that. We’re out of space for roads in Palo Alto. Do we use existing infill space for cars or for people?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“My fiancée and I don’t own cars,” he added, “and many of our friends don’t. We take Uber or Lyft, we bike, we walk, we take Caltrain. With ridesharing, autonomous cars, and electric vehicles, that’s progress that’s happening &lt;em&gt;right here&lt;/em&gt;. I think we should be a leader in that.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I followed up by asking if people were ever shocked to discover that he lived in Palo Alto without a car. As a former carless resident of the area myself, I couldn’t imagine it being easy. “Sometimes—well, no, not really,” Fine said. “I live a five-minute bike ride from the train, from groceries. To some of our seniors, that may not be an option—in some neighborhoods they have less commercial access, which is something we need to work on. In Palo Alto, 8% of trips are done by bike. That’s pretty big—after Davis, Portland, maybe Boulder. Palo Alto is very flat, with great bike boulevards. And there’s Stanford, of course.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Stanford can circumvent local government, and has much broader control over its land. Absent those privileges, Fine sees Palo Alto at a crossroads where it must choose regional cooperation. “The Bay Area is 110 cities, nine counties, 24 transit systems—that’s a really hard region to work in. Given our reality, we’ve got to work overtime.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Many communities are envious of Palo Alto’s success, and our quality of life,” he continued. “I believe we need to maintain that and improve it—in some cases that means change. I’m a proponent of managing change effectively.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In our interview, Fine was passionate and animated, yet spoke with the measured cadence of a well-rehearsed veteran politician. Optimism and tempered outrage strike a careful balance in the city’s political atmosphere. The next forum will be held on September 29th, hosted by neighborhood groups, also in council chambers.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo courtesy of Gary Fine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/foster-city-considers-68-units-in-commercial-zone/">
    <title type="text">Foster City Considers 68 Units in Commercial Zone</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:0c0659f6-86d3-33db-bef3-bc0816d889ff</id>
    <updated>2016-09-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/foster-city-considers-68-units-in-commercial-zone/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Foster City managed to go from a landfill to a flourishing planned suburb in less than a century. Last night, the city’s Planning Commission debated how exactly that trajectory might continue on a parcel known as “Phase C” on Triton Drive. Developers at the Sares Regis Group hope to receive a rezoning for the area, largely allotted for office space, in order to provide &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/68-units-proposed-in-foster-city/&quot;&gt;68 townhomes&lt;/a&gt; with a shuttle service to the nearby Caltrain station.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The most vocal members of the Commission voiced concern that rezoning for more housing could slow the city’s commercial growth. The parcel is currently only zoned for 17 residential units. Commissioner and former mayor Richard Wykoff led the charge, arguing that there was “a conflict between downsizing the commercial space and the economic plan.” He strongly favored a compromise suggested by the Planning Department to build a hotel there instead, though no such project has been proposed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/foster-city-considers-68-units-in-commercial-zone/phasecfc.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infographic detailing predicted benefits of the new development (courtesy: Sares Regis)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While some local business owners did express concern over the loss of commercial space, the majority of local residents generally supported the additional townhomes. Commissioner Noemi Avram seemed more receptive to these views, noting that Foster City is the only locality on the Peninsula to require 20% Below Market Rate units on new construction. Foster City currently only has seven such units, so Phase C would effectively triple the amount of permanently affordable housing within city limits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco housing advocate Laura Clark, founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.growsanfrancisco.org/&quot;&gt;Grow SF&lt;/a&gt;, commented on what she perceived as a markedly tone-deaf atmosphere at the meeting. “The Commission, most prominently voiced by Wykoff, showed no concern for the fact that they are only 68% of the way toward meeting the minimum of their &lt;a href=&quot;http://fostercity.org/departmentsanddivisions/communitydevelopment/Features/upload/HOUSING-ELEMENT-ADOPTED-2-2-2015.pdf&quot;&gt;regional housing obligation&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night's meeting was a study session, so no legislative action was taken.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/as-millennium-tower-sinks-blame-game-ensues/">
    <title type="text">As Millennium Tower Sinks, Blame Game Ensues</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:cecf4c42-ee4e-33ad-a603-ef1a42734035</id>
    <updated>2016-09-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/as-millennium-tower-sinks-blame-game-ensues/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Once intended to be Downtown San Francisco’s most appealing luxury condominium high-rise, the Millennium Tower has instead become a convenient symbol of the tragicomic hubris underlying the city’s real estate market. But whose hubris?—This has become the subject of heated debate, embroiling an ever-growing cast of characters in all sectors. According to those involved, who exactly bears the blame for the tower’s unstable property values and physical structure, sinking three inches at its base and sixteen inches on the top floor, is everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Aaron Peskin has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/supervisor-peskin-blames-faulty-millennium-tower-political-interference-plans-lead-investigation/&quot;&gt;called for an investigation&lt;/a&gt; into the tower’s faulty foundation, suggesting that “political interference” may have rushed the building’s approval in 2009. Condo owners in the building launched a &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/class-action-lawsuit-filed-against-millennium-tower-developer/&quot;&gt;class-action lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; alleging negligence on the part of developer Millennium Properties as well as the Transbay Joint Powers Association, which built its new terminal into the foundation of the tower. Both plaintiffs in the suit have blamed each other in decidedly undiplomatic press statements this week.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Transbay agency released a preemptive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CtVteemLin4&quot;&gt;“I didn’t do it”&lt;/a&gt; statement &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/9/14/12919764/millennium-tower-sinking-transbay-powers&quot;&gt;insisting&lt;/a&gt; that after Millennium Properties agreed to donate some of the tower’s space in exchange for “monitoring” its movement, they did exactly that. The TJPA argues that their repeated warnings before their terminal project broke ground went unheeded by the condo developer.  The agency not only shifted the blame for failing to warn owners back to the property managers, it also noted that they “anticipated” being blamed by Millennium Properties.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The agency additionally argued that they had offered an agreement to take on some of Millennium’s liability in exchange for joint record-keeping, which the developer declined. MP vociferously denied that this ever happened.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;MP was quick to fire back, insisting that the building had not sunk beyond “revised predicted ranges” until Transbay began building its adjacent foundation. (Though the developer insists their predicted ranges were safe, they did not specify what they were.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Most alarming among their denials of responsibility, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/9/15/12930402/millennium-towner-sinking-foundation-buildings&quot;&gt;Curbed SF&lt;/a&gt; points out, is the Millennium Partners spokesperson’s comments about other buildings that, like their tower, did not drill their foundations into bedrock. The St. Regis Hotel, SFMOMA, the Embarcadero Center, and many prominent hotels also &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/98836506&quot;&gt;rest on the layer of sand&lt;/a&gt; known as the Colma Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Wherever the blame may ultimately fall, all parties involved can expect significant fallout from legal and legislative actions.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/fearing-rent-increase-child-care-center-buys-building/">
    <title type="text">Fearing Rent Increase, Child Care Center Buys Building</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:348b77fb-16f2-3cb4-b067-ad2f265165cf</id>
    <updated>2016-09-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/fearing-rent-increase-child-care-center-buys-building/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last year had some nail-biter moments for the Mission Child Care Consortium. Facing an end of its lease in 2018, the city’s largest non-profit childcare agency &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/low-income-mission-child-care-center-worries-about-losing-lease/&quot;&gt;expected&lt;/a&gt; a rent hike of nearly double what they were paying, from $28,000 to $50,000 per year, at its current site of 4750 Mission Street. Despite arguments to the contrary from the owner at the time, who insisted he had no intention of disenfranchising the non-profit, Mission Child Care successfully raised $5.6 million to purchase the building.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Consortium is situated between the Balboa Park and Excelsior neighborhoods, and is walking distance from the Balboa Park BART station. The 14 bus, with a stop one block north of the building, runs from Daly City all the way to Embarcadero Station.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ahsha Safaí, who is running to replace John Avalos as District 11 Supervisor, announced the transfer of 4750 Mission Street in a press release. “This victory is the result of 8 years of hard work and another 2 years of community organizing,” he writes, noting that the facility will continue to provide subsidized care for 224 children of working families.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Safaí, a resident of the Excelsior, supported an earlier attempt to purchase the property nine years ago, when he served as deputy director of the Mayor’s Office of Community Development. He also led a signature-gathering campaign in 2015 to raise support for a loan to finance the sale.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/is-a-nonprofit-developer-laundering-money-to-local-campaigns/">
    <title type="text">Is a Non-Profit Developer Laundering Money to Local Campaigns?</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a1f8434c-9038-36c9-9ef5-ef741afb919a</id>
    <updated>2016-09-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/is-a-nonprofit-developer-laundering-money-to-local-campaigns/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This article is the result of our being unable to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vETxuL7Ij3Q&quot;&gt;“follow the money.”&lt;/a&gt; Yerba Buena Neighborhood Consortium, LLC has been a major donor in recent San Francisco elections, most notably the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/prop-c-approval-enables-legislators-set-affordable-housing-requirements/&quot;&gt;Yes On C&lt;/a&gt; committee. John Elberling, Director of affordable housing developer TODCO Group, LLC, founded both LLCs on the same day in 2013. TODCO &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.todco.org/our-housing/&quot;&gt;owns&lt;/a&gt; several senior housing projects, SROs, and Leland Apartments (pictured above), a multifamily apartment complex for disabled residents with Section 8 vouchers.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While TODCO receives income from government grants and property management, YBNC has no discernible source of income. Instead, it appears in a variety of campaign disclosure forms, effectively concealing the true source of donations.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trauss.com/library/EthicsComplaintAgainstElberlingYBNC.pdf&quot;&gt;Ethics Complaint&lt;/a&gt; filed by Oakland resident and &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; co-owner Sonja Trauss alleges “egregious violations” of campaign finance laws. Trauss hopes the complaint will result in an audit which will reveal the source of YBNC’s revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Shell corporations are not a new trend in political campaigns. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/sep/14/corporate-cash-john-doe-files-scott-walker-wisconsin&quot;&gt;Last year&lt;/a&gt;, Wisconsin Governor Scott Walker was investigated for taking potentially criminal donations from a third-party lobbying group funneling money from large corporate donors. Sources close to the &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; claim that Elberling adopted the same strategy for funding ballot measure campaigns, potentially from money he earned from refinancing TODCO’s low-income housing projects.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Campaign literature for ballot measures is a common way for local political groups to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fec.gov/finance/disclosure/electioneering.shtml&quot;&gt;“electioneer”&lt;/a&gt; for candidates as endorsers, increasing their name recognition while not counting toward the particular candidate’s legal spending limits. In forms filed by the “Affordable Housing for All, Yes on Proposition C” Committee, Yerba Buena Neighborhood Consortium donated a total of $125,000 between January and June of this year. After an initial contribution of $35,000, the Committee added “sponsored by Yerba Buena Consortium” to its name on their filings. Several endorsement mailers sent out on behalf of the Prop C campaign, included in the complaint, provided Supervisor Jane Kim with free publicity.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Although the Yerba Buena Consortium is incorporated as a Limited Liability Corporation, it lists its business practices on incorporation documents as “Nonprofit Community Advocates for San Francisco’s South of Market Neighborhood.” This is possibly an anachronism leftover from YNBC’s earlier incarnation as a tax-exempt 501(c)3 of the same name, which lost its tax-exempt status in 2011 after the IRS found they were negligent in their filings. By law, a registered 501(c)3 is not allowed to spend any money on political campaigns. The relationship between the LLC and 501(c)3 entities remains unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/302-units-proposed-in-el-cerrito/">
    <title type="text">302 Units Proposed in El Cerrito</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:f6c570d5-4a03-315a-9aed-72df773e7c47</id>
    <updated>2016-09-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/302-units-proposed-in-el-cerrito/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The East Bay suburb primarily known as the hometown of classic rockers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Aae_RHRptRg&quot;&gt;Creedence Clearwater Revival&lt;/a&gt; may soon get a taste of multifamily urban housing. Oakland developer Holliday Development and the non-profit BRIDGE Housing have partnered in a plan for two apartment buildings near the El Cerrito Del Norte BART station adjoined by a pathway: a five-story 234-unit market-rate building, and a 4-story, 68-unit building of price-indexed Below Market Rentals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The site of the proposal, known as the Mayfair Block, is bounded by Kearney Street and San Pablo Avenue on the east and west, and Cutting Boulevard and Hill Street to the north and south. The parcel was formerly occupied by AK’s Food Corner. One building will feature 10,000 square feet of ground floor retail on the northern side facing Cutting Boulevard.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/302-units-proposed-in-el-cerrito/mayfairmap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Map of the Mayfair Block adjacent to the El Cerrito Del Norte BART station (source: Google Maps)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a special joint session of the Planning Commission and Design Review Board, the project received overall praise from city officials and the public, despite many proposed revisions. The &lt;em&gt;East Bay Times&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbaytimes.com/2016/09/12/el-cerrito-scrutinizes-del-norte-area-mixed-use-proposal/&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that some community members described the separation of market-rate and affordable housing as “disappointing,” additionally lamenting the presence of “too much space for parking.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;BRIDGE Housing made note of a completed project built at the Pleasant Hill BART station in a partnership with Holliday. The non-profit agency is also &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bridgehousing.com/what-we-do/macarthur-station&quot;&gt;developing&lt;/a&gt; a mixed-use apartment complex next to the MacArthur BART station in Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The city of El Cerrito recently rezoned the area for higher-density development near transit under the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.el-cerrito.org/index.aspx?nid=396&quot;&gt;San Pablo Avenue Specific Plan&lt;/a&gt;, adopted in December 2014. The Planning Department designed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Form-based_code&quot;&gt;Form-Based Code&lt;/a&gt;, as well as pedestrian-friendly transit goals, “[i]n order to increase accessibility and livability while increasing land use intensity.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/">
    <title type="text">Affordable Housing Requirement Has Reduced Production of Affordable Housing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:72175746-36e3-3066-802f-fb38bae8df26</id>
    <updated>2016-09-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;An analysis conducted by the &lt;em&gt;Metropolitan Observer&lt;/em&gt; shows that since &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfgov.org/elections/sites/default/files/Documents/candidates/IHR%20Legal%20Text.pdf&quot;&gt;Proposition C&lt;/a&gt; passed June 6 2016, applications to build new housing have dropped by 58% overall, and applications to build Below Market Rate (BMR), subsidized housing have dropped 20%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/propc1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We looked at the Preliminary Project Applications (PPAs) submitted to the SF Planning Department from June 2016 to September 2016 (post-Prop C passing) and compared those to the PPAs submitted during the same time last year, June 2015 and September 2015, to assess the effect of Prop C.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There were 18 residential projects representing 3,000 housing units proposed between June 2015 and the first week of September 2015. Applying the then-12% BMR requirement to the total number of units proposed results in 350 below market rate units proposed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/propc2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;12 residential projects representing 1,250 housing units were proposed during the same time period in 2016 - a drop of more than half from the prior year. The total number of affordable units these projects would contribute, is 289 affordable units - 61 fewer affordable units than what was produced in the same time period last year&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot; id=&quot;fnref-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, or a reduction of 20%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Proposition C was a ballot measure passed last June increasing the affordable housing requirement for new construction to 25% of total units. Some skeptics, including Mayor Ed Lee, argued that 25% was arbitrary. Opponents also feared that an excessively high BMR requirement would reduce the overall amount of housing proposed, and thereby reduce the amount of BMR units produced.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Proponents, led by Supervisors Jane Kim and Aaron Peskin, insisted that the measure was necessary to address the city's affordability crisis. The Supervisors further promised that they would be open to amending the requirement if analyses showed the requirement was in fact too high. Our analysis joins that of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/08/san-francisco-affordable-homes-requirement-prop-c.html&quot;&gt;City Controller's office&lt;/a&gt; in showing that the anticipated net production of affordable housing has decreased since this legislation went into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Notably, while the affordable units anticipated from the July and August of 2016 proposals, post-Prop C, exceeds those same months in 2015, approximately 80% of the post-Prop C affordable units would come from just two large projects. That means if those two projects wind up not being approved, the vast majority of potential affordable units go away - down to about 50 total affordable units. So while, for a given project, Prop C might increase the number of affordable units, it still decreases the &lt;em&gt;overall number of large projects&lt;/em&gt; that produce affordable housing at all, concentrating the risk in just a small number of projects&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref-1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/tweets-from-the-front-palo-alto-city-council-coverage/">
    <title type="text">Tweets from the Front: Palo Alto City Council Coverage</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:60c28653-6a17-3605-8414-307f47b53eaa</id>
    <updated>2016-09-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/tweets-from-the-front-palo-alto-city-council-coverage/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night, the Palo Alto City Council conducted a study session reviewing an upcoming proposal for 60 residential units to replace a vacant bus parking lot on El Camino Real, near the California Avenue Caltrain station. We sent our special Peninsula correspondent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.markmollineaux.com/&quot;&gt;Mark Mollineaux&lt;/a&gt; to cover the meeting via Twitter, and have collected important highlights in a Storify feed below. (Readers curious enough to watch the meeting in its entirety can do so &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/5ZxwXIyYuIo?t=9m55s&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Local developer Windy Hill Property Ventures sought input from the council before making a formal proposal to submit to the Planning Department. The parcel at 2755 El Camino Real is currently zoned for Public Facilities, meaning that any development intended for anything other than city use must seek approval for a zoning variance. This project comes after a proposal by Hayes Group Architects for two stories of housing above ground-floor retail was rejected on the grounds that it did not provide enough housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Although complaints were largely procedural in nature, Vice Mayor Greg Scharff underscored the neighbor’s concerns that the project would add to traffic congestion. Under the current proposal, only 45 parking spaces would be provided for 60 units (all studios or one-bedroom apartments), which is below the 1:1 parking ratio required by local zoning. At one point, Scharff suggested to Windy Hill representatives that they may be asked to pay a fee in lieu of the additional parking spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mayor Patrick Burt, however, rebuffed many criticisms pertaining to car use,  encouraging council and the public to consider vast improvements in autonomous vehicle technology, Caltrain rail electrification, and pedestrian-friendly infrastructure. Councilmember Cory Wolbach joined in urging the council to support the project, adding that he believed there was already too much parking proposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;storify&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/palo-alto-city-council-9-12-16/embed?border=false&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;750&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/palo-alto-city-council-9-12-16.js?border=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;noscript&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/palo-alto-city-council-9-12-16&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;View the story &quot;Palo Alto City Council, 9/12/16&quot; on Storify&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/midtown-terrace-seeks-downzoning-to-preserve-country-living-density/">
    <title type="text">Midtown Terrace Seeks Downzoning to Preserve &quot;Country Living&quot; Density</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:0ffb983d-fc64-3f4b-8a5d-c3cc6d82318e</id>
    <updated>2016-09-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/midtown-terrace-seeks-downzoning-to-preserve-country-living-density/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The neighborhood’s motto &lt;a href=&quot;http://midtownterrace.org/zoning.php&quot;&gt;reads&lt;/a&gt;: “Country living in the heart of San Francisco.” Though the median home price is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zillow.com/midtown-terrace-san-francisco-ca/home-values/&quot;&gt;$1.1 million&lt;/a&gt; in the suburban enclave just south of Twin Peaks, local historian Rex Bell &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=Brief_History_of_Midtown_Terrace&quot;&gt;describes&lt;/a&gt; it as “still a solidly middle-class neighborhood.” Whatever the subjective perceptions may be, organized neighbors are determined to ensure that city law enforces “country living” by amending the local zoning code.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Midtown Terrace homeowners have petitioned the San Francisco Board of Supervisors to amend the area’s zoning &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf-planning.org/sites/default/files/FileCenter/Documents/5358-Residential%20Standards%20Summary%20Table.pdf&quot;&gt;from RH-1 to RH-1 (D)&lt;/a&gt;. Though the differences initially seem subtle and benign, this zoning amendment could effectively render much of the existing built environment illegal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;RH-1(D) zoning prohibits any more than a single dwelling unit per lot, regardless of size. Under current zoning, a 4,500 square foot lot in Midtown Terrace could have at most two units (in other words, a duplex); several lots greater than 7,000 square feet in size allow a triplex.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of District 7, the supervisorial district that encompasses Midtown Terrace, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://localwiki.org/sf/RH-1%28D%29_Zones&quot;&gt;already zoned&lt;/a&gt; RH1(D). If the petition is approved, the new zoning would prohibit anything denser than a single-family home, anywhere in Midtown Terrace. This is particularly significant because there would no longer be density exemptions for Accessory Dwelling Units (ADUs), colloquially known as “backyard cottages”—other single-family neighborhoods in the Twin Peaks and Telegraph Hill Districts retain this exemption. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redfin.com/CA/San-Francisco/91-Aquavista-Way-94131/home/1637155&quot;&gt;Currently unpermitted ADUs&lt;/a&gt; in Midtown Terrace would effectively be illegal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Aside from density restrictions, RH-1(D) zoning also adds restrictions to single-family residences that can be built in the neighborhood. Rather than building to the edge of the property line, as the current zoning allows, new construction would be required to include side yards. It would also apply a minimum lot size of 4,000 square feet, although this would not retroactively apply to the majority of houses in Midtown Terrace, where the zoning currently allows a minimum lot size of 2,500 square feet.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The “D” in RH-1(D) stands for “detached dwellings,” since it bans townhome-style houses with no side yard separation. The Board of Supervisors’ Land Use and Transportation Commission will be considering the residents’ petition on Monday, September 19.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing-sep-9-san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing/">
    <title type="text">San Francisco Finds Unlikely Partnership in Ford for City Bike Sharing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:76cee8a3-73c7-3250-b49e-e064e517a9b4</id>
    <updated>2016-09-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing-sep-9-san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://media.ford.com/content/fordmedia/fna/us/en/news/2016/09/09/ford-partnering-with-global-cities-on-new-transportation--chario.html&quot;&gt;press release today&lt;/a&gt;, Ford announced that it would be partnering with a number of global cities on new transportation initiatives, starting with our own San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The automaker giant - an unlikely advocate for transit - will be sponsoring the Bay Area’s bike share program, expanding the fleet from its current volume of 700 up to 7,000 by the end of 2018. San Francisco’s share of this increase will be 4,500, up from its current, fledgling 328. And in another transit-friendly move, Ford has acquired Chariot, a San Francisco private commuter shuttle service (and lone survivor among Leap and other similarly positioned services), with plans to expand those point-to-point services as well.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ford is working with Motivate, a leading global bike share company, and city officials to add new stations and ramp up the volume of city bikes over the next two years. The program’s footprint won’t be limited to San Francisco either - the plans will include East Bay, including Oakland, Berkeley, and Emerville, and San Jose. Ford will be rebranding the Bay Area Bike Share program as “Ford GoBike” -  which users will be able to access through its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fordpass.com/en_us/home.html&quot;&gt;FordPass&lt;/a&gt; platform, which it touts as a one-stop mobility shop for a variety of transportation needs.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While the image of riding around in a public bike splashed with corporate logos may not appeal to the average San Franciscan, the bike-share sponsorship is undoubtedly good news for the city as a whole, and the Bay Area at large. Ford’s support will infuse the program with capital that may not otherwise be available through city coffers, and increase the availability of city-share bikes, hopefully easing the number of single-rider car trips and congestion on buses. The expansion into East and South Bay shows similar promise.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing-sep-9-san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing/batesbike.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Berkeley Mayor Tom Bates speaks in favor of the program in front of San Francisco City Hall (courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bikeeastbay.org/campaigns/bike-share-all&quot;&gt;Bike East Bay&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To that point, city officials around  the Bay have broadly expressed enthusiasm for this partnership. Berkeley Mayor Tom Bates spoke at an announcement outside City Hall earlier today, and was &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SFBayBikeShare/status/774297091162058752&quot;&gt;quoted&lt;/a&gt; by Bay Area Bike Share as “extremely excited about the prospect of getting these incredible bicycles to East Bay...This is the future!” Emeryville Mayor Dianne Martinez showed similar support on her &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BikeEastBay/status/774303788177907712&quot;&gt;Twitter account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Further, the extension of Chariot, while lower on the green transit totem pole than bicycling, also represents positive change for San Franciscans, in widening the assortment of transportation options for commuters. For parts of the city that are underserved by MUNI, BART, and other city-run transit systems, its advocates argue, this type of dynamic shuttle service can ease commuter pain at a cost competitive with Uber and Lyft - though still higher-priced than public transit options. And from an environmental perspective, if commuters can carpool in larger “pools” than shared Lyft or Uber rides, this would reduce the emissions related to those trips.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The first new bike stations are expected to arrive in spring of next year, with further expansion coming online through 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/affordable-housing-planned-for-16th-and-mission/">
    <title type="text">Affordable Housing Planned for 16th &amp; Mission</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:229590d3-0cf1-377b-9b98-34377edec995</id>
    <updated>2016-09-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/affordable-housing-planned-for-16th-and-mission/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, the Planning Commission received permit applications for an affordable housing project at &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionhousing.org/1950-mission-st-affordable-housing-takes-next-steps/&quot;&gt;1950 Mission Street&lt;/a&gt;. The project is an ambitious proposal with 157 apartments, architecture and amenities being designed by a steady stream of community input. The partnership between two nonprofits, Mission Housing Development Corporation (MHDC) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bridgehousing.com/&quot;&gt;BRIDGE Housing&lt;/a&gt;, will reserve 20% of its units (31 apartments) for formerly homeless families, and rents will be price-indexed for households earning 45% to 60% of Area Median Income.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Planned amenities include a rooftop garden, a communal living room and kitchen, and a bike maintenance workshop for neighborhood youth. The site lies between 15th and 16th Streets on Mission, a short walk from the 16th St &amp;amp; Mission BART station.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/affordable-housing-planned-for-16th-and-mission/1950aerial.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Artist rendering of 1950 Mission, aerial view&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;1950 Mission Street will replace a newly operational “navigation center” for the city’s homeless center, a pilot project run by the mayor’s Office of Housing and Community Development. This currently occupies the abandoned site of the former Phoenix Continuation High School, which was vacated and listed as surplus property by the school district in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cervantesdesignassociates.com/&quot;&gt;Cervantes Design Associates&lt;/a&gt; and the Latino advocacy group &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.podersf.org/&quot;&gt;PODER&lt;/a&gt; spearheaded a community engagement process to design the building and its amenities. MHDC Director Sam Moss described community-based planning as a “guiding principle” behind the project. Aside from organizing several workshops among local stakeholders, PODER and Cervantes have also convened a 1950 Mission Community Advisory Committee to foster the relationship between neighbors and the project sponsors.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;BRIDGE and MHDC plan on breaking ground in 2017. San Francisco’s local &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfgov2.org/ftp/uploadedfiles/elections/candidates/Nov2015/AffordableHousing_Text.pdf&quot;&gt;housing bond&lt;/a&gt; will finance the $80 million project, along with federal funds from low-income tax credits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/sf-controller-repeats-prop-c-is-too-damn-high/">
    <title type="text">SF Controller Repeats, Prop C Is Too Damn High</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a5eeb7b0-d251-3085-af3e-b42ebb1e19bb</id>
    <updated>2016-09-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/sf-controller-repeats-prop-c-is-too-damn-high/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night, the city controller’s office of San Francisco reaffirmed earlier recommendations curbing the price-indexed affordability requirements of market-rate development passed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/San_Francisco,_California,_Affordable_Housing_Requirements_Charter_Amendment,_Proposition_C_(June_2016&quot;&gt;Proposition C&lt;/a&gt;) last year. During the monthly meeting with the office’s advisory committee, Controller Ben Rosenfield supported lowering the percentages of Below Market Rental units required in new private development to be set at 14-18% per year, with a 0.5% increase each year. Under these non-binding recommendations, condominium development would have a 17-20% requirement as well.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Proposition C was co-authored by Supervisors Aaron Peskin and Jane Kim, who both assured critics they would reevaluate the affordability requirements per the Controller’s recommendation. Rosenfield has argued that any requirement above 18% Below Market would stifle overall housing production. Roland Li at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/09/prop-c-affordable-housing-study-for-sf.html?ana=twt&quot;&gt;San Francisco Business Times&lt;/a&gt; attended the meeting and provides the full scoop.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/london-housing-crisis-proves-nostradamus-writes-for-the-onion/">
    <title type="text">London Housing Crisis Proves Nostradamus Writes For &quot;The Onion&quot;</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:44e93955-636d-37ce-97a6-527f0f87c876</id>
    <updated>2016-09-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/london-housing-crisis-proves-nostradamus-writes-for-the-onion/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;News readers around the globe know the American satirical site The Onion as a steady source of prescient, incisive commentary on our modern society. Their hyperbolic headlines often reflect our deepest fears or ugliest biases, but seldom do we see life outright imitating their art. Amid a global surge in urban real estate prices, the particularly crisis-level housing shortage in London has prompted just that.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/aug/31/londons-elite-pushed-out-of-exclusive-postcodes-by-super-rich?CMP=Share_iOSApp_Other&quot;&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; reported on August 31st: “London’s elite pushed out of exclusive post-codes by super-rich.” Sound familiar? In 2008, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theonion.com/article/report-nations-gentrified-neighborhoods-threatened-2419&quot;&gt;The Onion&lt;/a&gt; ran the satirical headline: “Nation's Gentrified Neighborhoods Threatened By Aristocratization.” It’s real. It’s happening. This is not a drill.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Researchers from the London School of Economics’ (LSE) International Inequalities Institute have found that a surge of hyper-wealthy buyers have prompted the formerly elite establishment of lawyers, doctors, and other white-collar professionals “to buy in areas they previously considered undesirable.” Similarly, The Onion's article described how “the enormous treasure-based wealth of the aristocracy makes it impossible for those living on modest trust funds to hold onto their co-ops and converted factory loft spaces.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The similarities are uncanny. Dr. Luna Glucksberg—the totally real, non-parodic researcher at the LSE— warned of “ripple effects” from the displacement of high-income workers to areas further down the market in price, a gentrification wave that could harm affordability for all Londoners. “The study shows that the wealthy individuals and families that live in London’s most exclusive areas no longer feel able to compete at the top end of the capital’s property market,” she told The Guardian.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The aristocrats in the older, um, fictional article voiced a similar concern. The new landed gentry, writes The Onion, “deflected blame onto regification, a process by which they say they were priced out of their vast rural holdings by kings who wished to consolidate property and develop monumental palatial estates.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The process known as “reverse filtering” is very real, and is outlined in John Mangin’s seminal study “&lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.law.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/stanford-law-policy-review/print/2014/01/mangin_25_stan._l._poly_rev_91.pdf&quot;&gt;The New Exclusionary Zoning&lt;/a&gt;” (2014). “In areas with a capped supply and increasing demand,” Mangin writes, housing in effect ‘filters up’—housing formerly occupied by low-income people becomes housing for high-income people. If high-income people are unable to build new housing for themselves, they will buy existing housing and fix it up.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Just yesterday, California’s Legislative Analyst’s Office &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lao.ca.gov/LAOEconTax/Article/Detail/201&quot;&gt;made note&lt;/a&gt; of several analyses showing that real wage and population growth was receding from high-opportunity coastal areas to lower-income inland regions. “In part,” the LAO writes, “we suspect, due to California's lack of new residential housing supply and resulting high costs in coastal areas, a large portion of California's population growth occurred in areas of the state with incomes below the statewide median since 1990.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Perhaps The Onion was not being prescient so much as merely observing longstanding trends. Again, it’s worth repeating: This. Is. Not. A. Drill.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/telegraph-avenue-plan-prioritizes-berkeleys-pedestrians/">
    <title type="text">Telegraph Avenue Plan Prioritizes Berkeley's Pedestrians</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:04f0ecef-e2f5-3e41-b948-672b08e7dee1</id>
    <updated>2016-09-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/telegraph-avenue-plan-prioritizes-berkeleys-pedestrians/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/09/07/realm-plan-calls-for-pedestrian-oriented-telegraph-avenue/&quot;&gt;plans&lt;/a&gt; by Taecker Planning and Design present an ambitious &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/Telegraph-Public-Realm-Plan-Final-Low-Res.pdf&quot;&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt; for Berkeley’s bustling Telegraph Avenue corridor. Already the city’s densest area outside of the downtown, the main artery of the “Southside” neighborhood would be revamped to ease traffic congestion and create an environment more welcoming of pedestrians.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After efforts to preserve a two-story structure from the 1970s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/06/20/berkeley-council-denies-landmark-status-for-the-village/&quot;&gt;failed&lt;/a&gt; to stave off a seven-story apartment project, the Telegraph Public Realm Plan seeks to further adjust to the influx of students to the area—an ever-growing source of sales tax revenue for the city—as well as regional population growth. Local businesses have recently been welcoming of increased density, though transit improvements have been slow to reach the corridor after Councilmember Jesse Arreguin delivered a &lt;a href=&quot;https://oaklandliving.wordpress.com/2010/05/12/joel-ramos-car-enthusiasts-kill-brt-in-berkeley/&quot;&gt;decisive&lt;/a&gt; “abstain” vote against an environmental study of the proposed Bus Rapid Transit program in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Although Arreguin &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ebyd.org/site/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/EBYD-Questionnaire-Jesse-Arreguin.pdf&quot;&gt;stated&lt;/a&gt; at the time that he “was concerned about the loss of local service and the impacts that could have on senior and disabled bus riders” and would have supported a “better plan” with “dedicated lanes during rush hour,” his abstention resulted in only Downtown and East Oakland breaking ground on dedicated BRT lanes and passenger loading islands.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At the time, Berkeley City Council effectively approved a “no-build” alternative resulting in very little change for bus transit on Telegraph Avenue. Six years later, there is still no sign of protected lanes, but the Public Realm Plan does offer what the designers call “Shared Streets,” accommodating motorists, cyclists, and pedestrians.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/telegraph-avenue-plan-prioritizes-berkeleys-pedestrians/dwighttriangle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Dwight &amp;amp; Telegraph triangular intersection optimized for pedestrians (source: Taecker Planning)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Taecker describes the concept as “a plaza-like place with a single ground plane, storefront to storefront, without being interrupted by a curb.” These streets would periodically be closed off to cars for event such as street fairs, which already occur on two blocks of the corridor, between the Durant and Haste intersections.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The plan will also be expanding piloted “Scramble Intersections” beyond the current Bancroft intersection, where a pedestrian-only traffic light allowsthose on foot to cross the intersection diagonally.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/telegraph-avenue-plan-prioritizes-berkeleys-pedestrians/durantplaza.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durant Plaza proposal for public art installations at the current Bank of America building&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sidewalks between the intersections of Bancroft and Dwight Way would be enhanced by public art, modular trash and recycling bins, and retrofitted street lighting. The corner of Durant Avenue, with wider sidewalks than adjacent streets, would host a plaza with public art and a parklet dedicated to exhibiting the rich history of Telegraph Avenue. The “Dwight Triangle,” in turn, would provide a southern gateway with another pedestrian-friendly plaza.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Demonstration projects are planned to be completed by 2017 at the latest. Depending on public reception, the plan could take anywhere from three to ten years, according to local news site Berkeleyside.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/courts-strike-down-eviction-protection-for-teachers/">
    <title type="text">Courts Strike Down Eviction Protection for Teachers</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:35379255-1e94-3218-bed4-26a4caa33695</id>
    <updated>2016-09-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/courts-strike-down-eviction-protection-for-teachers/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last week, a Superior Court judge struck down legislation from Supervisor David Campos intended to protect school employees from no-fault evictions during the school year. As an extension of tenant protections already available to families with school-age children, the Campos &lt;a href=&quot;https://sfgov.legistar.com/View.ashx?M=F&amp;amp;ID=4384428&amp;amp;GUID=995CE4CE-1094-4BFB-BC9C-1301F971D14A&quot;&gt;bill&lt;/a&gt; passed the Board of Supervisors unanimously, but was felled by a lawsuit from the San Francisco Apartment Association and the Small Property Owners of San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The ruling comes amid a slew of bad news for anti-displacement measures in the city, after Supervisor London Breed met with federal officials &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/08/supervisor-to-meet-with-feds-over-citys-anti-displacement-plan/&quot;&gt;to defend&lt;/a&gt; her “neighborhood preference” ordinance. The Department of Housing and Urban Development recently suggested that Breed’s legislation, which would give locals in a particular district priority in lotteries for Below Market Rental units, could violate the 1968 Fair Housing Act.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Legal counsel for the litigating property owners’ groups called Campos’s eviction protection for teachers “short-sighted” and “counterproductive” in light of the city’s raw housing shortage. Judge Ronald Quidachay agreed with this argument, calling it “invalid,” “preempted by state law,” and “unenforceable.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Campos, in turn, opined that the court was enforcing statutes that were out of touch with local needs. “We take a long view,” he told the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/politics/article/Judge-tosses-SF-law-preventing-teacher-evictions-9198849.php&quot;&gt;Chronicle&lt;/a&gt;. “You have a set of laws and systems that are not designed to deal with the housing crisis we are facing.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://projects.sfchronicle.com/2016/teacher-pay/&quot;&gt;analysis&lt;/a&gt; by the same paper found that median rents in San Francisco could take up to 64% of a standard teacher’s salary, more than double what the federal government recommends.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-ramps-up-oakland-office-project-with-dollar8-million-renovation-permit/">
    <title type="text">Oakland Ramps Up Oakland Office Project with $8 Million Renovation Permit</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:e60435fb-84f2-3e75-bb2b-bc485be6c992</id>
    <updated>2016-09-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-ramps-up-oakland-office-project-with-dollar8-million-renovation-permit/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Perhaps no single real estate deal has been more emblematic of the Bay Area tech boom’s highs and lows than Uber’s purchase of the historic Sears building in Oakland. The ridesharing giant purchased the vacant building, now known as Uptown Station, from Lane Partners, a developer that had purchased it in 2014 for $24 million with ambitious redevelopment plans. Uber &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2015/09/uber-oakland-lane-partners-walton-street-capital.html&quot;&gt;paid&lt;/a&gt; $123.5 million for the property, which they plan to use for expanded headquarters—approximately half the square footage price of office space in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Uber &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildzoom.com/property-info/1955-broadway-oakland-ca&quot;&gt;filed&lt;/a&gt; a permit application last week for interior remodeling, primarily for “structural upgrades at first floor atrium” and repairing stairs on the third and fifth floors. Observers expect many more filings to come as the company looks to convert the former department store into a modern tech office.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though initially expected to open in the spring, Uber says it now expects the new offices to open in late 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The office’s expected influx of tech employees has already shaped the narrative of real estate in Oakland’s Uptown District, which has already seen a resurgence of retail, restaurants, and music venues in the past decades. A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.redoakrealty.com/east-bay-real-estate-mls/OAKLAND-property-for-sale-3881-Martin-Luther-King-Jr-Way-OAKLAND-CA-94609?mlsid=40718150&quot;&gt;listing&lt;/a&gt; in the nearby Longfellow neighborhood two miles away advertises an empty lot as a “Developer’s dream come true,” urging bidders to “[p]ick this one up before others get the word that Uber is coming to town.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/los-gatos-council-denies-320-unit-mixed-use-project-at-north-40/">
    <title type="text">Los Gatos Council Denies 320-Unit Mixed-Use Project at North 40</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:0cf23116-588f-36a4-ab5a-cb65af1ecbf4</id>
    <updated>2016-09-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/los-gatos-council-denies-320-unit-mixed-use-project-at-north-40/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night, the Los Gatos Town Council voted 3-2 to deny a permit application to construct 320 residential units and 66,800 square feet of retail space, known as North 40. The decision had been deferred from an earlier council meeting to this special session.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite objections by the developer, Grosvenor Homes, Mayor Barbara Spector spearheaded the motion to deny based on its failure to comply with &lt;a href=&quot;https://legistarweb-production.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/attachment/pdf/21407/Staff_Report_-_N40_FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;particular features&lt;/a&gt; of the town’s Specific Plan for the area. Although it is compliant with local zoning, with the implementation of the State Density Bonus, locals objected primarily on the grounds that the North 40 project did not provide enough senior housing for the area’s aging population. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://legistarweb-production.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/attachment/pdf/23957/081616.pdf&quot;&gt;minutes&lt;/a&gt; from a previous meeting on the project, the mayor cited the Specific Plan’s mandate that “the development should address Los Gatos unmet needs,
identified as Generation Y and Baby Boomers.” 50 of the 320 units would be price-indexed units reserved for senior citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There were also broader objections to changing the character of a municipality with a small-town feel that has nevertheless faced impacts of the regional economic boom, particularly in the form of freeway traffic. The aesthetic concerns, combined with objections based on the Specific Plan, coalesced around the local citizens’ group Town Not City.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Councilmember Steven Leonardis expressed concerns over traffic near the hospital, which he said already faced significant congestion. “If we’re going to add more capacity…I’m wondering how that would be addressed, if there would be any monetary contributions, or add a right of way with a third lane going northbound,” Leonardis remarked.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Confusion abounded over the state’s HCD memo emphasizing that denial of the project could only be based on “objective standards.” Leonardis asked city staff, “does that mean we can’t recommend changes and improvements?” Under the interpretation of state law, staff said, architectural improvements would not be considered a breach of state law if they were incorporated into a subsequent proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Councilmember Marcia Jensen objected to what she considered excessive perfectionism in mandating specific details of an otherwise zoning-compliant project. Her final comment before the vote questioned the assumption that the Town Council “can cause a property owner to come to us with exactly what we want, in exactly the way we want it, at exactly the time we want…We cannot mandate exactly what the application is,” she concluded. Jensen urged the council whether this could negatively impact the overall production of housing in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sonja Trauss, founder of the San Francisco Bay Area Renters' Federation and co-founder of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://carlaef.org/&quot;&gt;California Renters Legal Advocacy and Education Fund&lt;/a&gt; (CaRLA), provided a brief statement. &quot;Los Gatos is out of compliance with the state's Housing Accountability Act, and we will be suing them to enforce the law and ensure that this project gets built.&quot; Trauss is currently spearheading an ongoing lawsuit in Lafayette on similar grounds.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Pilar Lorenzana-Campo, Policy Director of &lt;a href=&quot;http://siliconvalleyathome.org/&quot;&gt;Silicon Valley At Home&lt;/a&gt;, was watching the live video stream last night. The Santa Clara County-based advocacy group has been speaking in favor of the North 40 project since it was first proposed. “We’re really disappointed with last night’s decision in the face of the housing crisis we have right now,” she said in a phone interview. “We really need every community to step up and make sure they build enough housing, including market-rate and affordable housing, to meet the needs of their workers. There’s not enough housing to go around, so their decision to deny this application after years of engagement is really disappointing.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lorenzana-Campo also echoed Councilmember Jensen’s sentiments that the denial represented undue perfectionism in the face of a severe shortage. “This is the project that has been before them for a few years ago. The fact is that they entertained the proposal and were working with the developers, with the project design in question—they needed to take action to improve housing conditions in Los Gatos. In denying the project, they are just making the housing crisis worse, not only for their residents and workers, and for other residents in their region. Now some other community is going to have to provide the extra housing to make up for the unmet need. This is a regional issue, and Los Gatos needs to shoulder their fair share, as do all the other cities in Santa Clara County.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-jose-tenants-face-uphill-battle-against-rent-hike/">
    <title type="text">San Jose Tenants Face Uphill Battle Against Rent Hike</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:63702444-1553-3fe4-888d-532c0b128989</id>
    <updated>2016-09-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-jose-tenants-face-uphill-battle-against-rent-hike/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Two San Jose tenants face an increasingly Sisyphean struggle to hold off a crushing rent increase that could force them to move. Through an arcane loophole in the city’s rent control law, landlords were allowed to raise rents beyond the legal cap in order to pass through interest rates of new mortgage loans onto tenants.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Although San Jose &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/san-jose-eliminates-mortgage-interest-loophole-in-rent-control/&quot;&gt;amended&lt;/a&gt; the law to close this loophole in June, in the three-month period before it took effect, the city saw fifteen Debt Pass-Through Petitions filed, as many as had been filed in the last five years. City Councilmember Raul Peralez confirmed this statistic in a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/JesseGaryKTVU2/videos/1572902493016105/&quot;&gt;interview with KTVU&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite receiving an unfavorable ruling from a hearing officer, residents Keith Jones and Julie Allen of 85 East Taylor Street plan to appeal their case. Under the current court decision, rent on the studio apartment the couple shares will increase from slightly over $1000 per month to $1595. The couple has lived at their current residence for six years.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While San Francisco’s displacement epidemic has garnered national media attention, San Jose’s equally disastrous housing crisis has received little beyond lip service outside of the South Bay. The city recently found itself legally unable to halt the single &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sanjoseinside.com/2016/06/29/mass-eviction-san-joses-largest-to-displace-670-people/&quot;&gt;largest eviction&lt;/a&gt; in the Bay Area, with a developer slated to tear down 216 units of low-income units for three times as many market-rate apartments.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though the legal process will be costly, Jones and Allen do not consider the hike in rent to be any less of a burden. “To be honest, we could potentially pay this,” Allen said over the phone. “But we would be rent-burdened. It would be another $600 a month that could go to our savings, especially if we decided we wanted to purchase something.” She also noted that Jones, at 57, is approaching conventional retirement age. “We have to think about our future and our retirement. We like to travel, we like to enjoy life. And in emergencies, if someone has to go to the hospital or something, it would really cut into it. It’s a huge increase in the cost of living now, coupled with the fact that salaries aren’t rising to keep up.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/san-jose-tenants-face-uphill-battle-against-rent-hike/kj2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keith Jones and Julie Allen in front of their apartment at 85 East Taylor Street&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Allen also stressed that it would be “virtually impossible” to find something within a similar price range in the area. “We would be looking into moving out of the area, even out of the state.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Jones was frustrated that everyone from city officials to pro-bono legal aid from the Law Foundation encouraged him to negotiate with the landlord, a paradigm he says places undue pressure on vulnerable tenants. “More than likely, I will probably do [the appeal] on my own,” Jones added. “We can’t afford to pay the fees for a new attorney. If I bring the landlord into court, we may have to pay for the landlord’s attorney fees.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Historically, it’s very rare that tenants win in these kinds of cases,” Allen added. “We actually were able to explain our situation at the last hearing…but the whole thing that we initially heard about was landlord hardship. They never talked about tenant hardship.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite the cost burden, Jones pointed to significant technical oversights he was confident could help him win in an appeal. His main frustrations stems from the fact that the court’s hearing officer initially sided with Jones, only to abruptly change her mind. In the court’s opinion, the debt pass-through was not based on the mortgage itself, but an amortization of the clerical fees from applying for the mortgage.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“In the decision,” Jones explained, “she sided with the new landlord, though the ordinance clearly states that you need 60+ months in mortgage payments. The landlord only made 59. The decision  isn’t supported by what her argument is. 59 versus 60 payments is very clear.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Jones also disputed that the landlord had adequately documented the terms of their recent loan. “That the fees were amortized over 15 years—there is no documentation, no support as to whether the loan that the new landlord took out is amortized over 15 years. The only thing that is supporting that is a letter from the bank stating that the loan is amortized for 15 years. On all other documents, it says it’s amortized for 5 years plus a balloon payment.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Because Jones and Allen both work full-time, Councilmember Raul Peralez was only able to schedule a meeting with them at the end of this month, after numerous attempts to meet with them in early afternoon hours.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/30-van-ness-will-return-to-market-without-listed-price/">
    <title type="text">30 Van Ness Will Return to Market Without Listed Price</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:f11e0eb9-bff0-330c-9f5e-f67a3050d5c0</id>
    <updated>2016-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/30-van-ness-will-return-to-market-without-listed-price/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On December 8, 2015, Supervisor Aaron Peskin’s first day back on the board, Peskin celebrated by reneging a deal made by the city's &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfgov.org/realestate/&quot;&gt;Real Estate Division&lt;/a&gt; to sell 30 Van Ness for $80 million, potentially creating a $60 million liability for the city.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The city-owned site at 30 Van Ness Avenue will go back on the market on September 6th with no listing price. Roland Li at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/09/30-van-ness-san-francisco-housing-development.html?ana=twt&quot;&gt;Business Times&lt;/a&gt; reported the San Francisco Real Estate Division’s announcement earlier today, which has been widely anticipated since Supervisor Aaron Peskin &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfyimby.com/news/2016/8/2/aaron-peskins-art-of-no-deal&quot;&gt;blocked&lt;/a&gt; a proposed sale ten months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;30 Van Ness is currently a 6-story city office building. With an impending $60 million in seismic upgrades required to continue its office use, along with the revenue potential from its current zoning for 40 stories, the city decided put the parcel on the market. After vetting 15 offers from large developers, the  Office of Real Estate reached an agreement with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.relatedcalifornia.com/&quot;&gt;Related California&lt;/a&gt; to sell the property for $80 million and for the property to set aside 20% for affordable housing. Related proposed to build 40 stories with 500 dwelling units (400 rented at market rate, 100 Below Market Rentals) with one single entrance (no &quot;poor door&quot;) on prime transit-accessible land,. Related also planned to lease at least 5000 square feet of the space for a new child care center.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite having completed a competitive bidding process, several supervisors claimed to believe there was still another developer with a potentially better offer.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Peskin, bolstered by factional “progressive” allies Campos, Mar, and Kim, raised doubts that the $80 million offer from Related California was the highest return the city could obtain. The deal included an allotment for 25% Below Market Rental units if the proposed &lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/San_Francisco,_California,_Affordable_Housing_Requirements_Charter_Amendment,_Proposition_C_(June_2016&quot;&gt;Proposition C&lt;/a&gt;) requirements passed (which they did), with city funds paying the difference to increase the price-indexed unit ratio to 33%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;During a marathon 9-hour meeting on December 8, 2015, Supervisors Mar and Kim both made statements to the effect that there was a “better deal to be had.” Supervisor Campos, representing the Mission District in Bernal Heights, chimed in: “Is this really, not even the best deal, but is this a good deal for the city and our district? I don’t know if I could say that…I think this is one of those things that in a very short time, we're going to look back and say, 'What the heck were we thinking?'&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I say this as somebody who has spent most of his adult life in the business of real property sale and acquisition that we, respectfully, are leaving a bit too much money on the table,” Peskin declared.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Our fundamental job,” the Supervisor continued, “is to get as much for our shareholders, the people of the city and county of San Francisco, as we can. And with all due respect to our department of real estate, we have not gotten that.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A city official testifying at the meeting informed the Board that all other bids were significantly lower than the $80 million Related was offering. After the sale was voted down, no higher offer came before the city.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;John Updike, director of the city’s real estate department, expects that the city will make a decision among future bids by the end of the year. The developer would have to pay for seismic upgrades, and would have the option to maintain its current use as office space.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
