<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Bay Area Metropolitan Observer</title>
  <id>urn:uuid:52c4ddef-40d4-3bc8-bbd3-d91037b58706</id>
  <updated>2017-01-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/" />
  <link href="http://sfbamo.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <author>
    <name></name>
  </author>
  <generator uri="https://github.com/ajdavis/lektor-atom" version="0.2">Lektor Atom Plugin</generator>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/feeding-the-hungry-studying-shadows-top-priorities-at-planning-commission/">
    <title type="text">Feeding the Hungry, Studying Shadows Top Priorities at Planning Commission</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:f1858de3-ebc9-38fb-becd-2e638e3c1ca2</id>
    <updated>2017-01-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/feeding-the-hungry-studying-shadows-top-priorities-at-planning-commission/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Dennis Richards (pictured above), acting president of the San Francisco Planning Commission, told a pair of French nuns, “I’ll even try your food,” before moving to approve their application for a use permit to run a non-profit soup kitchen out of vacant retail space. “You can donate, too,” one Sister replied.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I’ll come volunteer,” Richards added without missing a beat.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Thus concluded the first, heartwarming half of the Planning Commission’s Discretionary Review agenda yesterday. The stars were aligned: Tony Robbins, celebrity business consultant, had partnered with Salesforce CEO Marc Benioff to donate a new space, located at 1928 Mission Street, to the Fraternite Notre Dame Mary of Nazareth House, after the landlord of their soup kitchen at 54 Turk Street moved to evict the nuns. Both Robbins and Benioff testified in favor. Newly sworn-in District 9 Supervisor Hillary Ronen brought droves of local supporters to the meeting, saying it was the most “compassionate, appropriate service to come to the Mission.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Several neighbors from the 1930 Mission Street condominiums above the storefront came out to oppose the use permit, citing safety concerns. One man stated, after a litany of supporting testimonies, that although he still felt “this is just not the right place,” he would still be open to it being “very nearby.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Estimated sale prices for the condos at 1930 Mission Street range from $800 to $1200 per square foot. Property tax assessments in the building were, on average, roughly half of their market value. The vacant storefront and condominiums also share the building with a medical marijuana office.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Another resident of 1930 Mission, a visibly younger woman sporting dyed blue hair (pictured above), had already spoken in support of the soup kitchen, mostly anticipating the man’s later rebuttals. “This will make the area safer,” she said. She was one among many nearby residents who insisted that alleviating the hunger of local homeless population would positively impact their daily life.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The mood was not as cheerful when the meeting’s Discretionary Review portion turned to a five-story mixed-use proposal with 28 dwelling units and ground-floor retail at 198 Valencia Street.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A nearby decades-old beer garden, Zeitgeist, had complained publicly for weeks prior that the proposed apartment building would cast shadows over their outdoor patio and drive away customers. Although the city typically does not study shadows for space on private property, appellants from the bar brought a shadow impact analysis that did not follow officially mandated methodologies.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I would like to see more granular data here,” Commissioner Richards told the Zeitgeist representatives. “I feel for you guys, I really do, but right now I just don’t see it.” Zeitgeist claimed the building would shade 7% of their patio after 4pm between March and May, and from August to September. (Planning Department staff argued that a 4% estimate was more likely under their methodology.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;One man who had been working at Zeitgeist for 13 years testified, “without the sunshine, we would no longer be Zeitgeist.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The project at 198 Valencia would be replacing a one-story automobile oil changing station, which drea concern from Peter Pappadopolous of the non-profit Cultural Action Network. “We're concerned about the loss of another auto shop,” he said. “The city has been losing many of its auto repair shops to housing in recent years.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yet many speakers were more forceful in their support for the project than a mere “I just don’t see it.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Think of if the other way around—would we consider removing 28 homes if this place wanted more sunshine?” asked Sonja Trauss, webmaster of this publication. “Of course not.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We shouldn't allow special interests to obstruct the construction of housing and inflation of property values,” one man said.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Multiple speakers also mentioned California’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/codes_displaySection.xhtml?lawCode=GOV&amp;amp;sectionNum=65589.5&quot;&gt;Housing Accountability Act&lt;/a&gt;, which requires cities to approve housing developments that meet local zoning requirements in the absence of a quantified health or environmental detriments. For this reason, the alternate option of removing ground-floor retail to include more residential units was quickly dismissed, since the building could still legally rise to 50 feet. (Under the current proposal, an additional five-foot “parapet” is allowed.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supporters and opponents alike will have to wait over a month to see if any detriment can be quantified. The commission voted 5-1 to continue the item until their February 16th meeting, pending another study of shadows.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/lawsuit-eliminates-23-homes-from-redwood-city-condo-proposal/">
    <title type="text">Lawsuit Eliminates 23 Homes from Redwood City Condo Proposal</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:05ce8607-5f96-325e-8ab6-a2af46dd1266</id>
    <updated>2017-01-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/lawsuit-eliminates-23-homes-from-redwood-city-condo-proposal/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A coalition of neighbors in San Mateo County dubbed “Redwood City Residents for Responsible Development” (RCRFRD) successfully leveraged environmental litigation to downsize new development in the downtown area. The developer, Jefferson Res, LLC, submitted applications for a permit in September 2015 for an 8-story condominium building with 91 dwelling units at 603 Jefferson Avenue. After approving it in May of 2016, the City Council voted to deny an appeal brought by two residents in late July.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Following the settlement of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/55dbb5e9e4b0703ec759c956/t/587697f320099e396b9c5553/1484167439462/Redwood+City+-+603+Jefferson+-+Suit.pdf&quot;&gt;lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; brought under the California Environmental Quality Act (CEQA), the developer agreed to shorten the project to 6 stories, comprising only 68 units.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Multiple studies from the law firm &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hklaw.com/news/holland-knight-study-uncovers-widespread-ceqa-litigation-abuse-08-04-2015/&quot;&gt;Holland &amp;amp; Knight&lt;/a&gt; have shown that the majority of CEQA lawsuits target public transit, renewable energy, and infill housing development. The appellants alleged “severe” impacts on traffic in their suit, relying on a Level Of Service (LOS) measure for traffic impacts which California lawmakers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opr.ca.gov/docs/SB_743_CEQA_Guidelines_Update_Local_Government_Roundtable_8_18_14.pdf&quot;&gt;have begun phasing out&lt;/a&gt;, instead quantifying traffic impact in terms of Vehicle Miles Travelled (VMT).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Isabelle Chu, founder of the non-profit advocacy group &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.redwoodcityforward.com/&quot;&gt;Redwood City Forward&lt;/a&gt;, was deeply disappointed by the outcome of the lawsuit. “If these [developments] were deeply unpopular, we’ve had ample opportunity to vote out our current city council. That has not happened,” she said in a brief phone interview. “Judging from the actions and voting patterns, the city of Redwood City likes the downtown, or at least doesn’t object to it. Consequently, these actions are overriding the will of everyone who elected the city council; everybody who gave input into the Downtown Specific Plan; and everyone who lives, works, and visits the downtown.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ms. Chu reserved particular ire for the grounds on which the suit was filed. “It’s based on an outdated measure [LOS] which indicates that their primary concern is not, in fact, the environment, but rather the convenience of their drive. First of all, the primary determinant of traffic is the economy, not housing,” she added.  “Housing near jobs reduces traffic, all things being equal. Traffic is an inconvenience. Housing is a basic necessity. To deny somebody a place to life because you’re inconvenienced is unjust.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Brian Hanlon, founder of the California Renters Legal Advocacy and Education Fund (CaRLA), sees the lawsuit as part of a broader pattern of abusing environmental litigation to maintain suburban sprawl. “Local NIMBYs should not be able to use CEQA to compel a reduction of 23 homes in a downtown development,” Mr. Hanlon wrote in an email. “The claim that building an 8-story residential building would cause ‘severe significant environmental impacts’ is absurd.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In the event that plaintiffs lose their case, an unincorporated club can easily avoid liability for damages or attorney’s fees. (Holland &amp;amp; Knight researchers recommend reforming this aspect of the law, requiring litigants to state their full names to deter CEQA abuse.) Consequently, the plaintiffs could not be reached for comment.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/sf-sketchfest-brings-local-flavor-and-global-laughs/">
    <title type="text">SF Sketchfest Brings Local Flavor and Global Laughs</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:d13b8a50-2481-314d-8700-09dbf5734e6e</id>
    <updated>2017-01-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/sf-sketchfest-brings-local-flavor-and-global-laughs/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco is perpetually a city of rising stars, but conventional wisdom dictates that once they rise, they must flee for Los Angeles with all deliberate haste. SF Sketchfest has established itself as a global institution to counter the tinsel-town dominance of show business, pushing the envelope with new and innovative comedians alongside the star power of established stalwarts.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself staring at a list of obscure names, don’t worry—it’s as much of a celebration for twisted comedy nerds as it is a festival rife with conventional punchline structures for the casual consumer.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Whether casual or obsessive, you would do yourself a huge disservice to stick to the standup shows, as improv is arguably just as crucial in the chemistry of comedy. That’s why the almost-daily improv showcase at PianoFight is absolutely essential for those seeking a deep dive into the most unpredictable form of comedy available. Of particular note is the showcase on Thursday, January 19th, hosted by the local clothing-optional sketch comedy troupe &lt;a href=&quot;https://sfsketchfest2017.sched.com/artist/chardonnay.1vyfjsd0&quot;&gt;Chardonnay&lt;/a&gt;. (Yes, we recommend them because &lt;em&gt;they are funny,&lt;/em&gt; okay? Get your head out of the gutter.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On that same night, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sfsketchfest2017.sched.com/event/8wLz/sf-sketchfest-nightlife-at-the-california-academy-of-sciences?iframe=no&amp;amp;w=100%&amp;amp;sidebar=yes&amp;amp;bg=no&quot;&gt;California Academy of Sciences&lt;/a&gt; will host an adults-only extravaganza with a live performance by “scientists” Frank Beaulieu and Frank Conniff of Mystery Science Theater 3000, live DJs, alcoholic beverages, and satirical TED Talks, among other weird offerings.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the avant-garde, San Francisco plays second fiddle to no one. It will be especially delightful to the most curious comedy-seekers to see Ian Abramson’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://sfsketchfest2017.sched.com/event/8wMm/7-minutes-in-purgatory-with-ian-abramson-and-guests-alex-jude-joel-kim-booster-dave-hill-joyelle-nicole-johnson-seaton-smith-brent-weinbach-ahamed-weinberg-and-alice-wetterlund?iframe=no&amp;amp;w=100%&amp;amp;sidebar=yes&amp;amp;bg=no&quot;&gt;7 Minutes of Purgatory&lt;/a&gt;, which debuts this Friday, 8:00pm at the Eureka Theater. Abramson encloses comedians in a soundproof booth, where they perform for an audience in a separate room via closed-circuit television. It’s a disorienting experience for both audience and performer, robbed of their symbiotic relationship, often to hilarious effect.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Our fair city of Saint Francis can no longer be mistaken for a provincial backwater town—not with an international standup showcase featuring award-winning commedians Aisling Bea and James Acaster, from Ireland and New Zealand, respectively. On &lt;a href=&quot;https://sfsketchfest2017.sched.com/event/8wLl/international-standup-spotlight-aisling-bea-and-james-acaster-hosted-by-josh-johnson?iframe=no&amp;amp;w=100%&amp;amp;sidebar=yes&amp;amp;bg=no&quot;&gt;Friday, January 20th at the Brava Theater&lt;/a&gt;, showgoers can treat themselves to unfamiliar comedy delivered by strangely-accented yet masterful performers whose sense of humor is never lost in translation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What delights us most, frankly, is that readers could ignore all our suggestions and would still be guaranteed a great time. Ultimately, SF Sketchfest is simply a celebration of human speech and movement. Nobody really knows why we enjoy laughter so much, but we’re more than happy to suspend our disbelief and leave our jaded cynicism at coat-check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jhA2OEN5Dxo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/j_VQVYWwz_U&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xpZLusV-1IY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/at-first-sight-alamedans-welcome-density-on-waterfront/">
    <title type="text">At First Sight, Alamedans Welcome Density on Waterfront</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:5bafcf39-a312-3738-9070-2e6f4df16d56</id>
    <updated>2017-01-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/at-first-sight-alamedans-welcome-density-on-waterfront/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Alameda’s Planning Board convened in council chambers to review the &lt;a href=&quot;https://laurendo.wordpress.com/2017/01/09/wade-in-the-waterfront/&quot;&gt;Encinal Terminals Master Plan&lt;/a&gt;, an ambitious proposal on the island’s waterfront facing Oakland. What proceeded was a spectacle most unusual in the Bay Area: a municipal public hearing in which virtually every attendee enthusiastically supported greater density.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Across the estuary, Oakland will be building up to 30 stories at the Brooklyn Basin,” one speaker noted. “So I think fourteen stories might not even be tall enough to fit the surrounding area.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The planning board generally concurred with this observation, commenting approvingly on the varying heights and “stepped-back” massing on the waterfront.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The current proposal comprises 589 dwelling units, ranging from 2-story townhomes to the aforementioned 14-story apartment building. It would also include a marina for boat rentals, three acres of open space for recreation, and over 50,000 square feet of commercial space for restaurants and retail.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/at-first-sight-alamedans-welcome-density-on-waterfront/encinal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preliminary site plan for Encinal Terminals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;One speaker expressed enthusiasm for the possibility of commuting across the estuary via kayak, but noted that Oakland and Alameda would have to adopt “kayak parking” infrastructure similar to Minneapolis. Board Member Lorre Zuppan also urged the developer, North Waterfront Cove, LLC, to consider building parking that could be adapted to other uses in the future, given the surge in ride-hailing services and generational decline in car ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://alameda.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?ID=2914505&amp;amp;GUID=B0CB5B38-F5C8-4D18-A0B9-E495A5230B59&amp;amp;Options=&amp;amp;Search=&amp;amp;FullText=1&quot;&gt;staff report&lt;/a&gt; indicates that after the city rezoned the area from manufacturing to mixed-use, it remained vacant since 2010. Indeed, one speaker referred to the current site as “grey-field,” and several board members referenced the prevalence of bird droppings during a recent visit.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Philip James, an Alameda resident, further clarified his support for the project: “We have a chance to turn a piece of land that's mostly inaccessible to the public into a public good, and that's a chance we should take,” James wrote in an email. “The one concern I have is for affordable housing - I wish there were more of it! Beyond that, I hope this project is successful, and helps Alameda families grow.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Angela Hockabout, founder of the Alameda Renters Coalition, was even more unequivocal in her support. “The Encinal Terminal development has the potential to send a message to every Bay Area suburb that even development-adverse communities can build the dense neighborhoods we need to solve this housing crisis,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The only way we are going to mitigate the housing crisis is to build up,” Hockabout added.  “California needs to build 1.8 million homes by 2025 and I intend to see each and every one of those units built.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/the-school-board-graduate-sandra-lee-fewer-district-1/">
    <title type="text">The School Board Graduate: Sandra Lee Fewer (District 1)</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:ca46ad17-79e6-3d72-979f-7f1646253cbc</id>
    <updated>2017-01-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/the-school-board-graduate-sandra-lee-fewer-district-1/" />
    <author>
      <name>Bay City Beacon staff</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article originally appeared in&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.baycitybeacon.com&quot;&gt;The Bay City Beacon.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Coming from nearly 8 years on the San Francisco School Board, Sandra Lee Fewer joins a number of elected officials (Jane Kim, Eric Mar, Norman Yee) that have jumped from the School Board to the Board of Supervisors.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A fourth generation native and Chinese American, Sandra Lee Fewer campaigned as a long-time Richmond District local with strong ties to the progressive wing of San Francisco politics. She supported limited growth and opposed the Geary Bus Rapid Transit, and held the sole endorsement of the SF Tenants Union.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The interview below has been edited for clarity and brevity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are your priorities for the first term?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;My priorities are to take care of issues in my district. One is to look for three places that build 100% affordable housing, another thing is to take care of some of my issues in my neighborhood such as like the quality of life, street repairs.  What I’ve heard on the campaign was a lot of quality of life issues that my neighborhood needs a little love. So I think that I would start with that - before I was elected I started on a dog park in GGP, I think I want to finish that.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I also want to work on some of the transit issues in the Richmond district, and it really is on the quality of life issues. What I heard loud and clear is that people feel like the Richmond does not get as much service as we should and we are literally neglected on the west side. I think it would take a while to get up to speed on everything and after that I hope to advocate for my neighborhood to get some of these remedies.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Any immediate pieces of legislation you’re thinking about introducing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;No, I feel like the first six months I am going to learn, take it slow, see how things are, see how things are run, who the people are, and really get out in my neighborhood and meet the community groups throughout my neighborhood and listen. I think the first six months I am planning to do a lot of listening and to see what kind of issues citywide or in my district I should be offering.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you tell me your thoughts about how the election went this year for you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sure, I think the election was very difficult, in January I pulled papers to run.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I was sort of a reluctant candidate, I am a little older and didn’t think I be doing this in my life. But I think once I pulled papers we were boasting ahead, we were working very hard and I think we worked really hard till the last vote had been cast on Election Day.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There were 10 candidates that ran in this race and I learned from every single one of them. All these candidate forums, you start to listen to everyone’s ideas and their feelings about the neighborhood, and since they are all residents of the neighborhood it gives you sort of of a feel what people are thinking and feeling - and I thought it was a good thing to have an open election. People feel that they could step up and run for office if they feel they haven’t been heard or they can just run for office because they feel like they have something to say and that their leadership can get a certain task done. I think it’s really an example of how our democracy work when you have ten people running for one seat. But actually I think everyone can learn from each other and I know I did, I was listening very closely to what my fellow candidates had to say and taking it in that they absolutely represent a train of thought in my district.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It was a hard campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A lot of money was spent for and against you in the campaign.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Well I think a lot of the money that came in against me, I want to point out that we are out spent considerably, and the money from the people that supported me were labor unions and the working people of San Francisco. People who were against me were realtors, developers, tech, police, and some labor unions that want to build, build, build. And so I think it really represents how the city is changing and people think that big money can win a race, that they can interfere the democratic process of a district neighborhood election and spent a million dollars trying to win a neighborhood election.  The more money that was spent against us the harder we worked because we were adamant that big money was not going to win this race. People were going to win this race and I think that the results of the election just proved that.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the hardest challenge facing your district right now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I think that it’s really about keeping our neighborhood intact as a neighborhood. That means keeping the people who live here, who want to live here so they can stay here, while we have some growth. We will have to grow on the west side but it isn’t “if we grow” its “how we grow”. I think we can grow without displacement and I think we can grow without gentrification taking over our small businesses and also our people on fixed income.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The thing about Richmond District is that 65% of people who live here are renters, and there is no rent control for small businesses, so if we grow too quickly, small businesses will be priced out and won’t be able to survive - and these are small business that has served our district for a very long time, most of them are “mom and pop” stores and I think we all have personal relationships with these stores.  So that growth that needs to happen needs to be very planned, and it needs to be intentional, and it has to intentionally not push out residents in the Richmond District.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geary’s Bus Rapid Transit was a very controversial topic during the election. Are you planning to support it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;My view on Geary BRT (Bus Rapid Transit) is that it is some what disturbing that that (the BRT) is the only thing dominating the conversation about transportation in the Richmond District. Because the BRT does not connect us to the rest of the city, I have told transit authorities that I can’t endorse it unless they can show me how this is part of a bigger plan so that residents of the Richmond can get to the other parts of SF. It takes me an hour or over to get to City College, an hour to the Mission, and the Geary BRT just takes us to down town.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;With all the development happening in Mission Bay and way out in Hunter’s Point and they are going to redo the (Hunter’s Point) Shipyard and a lot of new jobs out there, tell me how are we going to be connected to the rest of the city - they can’t answer that question, and until they can show me how this BRT actually connects us to a larger transportation system to serve the residents of the Richmond District I can’t get on board.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/fear-and-finance-in-saint-francis-part-2-what-do-the-watchdogs-watch/">
    <title type="text">Fear &amp; Finance in Saint Francis, Part 2: What Do the Watchdogs Watch?</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:5f6f3738-bcec-368f-8a20-57439efe6633</id>
    <updated>2017-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/fear-and-finance-in-saint-francis-part-2-what-do-the-watchdogs-watch/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When I meet Herb Meiberger at a café in the Castro, he brings his faithful service dog, Bark. Bark (pictured above) does not bark once. Rather, he silently tastes my hand in greeting, accepts some scratches behind the ear, and sits on my feet, presumably to guard me from predators.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“He likes you. That’s a good sign,” Meiberger observes. “If Bark trusts you, I can trust you.” Then and there, he opens up.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For someone campaigning as a “watchdog,” Meiberger couldn’t have brought a more helpful allegory along.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mr. Meiberger is running for reelection to the Executive Board of San Francisco’s Employee Retirement System (SFERS), which oversees investment decisions on the city’s pension fund. As a Lecturer in Finance at San Francisco State University, he takes his duties assiduously, like a professor preparing curricula.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/fear-and-finance-in-saint-francis-part-2-what-do-the-watchdogs-watch/0.herb.campaign.flyer-1-page-001.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;campaign mailer courtesy of Herb Meiberger&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“You need more than four days to review information and make a decision,” he says of a critique printed in an attack ad by his opponent, retired police captain Croce “Al” Casciato. Casciato has accused his opponent of delaying a decision over a $400 million investment in Chinese &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.investopedia.com/terms/a/ashare.asp&quot;&gt;A-Share&lt;/a&gt; mutual funds. Though the assets would be controlled by the investment manager, SFERS staff is barred from revealing the managers’ names to prevent conflicts of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It was my idea, two years ago, to allocate funds in A-Shares. The Chinese stock market doubled in that time,” Meiberger says. “India and China are the future, especially now. Everyone knows that. After two years of nothing, staff comes back to us with this, which they want us to decide on in four days? I said we should do our homework, so of course I voted to delay. A few months later, I voted in favor of the investment.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Meiberger relates these details in a joking, easygoing cadence, despite his frustrations. It’s as though he’s seen this all before.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To him, it’s a culture divide. The pensioners organizing to unseat him are largely comprised of police and firefighters’ unions; Meiberger is a member of the SEIU 1021 union, the only “miscellaneous” elected board member. Ron Gold, a retired firefighter, wrote him a &lt;a href=&quot;http://herbmeiberger.com/hyc/herb-police-fire/#comment-10911&quot;&gt;glowing endorsement letter&lt;/a&gt; rife with barbed criticisms of the hedge-fund faction: “I retired from the SFFD in the early and frankly hope to outlast the pension fund’s assets,” Gold wrote, “which might not happen if they continue to play with hedges.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Meiberger takes his campaign mostly to those “miscellaneous” workforces—teachers, librarians, electricians, for example. Slightly under 60,000 San Franciscans are eligible to vote in the SFERS election, so Meiberger conducts most of his voter outreach on foot, bringing donuts and campaign literature to office lunch hours and chatting retirement finance with future pensioners.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/fear-and-finance-in-saint-francis-part-2-what-do-the-watchdogs-watch/herb-page2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;excerpt from page 2 of Meiberger's campaign mailer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mr. Meiberger is largely running on his decades of experience. “I served during all 17 years of Al Casciato’s time on the board,” he adds. “His record is also mine.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While Meiberger plans to disclose his campaign financing with the San Francisco Ethics Commission, he alleges that his opponent has circumvented this requirement with a clever trick. Casciato’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.electcasciato.com/donate_to_al&quot;&gt;donation page&lt;/a&gt; refers donors to an address where they can mail checks—an address shared by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://campaignlawyers.com/&quot;&gt;law firm&lt;/a&gt; of election attorney Jim Sutton. Law firms are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/law-firms-accounts-pose-money-laundering-risk-1482765003&quot;&gt;exempt&lt;/a&gt; from requirements to disclose donations.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“This election is the wolves versus the watchdogs,” he tells me when our interview formally begins. “That’s what it comes down to.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As we related in our previous &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/fear-and-finance-in-saint-francis-police-and-the-politics-of-city-pension-reform-part-1/&quot;&gt;coverage&lt;/a&gt;, Meiberger sees his opposition united around a singular cause: hedge funds. With high fees, low returns, and managers banking in Bermuda, Meiberger abhors this form of investment. Warren Buffett agreed with him. Further, he won’t speculate why his opponents advocate for them. “I have no idea,” is all he says. “Maybe it’s a fad.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Retired city employee Patrick Monette-Shaw offers a simpler theory. In a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/pension-election-lies-may-cost-taxpayers-dearly/&quot;&gt;op-ed&lt;/a&gt; for the San Francisco &lt;em&gt;Examiner&lt;/em&gt;, Monette-Shaw notes that hedge fund investors are attracted by “alpha” (yields exceeding projected returns). “The hedge fund details are SFERS’ only investment undisclosed to the public and plan participants…If gambling on increased alpha fails, and the fund loses millions of dollars, it will haunt taxpayers with increased General Fund employer-share contributions to prop up investment losses,” he writes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Much of the tension between Meiberger and hedge fund advocates emerged early last year when SFERS’ Chief Investment Officer Bill Coaker recommended a 15% allocation of the city’s pension fund ($3 billion of a fund valued at $20 billion) into hedge funds. Meiberger was told that the names and fees of external hedge fund managers could not be disclosed to the Board or the public. The board voted to allocate $1 billion, while Coaker began advocating for a 25% allocation – a full $5 billion – into hedge funds.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though Meiberger prides himself on bridging the cultural gap in labor unions (he was made an honorary member of the Veterans Police Officers Association thanks to his twenty years on the SFERS board), lately he has seen unprecedented betrayals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To his credit, Meiberger notes that Casciato referred to the SFPD’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://mysfers.org/wp-content/uploads/SFERS-DROP-Brochure.pdf&quot;&gt;Deferred Retirement Option Program&lt;/a&gt; (DROP) as a “great deal.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After Casciato retired from the Executive Board in 2012, the police and firefighters ran their own candidate, Brian Stansbury, to replace him. Stansbury lost to Gus Vallejo, whom Meiberger endorsed. It thus came as a shock to Meiberger when he saw Vallejo’s name co-signing an open letter in the POA journal urging him to resign.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We haven’t really spoken since,” Meiberger noted.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;He suspects that Joe Driscoll, a firefighter and former student of his, is the brains behind the campaign against him. “To date, he’s run three candidates to oppose me,” he says before laughing. Frankly, it is hard to tell what his laughter ever means.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;His laughter feels even more foreboding when he compares his record with Casciato’s. It’s the laughter one would expect from a finance professor who knows his bratty young students will one day grow up to run Goldman Sachs. “It’s like we were each on opposite sides during the 2008 mortgage crisis,” Meiberger notes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;According to Meiberger, one of his most notable accomplishments was selecting SFERS’ most successful bond managers, Greg White of the Scarsdale, NY-based firm Prima Capital Advisors. After investing in commercial mortgages and placing them in a trust, SFERS securitized the equity and saw 5% returns. As a result, SFERS’ bond credit rating was upgraded in 2008, at the beginning of the Great Recession.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“When did Casciato ask about investments?” he wonders aloud. “I don’t remember any time.” Quite the contrary, Meiberger and Driscoll took precisely the opposite approach during the same time, Meiberger alleges.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Meiberger claims that one of Casciato’s only strongly-expressed opinions was to support investing in commodities, a notoriously volatile market. In 2008, due to massive losses from securitized debt in Lehman Brothers, SFERS saw some of its accounts frozen. (Lehman Brothers’ catastrophic collapse is widely credited as a major catalyst of the 2008 financial crisis.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When I ask if these events spurred a change in the conversation regarding securities at the SFERS Board, Meiberger emits his loudest, most piercing laughter of the evening. “No,” he replies. “What would make you think that?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When we part ways, with Bark trotting at his side, Meiberger repeats his boastful prediction that Casciato will not speak to the press. So far, with the exception of an acknowledgement from his representative at Telegraph PR, he remains correct: the Casciato campaign has yet to respond to repeated requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/the-progressive-fighter-hillary-ronen-district-9/">
    <title type="text">The Progressive Fighter: Hillary Ronen (District 9)</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:c08ac0d4-5169-32f9-aa98-ab9fd792ed0b</id>
    <updated>2017-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/the-progressive-fighter-hillary-ronen-district-9/" />
    <author>
      <name>Bay City Beacon staff</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This interview was originally published in the&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thebaycitybeacon.com&quot;&gt;Bay City Beacon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Mission District has always been the progressive stronghold of San Francisco politics. It’s been the seat of Former Assemblymember Tom Ammiano and outgoing Supervisor David Campos, elected officials who have prided themselves on being the progressive vanguard. That pattern of left-leaning leadership continues as Hillary Ronen becomes the first woman in modern district elections to represent the Mission.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ronen comes as a City Hall veteran, having served as Campos’ Chief of Staff for the last six years. She embraced those credentials throughout the campaign, leading to a solid victory this past November. Expect her to be the next progressive stalwart at City Hall.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The interview below has been edited for clarity and brevity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are your priorities for the first term?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I have three top priorities - the first is to not only build and create affordable housing in the district but also pass and introduce policies that will help us get there. The second priority is to deal with homeless and the tent encampments in the Mission, which is partially related to housing but also has different components and aspects to it, and make sure that we are building more navigation centers so that there are dignified shelters for people to stay in until they get housing. The third priority is responding to the Trump administration, and protecting immigrants, protecting people’s health insurance and making sure that we can continue to implement police reform in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Any immediate pieces of legislation you think about writing soon?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I have a few pieces, they are dealing with homelessness and different housing issues in the Mission, and also protecting the Latino Cultural District around 24th street.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you tell me your thoughts about how the election went this year for you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It went extremely well in the end - I won, very candidly, with the vast majority of the votes, and it was an incredible learning experience. Incredible to talk to so many of the residents in the district and get to know the three neighborhoods on a deeper level, and I am incredibly happy with the resounding win. My excitement about that has been peppered by the results of the national election which was quite exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the campaign you talked about how we have to build towards affordability. You talked about building 5000 affordable units in the mission. Where do you see this housing going? And when do you expect it to come?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I want to build the 5000 affordable units over a 10-year period, some of those units are in the hopper right now, based on the work we been doing the past couple of years in David (Campos)’s office, and I am going to continue to fight for an average of 400-500 units a year going forward. It will be a mix of 100% affordable housing development, obtaining small sites and turning them into 100% permanent affordable housing, and then fighting for below-market-rate units and market-rate developments.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the hardest challenge facing your district right now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Housing and homelessness, which were my top two priorities (on the campaign).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You spent time as David Campos’ Chief of Staff. What parts of this office or legislation style are you going to keep or change?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;David (Campos) during his two terms in the office really focused a lot on city-wide issues in San Francisco, and I am really going to focusing inward on the district, at the issues that we been talking about housing, homelessness, schools - everything in our district - so I think that would be the main difference. I think what will be similar about us is that we both are very fierce fighters and we want to make sure the voices that are traditionally excluded from politics are front and center, and heard by the office and the city.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/after-13-years-geary-rapid-bus-project-moves-forward/">
    <title type="text">After 13 Years, Geary Rapid Bus Project Moves Forward</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:41857312-8e51-3c91-9fd9-cc24dc1d186a</id>
    <updated>2017-01-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/after-13-years-geary-rapid-bus-project-moves-forward/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Transit advocates saw a major victory at San Francisco City Hall last night after the County Transportation Authority (SFCTA) voted unanimously to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/transit-officials-approve-final-eir-geary-bus-project/&quot;&gt;certify the Environmental Impact Report&lt;/a&gt; (EIR) for the Bus Rapid Transit project along Geary Boulevard.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The dedicated center lanes for bus travel initially received a favorable feasibility report in 2004, after a funding shortfall rendered an underground subway proposal largely a pipe dream.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor London Breed, a commissioner on SFCTA, said that it had been her first goal upon winning her seat on the Board to “make magic happen” and replace all BRT projects with underground subways. Now, however, she was willing to accept that the project is something the city “can afford to accomplish.” Despite strenuous neighborhood efforts to delay the vote, the ten-person board unanimously agreed that it was high time to move the project forward.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Eric Mar, serving his penultimate day in office, eagerly expressed the need for faster bus service on one of the country’s busiest transit corridors. He made comparisons as far-ranging as Mexico City and Bogotá, Colombia to underscore the importance of dedicated lanes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfcta.org/prop-k-home&quot;&gt;The funding for Geary BRT&lt;/a&gt; was secured in 2003 with the passage of Proposition K, a half-cent sales tax measure that renewed 1989’s Proposition B.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Andrew Sullivan, who sat on the Expenditure Plan Advisory Committee for Proposition K, was optimistic to see the project finally coming to fruition.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“No way did we expect the process to take &lt;em&gt;thirteen years&lt;/em&gt; until the EIR when we approved the expenditure plan,” Mr. Sullivan wrote in an email. “Since that time, many BRT projects in North America including the LA Organge Line and Mexico City Metrobus have opened, while Geary has languished.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mr. Sullivan was also quick to dismiss concerns that Geary BRT approval could interfere with future plans for rail service. “Of course it's great news that the EIR has finally been approved, and we look forward to construction beginning ASAP,” he wrote.  “But we do also welcome the discussion of extending BART to the corridor.  There's no conflict between the two projects”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Storify compilation of our live Twitter coverage is below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;storify&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/geary-brt-sfcta-hearing-1-5-17/embed?header=false&amp;template=slideshow&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;750&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/geary-brt-sfcta-hearing-1-5-17.js?header=false&amp;template=slideshow&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;noscript&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/geary-brt-sfcta-hearing-1-5-17&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;View the story &quot;Geary BRT: SFCTA Hearing (1/5/17)&quot; on Storify&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/the-union-workhorse-ahsha-safai-district-11/">
    <title type="text">The Union Workhorse: Ahsha Safaí (District 11)</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:73585d74-d871-334b-868d-0c65ea61ade7</id>
    <updated>2017-01-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/the-union-workhorse-ahsha-safai-district-11/" />
    <author>
      <name>Bay City Beacon staff</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article initially appeared in the&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://thebaycitybeacon.com/32740/260596/a/the-union-workhorse-ahsha-safai-excelsior&quot;&gt;Bay City Beacon&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;We will be republishing subsequent interviews with new members of the Board of Supervisors next week.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The common wisdom in San Francisco politics is that you only get one shot at being Supervisor - people don't lose a race and then come back to win the next one. Ahsha Safai seems to prove that common wisdom is commonly wrong.  8 years ago, he ran against the now-outgoing Supervisor John Avalos, and lost the race by a close margin.  In the time between his first run and this past one, Safai invested in his neighborhood, strengthened his relationships in the community, and raised a family.  Now he stands as the Excelsior's very own Comeback Kid.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As an elected official, Safai seems like a stunningly good match for his District.  A family man with a wife and two kids, he represents one of the most residential neighborhoods of the city.  A union organizer, his constituents are often card-carrying union members with working-class backgrounds.  His candidacy received endorsements from both progressive and moderate leaders, which is rare in the bloodsport of SF politics, but a good fit for a district that seems to care less about ideology and more about the ability to tackle everyday problems.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The interview below has been edited for clarity and brevity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are your priorities for your first term?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I knocked on every door in District 11 and intently listened to what people had to say. The issues I ran on are a reflection of those conversations -- what voters told me to address and not lose sight of. Some of the issues constantly raised were universal pre-school for four-year-olds (citywide and city funded), the construction of more workforce housing, lack of parking and homelessness. I will tackle these issues, and more, in a regimented and empirically driven manner. There is no substitute for hard work, and I am ready to work.  If your readers are inclined, they can visit my campaign website to learn more about these, and other, issues and how I plan to address them in a more detailed manner.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there any immediate pieces of legislation you think about writing soon?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to prematurely announce what I will or will not be drafting before I am in office, however as to what legislation I will personally shepherd, that is not a mystery. You can expect that whatever I draft will reflect the voters’ mandate. Again, my campaign’s platform is a starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you tell me your thoughts about how the election went this year for you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;My race was challenging, but I expected that. I was diligent, spoke honestly about the issues and did not make false promises. People respect a straight shooter, and at the end of it all, I am happy to say that voters chose me to be their voice at City Hall. The campaign was a precursor to my impending tenure at City Hall – I will not sit idly, I will communicate with all stakeholders, and I will work hard to get things done.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Both you and your opponent came from union backgrounds, your race was considered to split labor. How are you going to mend or rebuild that coalition?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Reasonable minds can, and will, disagree. Although groups splintered into two camps, I never lost sight of the simple fact that at the end of the day we were all engaged because we had one simple goal: to uplift all San Franciscans. I will have an open door policy, will welcome everyone and will build coalitions to craft laws that positively impact our city’s residents.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the hardest challenge facing your district right now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I have an aversion to hyperbole; right now we face many pressing issues with no simple answers. A key issue, again, one of many, is the lack of workforce housing. Many people are being priced out because they just can’t qualify for aid, our housing crisis is real and damaging. I will put forward comprehensive solutions that will increase funding and eradicate red tape, and I will work with allies at all levels of government to tackle our housing ills. Like I said, going back to my original point, there are a whole host of challenges and it is my duty to address them as best and quickly as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As a citizen, you organized hundreds of neighbors to oppose Medical Cannabis Dispensaries. There is a new dispensary going into San Bruno Ave, what are your thoughts about that and are you going to continue to oppose future MCDs?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I am not anti-science or anti-cannabis, however what I am against is over-saturation. I opposed the opening of more medical marijuana dispensaries (MCDs) in District 11 because that burden was disproportionately falling on residents from that area.  And, it was also an issue that was constantly raised by people when I spoke to them directly. It is also inappropriate for me to say what I would vote for or against before the matter is presented to the Board of Supervisors.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-town-hall-addresses-inequality-warehouse-displacement/">
    <title type="text">Oakland Town Hall Addresses Inequality, Warehouse Displacement</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:1a35452e-3dcf-3361-aef8-b5aee8ddbb0e</id>
    <updated>2017-01-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-town-hall-addresses-inequality-warehouse-displacement/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Rebecca Kaplan, Oakland’s City Councilmember-at-large, convened a forum in City Hall with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/OaktownWarehouseCoalition/&quot;&gt;Oakland Warehouse Coalition&lt;/a&gt; last night. A panel including Councilmembers Gallo and Kalb, religious leaders, non-profit activists, and private sector organizers briefly discussed policy responses to the deadly Ghost Ship warehouse fire that killed 36 concertgoers on December 2nd. Over the course of three hours, attendance ranged from standing-room only to a handful of stragglers after the final public comment.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“As I see it, there’s no reason we can’t fight for fire safety and protecting people from displacement,” Kaplan said. “Whether it’s fire safety or lead paint safety, we shouldn’t accept that displacing everybody is the only solution.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kaplan mentioned pending legislation she would be bringing before the Council’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/191829997947283/&quot;&gt;Community Economic Development Committee&lt;/a&gt; to protect tenants from eviction as a result of code compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Central to the discussion was a proposed ordinance passed around the room printed on neon green paper by the Oakland Warehouse Coalition, the Emergency Tenant Protection Ordinance. The proposal includes many popular provisions—such as extending Just Cause eviction protection to tenants in properties not zoned for residential use—and other proposals widely not expected to be considered. For example, the Warehouse Coalition calls for the city to seize underutilized warehouse spaces via eminent domain to donate to artists.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The meeting began at an awkward pace, as many audible groans could be heard from the audience when a speaker quoted the bible for a second time in the first five minutes. “I’m a pagan,” the woman next to me grumbled. “Can I get up and say something irrelevant?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yet Kaplan dissuaded attendees from seeing her own religious background as a form of exclusion. Alluding to President-elect Donald Trump’s Muslim registry proposal, she declared that she intended to sign up for any such registry herself if it were introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Reverend Ken Chambers of the Westside Missionary Baptist Church adhered to concrete policy issues, discussing various financial hurdles to publicly financing affordable housing projects. In his view, tax liens imposed on vacant properties had some potential, but were insufficient. “The problem with those liens is, if you don’t have enough properties together, it doesn’t pencil out.” On the other hand, private developers, he argued, could muster the financing to make such projects work when they bought up properties, but that that made the need for inclusionary zoning policies even more urgent.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Two members of the panel were residents of undocumented live-work spaces themselves, including Jonah Strauss, a co-founder of the Oakland Warehouse Coalition. After briefly discussing the merits of the proposed ordinance, Strauss noted that the eviction of artists living at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/SevenDays/archives/2016/01/28/dozens-of-renters-lose-homes-as-city-closes-1919-market-street-warehouse-in-oakland&quot;&gt;1919 Market Street&lt;/a&gt; warehouse had been “encouraged by the owners.” He urged immediate action from the City Council to prevent landlords from knowingly fostering building code violations in order to evict tenants at their convenience.
“99.9% of live-work spaces in Oakland don’t look anything like the Ghost Ship. We don’t build like that,” Strauss said to marked applause.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The panel quickly expanded beyond the topic of housing and code enforcement to include calls for job training and a stronger social safety net for low-income residents. Susan Harmon of the Oakland non-profit Planting Justice not only described plans to create a “tiny homes” village on city land in West Oakland, but also called for a Guaranteed Basic Income to end the cycle of poverty for the most vulnerable Oaklanders.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But the bulk of the three hours, and the majority of the city’s pent-up frustrations regarding crushing economic inequality, was dominated by an open public comment period.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/oakland-town-hall-addresses-inequality-warehouse-displacement/oakmtg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Roughly 50% of the line to deliver public comment at Oakland City Hall&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;James Vann, an attorney with the Oakland Tenants Union, advocated for wider-reaching policy reform at the state level. “We think the definition of affordable housing must change,” Vann said, citing a current threshold of 60% Area Median Income as inadequate. (While some Below Market Rate units are price-indexed for 80-120% AMI, the Department of Housing and Urban Development defines “low-income” at 60-80%.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The majority of evictions are not caused by tenants,” he continued. Vann went on to advocate for a “flipping or speculation” tax so that real estate property transfers would fund city services and subsidized cooperative housing such as the Oakland Land Trust. He further urged the city to enforce owner occupancy for Ellis Act “owner move-in” evictions and require landlords to accept federal Section 8 vouchers.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Several homeless speakers, the majority of them black, spoke angrily of the city’s failure to care for its growing homeless population. While some described the situation as “genocide,” others offered tutorials in business law administered under the 29th Street freeway overpass, and another urged the council to reduce fines for parking violations in order to decriminalize living in cars.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many speakers came to corroborate Strauss’s argument that code compliance posed a significant threat for tenants. “I have so many documented personal stories of competent building inspectors being used in the wrong place,” one speaker said. “In one place with no fire code violations, they simply gave a cease-and-desist, which landlords use to void leases.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To cries of outrage from the audience, proprietors of the Everett &amp;amp; Jones restaurant in Jack London Square announced that they had been served a notice of violation for hosting a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Lefebvre_Sam/status/816843769592979456&quot;&gt;benefit concert&lt;/a&gt; without a cabaret license. Journalist Sam Lefebvre, who lives next door to the restaurant, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Lefebvre_Sam/status/816843769592979456&quot;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; a picture of the notice.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Local artist B.G. Anaraki mused on the larger problem represented by art spaces and live-work houses. “When I moved in 2006 it seemed my landlord was very eager to learn that we were artists and that we would be hosting parties. It was a house, not a warehouse. My theory is that they used us to further the decades-long agenda of pushing out historical residents of Oakland.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Anaraki described reliving the experience of watching the Ghost Ship burn whenever he closed his eyes at night. “Now when I have my eyes open I have to worry about all my friends being on the street, and it’s a shame.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A former resident of the Ghost Ship warehouse came with only two statements: thanking the public for their support, and urging immediate action. “I know that fire doesn’t wait,” she said. “It doesn’t wait for permits…Don’t wait.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Councilmembers Gallo and Kaplan stated that they would be supporting the proposed Emergency Ordinance. (Kalb had departed by the time they delivered their closing statements.) Oakland City Council returns from its winter recess on Tuesday, January 17.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/state-agencies-weigh-in-on-housing-and-mobility/">
    <title type="text">State Agencies Weigh In on Housing and Mobility</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:900d984e-c487-38b7-8d00-835c60a3a4df</id>
    <updated>2017-01-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/state-agencies-weigh-in-on-housing-and-mobility/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;California’s high housing costs are central to the state’s struggle with growing economic inequality. As state agencies analyze the causes and impacts of the chronic urban housing shortage, analysts have also begun zeroing in on the unique manifestations of the current widening income gap.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, the Legislative Analyst’s Office released a &lt;a href=&quot;http://lao.ca.gov/Publications/Report/3518&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; titled “Income Mobility in California Across Generations,“ illustrating a variety of characteristics underpinning California’s unique status as one of the country’s poorest and wealthiest states. The data is myriad and wide-ranging, but several firm conclusions stand out: while Californians generally see more income mobility across generations, this is not due to living in California.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/state-agencies-weigh-in-on-housing-and-mobility/lao-fifths.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: LAO)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While California sees higher intergenerational income mobility than the national average, moving to California is a statistically unwise choice for low-income families hoping to see their children prosper. Indeed, income mobility across generations was lowest in the top and bottom fifths of income levels. More populous counties such as San Francisco and Los Angeles saw greater income mobility than rural counties in decline, suggesting strong correlations between intergenerational mobility and proximity to diverse demographics and thriving job markets.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/state-agencies-weigh-in-on-housing-and-mobility/lao-fig8.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: LAO)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/state-agencies-weigh-in-on-housing-and-mobility/lao-fig9.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: LAO)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;So what does this have to do with housing?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Readers may recall a &lt;a href=&quot;https://faculty.chicagobooth.edu/chang-tai.hsieh/research/growth.pdf&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; coauthored by UC Berkeley economist Enrico Moretti which found that the urban housing shortage nationwide holds back annual GDP growth by nearly 10%. Moretti, a renowned expert on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nber.org/chapters/c7977.pdf&quot;&gt;agglomeration effects&lt;/a&gt;, argues that a lack of housing options stagnates real wage growth.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This week, California’s Office of Housing and Community Development (HCD) released a draft of its next Statewide Housing Assessment, “California’s Housing Future: Challenges and Opportunities.” Not surprisingly, the statewide housing shortage has a greater negative impact on populations facing the brunt of restricted income mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Among its most straightforward conclusions: “[l]ack of supply and rising costs are compounding growing inequality for younger Californians.” This state accounts for 22% of the country’s homeless population, and a staggering 33% of Californians pay at least half of their income toward rent.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/state-agencies-weigh-in-on-housing-and-mobility/hcd-incomems.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: California HCD)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;HCD found that new housing construction continues to be outpaced by demand, with only 80,000 dwelling units built statewide compared to an anticipated need of 180,000. Housing production has focused on single-family homes, whereas the decades between 1955 and 1990 saw a much higher production of multifamily dwellings.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;With an estimated population growth of 11 million by 2050, HCD concludes that the state needs 1.8 million more homes by 2025. Moreover, the vast increase in rents relative to wage growth will continue to disproportionately impact the California’s black, Hispanic, Pacific Islander and Native American populations.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/state-agencies-weigh-in-on-housing-and-mobility/hcd-race.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: California HCD)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, amending this supply shortfall in dense urban centers is described as a significant opportunity to curb the environmental detriments of sprawl, though HCD acknowledges that this is difficult to measure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The proximity of jobs, services, density, and the availability of public transportation are among the factors that can affect the need for automobile travel and thus transportation costs. In certain communities, higher housing costs can be mitigated by lower transportation costs when less affordable travel is required…Unlike housing affordability, which is widely accepted as paying no more than 30% of income towards housing costs, there is no official definition for housing and transportation costs combined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As the title implies, the report proceeds to identify opportunities to meet these strenuous policy challenges. The most significant opportunity identified is that of streamlining timely and costly local land-use discretion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Barriers and constraints (such as lengthy development review, lack of certainty…and local opposition) impact the type, quantity, and location of housing built…Local governments do not permit enough housing to meet their need, in part because they face competing priorities throughout the development process, including community opposition, incentives to approve sales-tax generating development…rather than residential development, and market conditions…In addition, lack of enforcement of State housing laws limit the effectiveness of existing tools intended to guide housing development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/state-agencies-weigh-in-on-housing-and-mobility/hcd-constraits.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: California HCD)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To ameliorate these compounding delays, HCD recommends streamlining the entitlement process and only maintaining public input “early and upfront” in the process. Further recommendations include greater regional cooperation and enforcement of State housing laws to ensure certainty and financial feasibility for new development. To amend the shortage of low-income housing, HCD also recommends reserving surplus public lands for deed-restricted or other forms of permanently affordable housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, intergenerational economic mobility in California is largely restricted to those already blessed with greater demographic potential for mobility. Your family, not your location, is your greatest measure of earning potential. Housing costs are a critical culprit.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ben Metcalf, the Director of HCD, sees a silver lining in all this. In an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.latimes.com/politics/essential/la-pol-ca-essential-politics-updates-california-housing-affordability-1483490282-htmlstory.html&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with the Los Angeles &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt;, he remarked: “If there is good news in all this, these are, in some cases, problems that we have created through local and state policies…because these are challenges that have been created through policies, we know we can fix them.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-all-is-in-flux-nothing-stays-the-same/">
    <title type="text">Op-Ed: All Is in Flux, Nothing Stays the Same</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:baa452a4-0e20-3593-a5a5-a19cb99a42b1</id>
    <updated>2017-01-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-all-is-in-flux-nothing-stays-the-same/" />
    <author>
      <name>Brian Hanlon</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boomcalifornia.com/&quot;&gt;Boom California&lt;/a&gt; recently published an &lt;a href=&quot;https://boomcalifornia.com/2016/12/29/a-boom-interview-in-conversation-with-jennifer-wolch-and-dana-cuff/&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with Mike Davis, a “chronicler of the California dark side and LA’s underbelly,” and advocate for community planning. I’ve [excerpted] &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hanlonbt/status/802318722429952000&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/hanlonbt/status/802318722429952000&lt;/a&gt;) sections from Davis’ best-known work, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ouleft.org/wp-content/uploads/Mike_Davis_City_of_Quartz.pdf&quot;&gt;“City of Quartz,”&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter to highlight how Los Angeles homeowners demanded land use and tax policies that enriched themselves while furthering racial and class exclusion. Davis is a talented prose stylist with a knack for skewering profiteering and segregationist Angelenos, but his lack of understanding of real estate markets leads him to support perverse policies. Below, I discuss shortcomings in his “progressive” approach and propose four suggestions when thinking about land use policy.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Devise policy to limit home prices, not land prices.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Davis assumes that “the stabilization of land values is the precondition for long-term democratic planning.” Like Davis, I support a Georgist Land-Value Tax, but the real problem for low- and middle-income people isn’t high land prices, it’s high home prices. Few people live on unimproved land. High land prices are a market signal to use land more intensely, i.e., to build dense housing instead of detached single-family homes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In hyper-expensive San Francisco, land acquisition costs are a small portion of the costs for new condo towers, but they are the majority of the costs for detached single-family homes. Urban policy that values class and racial inclusion will limit home-price appreciation by permitting more homes to be built.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most poor people live in market-rate housing. Don’t abandon them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Aside from a Land-Value Tax, Davis’ other big “nonrevolutionary” solution is to more strictly regulate land use. He wants to “municipalize strategic parts of the land inventory for affordable housing, parks and form-giving greenbelts.” Those are fine ideas IF the city either a) builds massive amounts of social housing on restricted land (politically &amp;amp; fiscally impossible) or b) permits private developers to meet the need for housing on unrestricted land (politically hard, fiscally easy, but not what Davis supports).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, home prices will climb and the poor will be displaced. Rent control helps incumbent residents, but does little for low-income migrants. If local policymakers seek to prevent displacement and permit in-migration of low-income people, they need to think more about the real estate market and less about publicly subsidized housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Value a diversity of uses and urban play over rigid long-term planning.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, Davis supports “long-term democratic planning” and thinks developers ruin social democracy by engaging in the political process to secure variances for their projects. On the other hand, Davis wants to allow a “democratic variety” in urban space and encourage “unprogrammed fun and discovery.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;These desires are incompatible. Limiting development and prescribing permissible land use activities restricts in-migration to wealthy residents and proscribes the creative adaptation of disused space. Weirdo 22 year-old artists aren’t going to apply for a below-market-rate housing waiting list, they’re going to move where rent and studio space are cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economic dynamism militates against long-term planning. Support flexible land use policies.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Davis believes “if you don’t intervene in the operation of land markets, you’ll usually end up producing the opposite result from what you intended.” As &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.law.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/stanford-law-policy-review/print/2014/01/mangin_25_stan._l._poly_rev_91.pdf&quot;&gt;housing scholarship&lt;/a&gt; makes clear, the reality is the opposite – if cities intervene in the operation of land markets via restrictive zoning, they may lower the price of land, but will increase the price of homes and worsen segregation. That’s not to say there is no need for infrastructure planning and encouraging home building along transit corridors, but councils of local residents are unlikely to concern themselves with the interests of nonresidents and therefore shouldn’t direct policy. What’s more, would-be planners face many unknown unknowns. As a former manager of the Communist Party’s bookstore, Mike Davis should take Marx’s analysis of capitalism in the “The Communist Manifesto” seriously:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The bourgeoisie cannot exist without constantly revolutionising the instruments of production, and thereby the relations of production, and with them the whole relations of society. Conservation of the old modes of production in unaltered form, was, on the contrary, the first condition of existence for all earlier industrial classes. Constant revolutionising of production, uninterrupted disturbance of all social conditions, everlasting uncertainty and agitation distinguish the bourgeois epoch from all earlier ones. All fixed, fast-frozen relations, with their train of ancient and venerable prejudices and opinions, are swept away, all new-formed ones become antiquated before they can ossify. All that is solid melts into air, all that is holy is profaned, and man is at last compelled to face with sober senses his real conditions of life, and his relations with his kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Not only do localities further exclusion when given the opportunity, they attempt to preserve existing built form and use when changed economic and social conditions demand alternatives. Marx could have been writing about California land use and tax policy when he &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1852/18th-brumaire/ch01.htm&quot;&gt;declared&lt;/a&gt;, “the tradition of all dead generations weighs like a nightmare on the brains of the living.” Let’s embrace the future by surrendering our futile desires for stability. Achieving inclusive communities demands it.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brian Hanlon is co-Executive Director of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carlaef.org/&quot;&gt;California Renters Legal Advocacy and Education Fund&lt;/a&gt; (CaRLA).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/meet-the-democrat-who-wants-california-democrats-to-focus-on-the-big-issues/">
    <title type="text">Meet the Democrat Who Wants California Democrats to Focus on the Big Issues</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a66e9abf-b968-3641-91f0-c6e11adbac0c</id>
    <updated>2017-01-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/meet-the-democrat-who-wants-california-democrats-to-focus-on-the-big-issues/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Alfred Twu wants your vote. But there’s a catch—if you live in California Assembly District 15, you must show up &lt;em&gt;in person&lt;/em&gt; on Saturday to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/uv?hl=en&amp;amp;pb=!1s0x80857934a4c28ae1:0x6188fb3430cdbde0!2m19!2m2!1i80!2i80!3m1!2i20!16m13!1b1!2m2!1m1!1e1!2m2!1m1!1e3!2m2!1m1!1e5!2m2!1m1!1e4!3m1!7e115!4zaHR0cDovL2FseW91bmcub3JnLzIwMTQvMDMv!5salbany+library+-+Google+Search&amp;amp;imagekey=!1e1!2shttp://alyoung.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/12/albany-lib-5.jpg&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwj5h9ua56bRAhUD5mMKHVl5Du8QoioIcTAK&quot;&gt;Albany Library&lt;/a&gt; from noon to 2pm. There you can cast votes for him, along with his slate of 13 other Democrats, for Assembly District Delegate. “Tell people to bring a pen,” he says at the conclusion of our interview. “We usually run out pretty quickly.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Does this sound too obscure and pointless to warrant your involvement? If you care about affecting policy change in California, you couldn’t be more wrong. Assembly Delegates serve two-year terms in which they attend annual state conventions to discuss policy initiatives and help shape the California Democratic Party’s agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a state controlled by a Democratic supermajority in the legislature, that’s tantamount to setting policy writ large.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Wherever the party agrees, the other side can’t stop us,” Twu says.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Twu ran as a party delegate pledging his vote to Senator Bernie Sanders during last year’s presidential primary. Building off that momentum, he now forms part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/1239369576157208/&quot;&gt;Democrats Rising&lt;/a&gt; slate for AD15, organized by East Bay Young Democrats member Seren Pendleton-Knoll.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/meet-the-democrat-who-wants-california-democrats-to-focus-on-the-big-issues/adem-front.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democrats Rising slate card, designed by Alfred Twu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I decided to run because I wanted to make housing a bigger part of the Democratic Party platform. I think out here, and really in most part of the country, housing is the largest expense people have,” Twu says. “With the mortgage interest deduction, and the bailouts of 2008, housing policy mostly focuses on homeowners. There’s not much talk about housing policy for people who rent.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Rent control comprises one of the slate’s top issues, as the urban housing shortage has led to a widespread outcry against California’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/its-time-to-overturn-the-state-ban-on-rent-control/Content?oid=4229744&quot;&gt;Costa Hawkins Act&lt;/a&gt;, which banned price controls for rental property built after 1975. “Right now people are hurting and need relief right away,” Twu says. “While more housing down the road will certainly help, the more immediate need is to get rent control in cities that don’t have the tradition of strong rent control we see in San Francisco and Oakland.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;By-right construction entitlement, a policy that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mercurynews.com/2016/09/21/commentary-jerry-browns-by-right-housing-plan-needs-another-try/&quot;&gt;Governor Jerry Brown&lt;/a&gt; tried and failed to pass last year, is far thornier in Twu’s mind, but he remains optimistic. “Making it easier to build new housing could shift people’s attention from being greedy landlords to extracting profit from building new buildings. In reality, there’s a lot of overlap between landlords and developers.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Twu also points to the demographic and political advantages central to the slate campaign strategy, which helps the candidates cover issues outside of their own primary focus. “Often, with forming a slate, the idea is getting people who are similar, but not too similar, so they all turn out different constituencies,” he says. His own constituency, in his view, is primarily formed of UC Berkeley students and pro-housing activist groups throughout the Bay Area.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/meet-the-democrat-who-wants-california-democrats-to-focus-on-the-big-issues/adem-back.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Full roster of the Democrats Rising AD15 slate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Democrats Rising slate is comprised of seven men and seven women from all across the district, ranging from Hercules and Richmond to North Oakland. “Other people on our slate [Ben Choi and Melvin Willis] were recently elected to the Richmond City Council, so they have their campaign volunteers and supporters. That’s why fracking and the oil trade, stopping Chevron in Richmond, are also among our big issues,” he adds.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/AD15Delegates2014/&quot;&gt;rival slate&lt;/a&gt; is kind of similar to ours, geographically speaking,” he notes, “but that slate was put together by our local Assembly member Tony Thurmond.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that different Assembly Districts vote for their delegates at different times. While AD15 votes on Saturday at noon, AD17 in San Francisco votes on Sunday at 10am. San Francisco’s western Assembly District, AD19, votes in Daly City on Saturday. You can find your Assembly District Delegate election &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cadem.org/our-party/adem/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/heres-the-package-four-assembly-bills-aim-to-tackle-housing-shortage/">
    <title type="text">Here's &quot;The Package&quot;: Four Assembly Bills Aim to Tackle Housing Shortage</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:9de3728a-a616-3d04-bfd5-ee4b74e23958</id>
    <updated>2016-12-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/heres-the-package-four-assembly-bills-aim-to-tackle-housing-shortage/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last week, we &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/chiu-seeks-additional-housing-funds-by-ending-real-estate-tax-benefit/&quot;&gt;covered&lt;/a&gt; Assemblymember David Chiu’s (D-SF) proposed bill to end the mortgage interest tax deduction for second homes to increase funding for the Low Income Housing Tax Credit (LIHTC). Since then, we’ve interviewed Assm. Chiu to discuss an &lt;a href=&quot;http://asmdc.org/members/a17/news-room/press-releases/assemblymember-david-chiu-joins-colleagues-to-announce-bills-to-address-affordable-housing-crisis&quot;&gt;entire package of ambitious legislation&lt;/a&gt; aimed at curbing the state’s crisis-level housing shortage.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In sum:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billNavClient.xhtml?bill_id=201720180AB71&quot;&gt;AB 71&lt;/a&gt; would eliminate the mortgage interest deduction that taxpayers can currently claim on a second home, typically a vacation residence. “Economists across the spectrum agree that the Mortgage Interest Deduction is highly regressive,” Chiu said. Because lower-income households typically do not itemize their deductions, the MID largely benefits higher-earning households. In 2012, 77% of benefits accrued from the federal MID went to those with incomes higher than $100,000 per year. Chiu estimates that the vacation home deduction cost California’s general fund $360 million in the past fiscal year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billTextClient.xhtml?bill_id=201720180AB72&quot;&gt;AB 72&lt;/a&gt;, introduced by Assemblymember Miguel Santiago (D-LA), would allocate funds for the state Attorney General’s office to enforce the &lt;a href=&quot;http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/codes_displaySection.xhtml?lawCode=GOV&amp;amp;sectionNum=65589.5&quot;&gt;Housing Accountability Act&lt;/a&gt;. So far, only private entities have sought litigation under the HAA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billTextClient.xhtml?bill_id=201720180AB73&quot;&gt;AB 73&lt;/a&gt; would create an incentive payments for cities to zone at higher densities and permit the construction of Transit-Oriented Development (TOD) with a minimum allotment of 20% of dwelling units price-indexed for middle- and lower-income households. The bill includes an environmental review component and prevailing wage requirement for union labor, two factors largely believed to have stalled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/08/unions-against-gov-browns-as-of-right-housing-plan.html&quot;&gt;Governor Jerry Brown’s housing streamlining proposa&lt;/a&gt;l this summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billNavClient.xhtml?bill_id=201720180AB74&quot;&gt;AB 74&lt;/a&gt;, known as the Housing for a Healthy California Act, would create a funding program to house chronically homeless Californians enrolled in Medi-Cal services. In other words, the bill explicitly ties supportive housing to healthcare funding. “To break the endless cycle of the revolving doors of emergency rooms, inpatient facilities, treatment centers and nursing homes,” Chiu wrote in a press release, “this new program would shift the paradigm by providing rental assistance for supportive housing to those individuals who are both homeless and receive significant public health care services.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In our interview, Assemblymember Chiu spoke more broadly of difficult times ahead under a Trump administration. “The threat to cut federal healthcare spending alone,” he said, “is very daunting” when considering its impact on the state’s budget. When asked if this could lead to reform for so-called “third-rail” fiscal issues, such as the property tax cap codified under Proposition 13, Chiu simply stated: “Everything is on the table.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/fear-and-finance-in-saint-francis-police-and-the-politics-of-city-pension-reform-part-1/">
    <title type="text">Fear &amp; Finance in Saint Francis: Policing the Politics of City Pension Reform (Part 1)</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:4fdb480a-4eff-3508-accb-c7253152206b</id>
    <updated>2016-12-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/fear-and-finance-in-saint-francis-police-and-the-politics-of-city-pension-reform-part-1/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When a city employee retires, should they draw a pension on your dime?—or theirs? Finding an acceptable middle ground for all stakeholders is becoming an increasingly heated topic as San Francisco &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/S-F-s-big-budget-falling-short-on-pensions-9214186.php&quot;&gt;anticipates a budget shortfall&lt;/a&gt; of several billion dollars, partly comprised of pension obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Herb Meiberger, a Chartered Financial Analyst who serves on the Executive Board of the San Francisco Employees’ Retirement System (SFERS), seems to understand the fundamental root of this tension. “[Union] members want lower employee contributions, and taxpayers want higher contributions. That’s the crux of the issue,” he said in a brief phone interview.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The SFERS Executive Board sets policy for the city’s pension fund, including percentages of asset allocations among stocks, bonds, and private equity. The fund’s total assets were valued at $20.4 billion last year. Assuming a 7.5% Return On Investment, the city is currently only able to guarantee 89.9% of its obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Underlying the heated election for Meiberger’s seat on the Board is a widening cultural rift over basic priorities in public retirement investments. For some, Cost Of Living Adjustment benefits (COLA) necessitate riskier investments for higher returns; others contend that inherently volatile capital markets require the utmost caution—or at the very least, an investor’s “due diligence”—when dealing with the livelihoods of retirees.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Meiberger sees himself as a “watchdog,” and in his view, his cautious and skeptical nature has made him powerful enemies. Former SFERS Board President Croce “Al” Casciato has boasted of raising nearly $185,000 in a little-known election to unseat Meiberger, who he accuses of costing SFERS millions with poor decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Casciato, a retired police captain, retired from SFERS in 2012. Recently, according to Larry Barsetti of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.protectourbenefits.org/index.php/action-alert/&quot;&gt;Protect Our Benefits PAC&lt;/a&gt;, a coalition of unions privately urged Casciato to run against Meiberger for a seat on the Board. The coalition includes &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifpte21.org/content/elect-al-and-protect-your-retirement-benefits&quot;&gt;IFPTE Local 21&lt;/a&gt;, IBEW Local 6, Union of American Physicians and Dentists, Municipal Executives Association, Municipal Attorneys Association, San Francisco Police Officer’s Association (SFPOA), San Francisco Veteran Police Officer’s Association (SFVPOA), Plumbers Local 38, and Teamsters Local 856.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/fear-and-finance-in-saint-francis-police-and-the-politics-of-city-pension-reform-part-1/al3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Campaign mailer for Al Casciato&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The October 20th journal of the SFPOA included an open letter urging Meiberger to withdraw his bid for reelection. Retired city employee Patrick Monette-Shaw penned an open letter &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stoplhhdownsize.com/What_Price_for_a_Seat_at_the_Retirement_Board_Table.pdf&quot;&gt;in response&lt;/a&gt;, challenging, among other things, Casciato’s claims that the city’s pension fund had lost $2 billion over the past few years. Though Casciato’s candidate statement asserts a $1.5 billion loss—$500 million less than his campaign mailer alleges—Monette-Shaw argues that a recent valuation found a much smaller shortfall of $422 million. Monette-Shaw’s letter goes on to describe a betrayal that “smacks of ethical bankruptcy,” given POA’s endorsement of Meiberger in 2006, and IFTPE Local 21 endorsing him as recently as 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Why the sudden shift?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It’s all about hedge funds,” Meiberger shoots back. “They want hedge funds, I don’t. They want some lapdog, they don’t want a watchdog.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/fear-and-finance-in-saint-francis-police-and-the-politics-of-city-pension-reform-part-1/al1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attack ad on Herb Meiberger (same mailer as above)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.investopedia.com/terms/h/hedgefund.asp&quot;&gt;Hedge funds&lt;/a&gt; are a form of limited partnership investments in which pooled funds can be leveraged with borrowed money in pursuit of higher returns. The industry of specialized investment managers has gained popular appeal due to a relative dearth of restrictions from the Securities and Exchange Commission relative to more traditional forms of investment with lower risks, such as mutual funds or index funds.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On February 11, 2015, Meiberger was the sole “No” vote on the Board when SFERS sought to invest $3 billion of pensions, 15% of its total assets, in hedge funds. Meiberger even &lt;a href=&quot;http://herbmeiberger.com/retirement-board-news/due-diligence/&quot;&gt;sought advice personally&lt;/a&gt; from investment magnate Warren Buffett, who warned him categorically against hedge funds. “I would not go with hedge funds – would prefer index funds,” Mr. Buffett wrote in reply. Eventually, the Board only approved a $1 billion investment.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Hedge fund managers often achieve a status akin to rock stars in the world of finance. Anthony Scaramucci, a top economic advisor to Donald Trump, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2013/05/08/hedge-fund-impresario-plays-host-in-las-vegas/?_r=0&quot;&gt;once wrote&lt;/a&gt;: “Mutual funds are the propeller plane, while hedge funds are the fighter jets.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Simon Lack, author of the seminal 2012 book &lt;em&gt;The Hedge Fund Mirage,&lt;/em&gt; argued that hedge funds bear lower returns and higher management costs relative to treasury bills. “Once a public pension plan recognizes that 5% is a better allocation to hedge funds than 20%,” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brandes.com/docs/default-source/brandes-institute/the-hedge-fund-mirage-qa-simon-lack&quot;&gt;he said&lt;/a&gt;, “they’re no longer relying on hedge funds to solve their funding gap, and consequently they can select more esoteric managers. This is how hedge fund investing was done during the period of time whose historic returns were generated that they’re seeing to emulate.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The political rift over hedge funds reached a breaking point in the SFERS after a controversial Currency Overlay Hedge Fund investment lost the SFERS Fund nearly $70 million, over Meiberger’s strong objections. (The Currency Overlay strategy was designed to attenuate leveraged risks with favorable foreign currency exchange rates.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While the majority of the Board has sought to reduce SFERS’s hedge fund allocations from 15% to 5%, their Chief Investment Officer recommended an allocation of 25%. This move appears to have galvanized Casciato’s supporters against Meiberger’s perceived moderation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It’s a power issue,” Meiberger speculates. “They like to be associated with billionaire hedge fund managers, and want to get their pictures taken together.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Meiberger adds that hedge funds are riskier not only due to their fees and returns, but a lack of liquidity. In September of 2014, the California Public Employees Retirement Sytem (CalPERS) &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/jonhartley/2014/09/22/why-calpers-is-exiting-the-hedge-fund-space/#7fff8579101f&quot;&gt;decided&lt;/a&gt; to liquidate $4 billion in hedge funds. Two years later, CalPERS &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortune.com/2016/01/13/calpers-hedge-funds-2/&quot;&gt;has yet to completely divest&lt;/a&gt; from hedge funds due to their inherent illiquidity.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;With the exception of an endorsing campaign mailer funded by the SEIU 1021, Meiberger says he is running a self-funded grassroots campaign. Candidates have not yet filed campaign finance reports with the city’s Ethics Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor’s Note: We will be running subsequent parts of this story next week after scheduled interviews with both Casciato and Meiberger.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/from-the-editor-next-week-today/">
    <title type="text">From the Editor: Next Week, Today</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:9a8e9fdb-5069-3514-8736-9cebc739ba85</id>
    <updated>2016-12-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/from-the-editor-next-week-today/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As the despondency and disgust for the burning dumpster fire that is 2016 gives way to dread and ambivalence toward the unknown horrors of 2017, we wish to alert our readers to an abundance of political and cultural happenings taking place in the Greater Bay Area Metropolis as of next week. This may also serve as a subtle preview for next week’s content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Monday, January 2nd: &lt;strong&gt;The Ivy Room&lt;/strong&gt; in Albany hosts &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/1074708429321927/&quot;&gt;a tribute&lt;/a&gt; to Berkeley’s iconic punk imprint Lookout! Records as part of a week-long &lt;em&gt;Lookouting&lt;/em&gt; retrospective. The concert will feature resurrected punk bands from days of yore—the spastic, slapstick Surrogate Brains from Stockton, and Santa Rosa booze-laden garage-punks The Invalids—along with Dr. Frank, the polymath auteur behind classic pop-punk outfit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4Xn9ZhmY_10&quot;&gt;The Mr. T Experience&lt;/a&gt;. $10 / 21+ / 8pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, January 3rd: The &lt;strong&gt;San Francisco Municipal Transportation Agency&lt;/strong&gt; (SFMTA) Board of Directors meeting will be held at 1:00pm in City Hall, 1 Dr. Carlton B. Goodlett Place, Room 400. The Board is widely expected to approve the Final Environmental Impact Report (FEIR) for the Geary Bus Rapid Transit project, which would dedicate a lane on either side of Geary Boulevard to Muni buses. With an initial feasibility report completed in 2007, Geary BRT is nearly a decade in the making, but evidently, some still feel that change has come too soon. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/transit-officials-offer-tweaks-to-geary-brt-project/&quot;&gt;Despite local pressure&lt;/a&gt; for the Board to delay approval to make time for more “community input,” former Richmond District Supervisor Eric Mar argued that “endless delays” were no longer necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Wednesday, January 4th: &lt;strong&gt;Oakland Councilmember-at-large Rebecca Kaplan&lt;/strong&gt; will host &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/1543924842289311/&quot;&gt;a forum with the Oakland Warehouse Coalition&lt;/a&gt; in Council  Chambers, Oakland City Hall,  at 5pm to discuss the city’s responses to the Ghost Ship warehouse fire. Kaplan’s office has announced: “The forum will address housing, homelessness, and jobs, and will be focused on solutions. We’d love for you to come and bring folks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/from-the-editor-next-week-today/oneoak.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;One Oak Street Project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Thursday, January 5th: San Francisco’s &lt;strong&gt;Planning Commission&lt;/strong&gt; will review the &lt;a href=&quot;http://commissions.sfplanning.org/cpcpackets/2009.0159E_Draft%20EIR.pdf&quot;&gt;Draft Environmental Impact Report&lt;/a&gt; (EIR) for the One Oak Street Project, a 40-story 310-unit residential tower proposed at 1500-1540 Market Street. The project seeks to add a public plaza on Oak Street, to be serviced by new elevators to the Van Ness Muni station below. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.themarkcompany.com/project/one-oak/&quot;&gt;The Mark Company&lt;/a&gt;, the developer behind One Oak, will need to extend the Height and Bulk District 120/400-R-2 designation across the block for the design to be zoning-compliant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Friday, January 6th: Oakland techno showcase &lt;strong&gt;Obscura Machina&lt;/strong&gt; will go on as planned, despite the passing of its gregarious organizer, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/in-memoriam-micah-danemayer/&quot;&gt;Micah Danemayer&lt;/a&gt;, in the tragic Ghost Ship fire. Danemayer’s collaborator Devyn Saturnus will debut their new project Red Cellar as part of his plans to carry on the torch for his fallen friend’s imprint, Discarded Records. Red Cellar will be joined by the dark, minimal electro-croonings of &lt;a href=&quot;https://stacian.bandcamp.com/album/songs-for-cadets&quot;&gt;Stacian&lt;/a&gt;, the industrial duo &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/glowingdaggerrecords/sets/plattenbau-body-of-desire&quot;&gt;Plattenbau&lt;/a&gt;, lo-fi ambient producer &lt;a href=&quot;https://discardedrecords.bandcamp.com/album/fascination-scenarios-of-violence-009-2&quot;&gt;Fascination&lt;/a&gt;, and Los Angeles-based &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/djsailorsaturn/&quot;&gt;DJ Sailor Saturn&lt;/a&gt;. The event will be held at The Night Light, 311 Broadway, Oakland. All proceeds will fund the Micah Danemayer Memorial Scholarship at the Massachusetts College of Art and Design. $7 / 21+ / 9pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/298150738&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/mountain-view-tenants-rally-to-defend-rent-control-measure/">
    <title type="text">Mountain  View Tenants Rally to Defend Rent Control Measure</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a2f3ad5a-c571-31fd-8a3e-1af648f41ce3</id>
    <updated>2016-12-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/mountain-view-tenants-rally-to-defend-rent-control-measure/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yesterday morning, Judge Beth McGowen approved a restraining order filed against the City of Mountain View by the California Apartment Association (CAA) to halt the implementation of a voter-approved rent control ordinance known as Measure V. The order stipulates that protections against just-cause evictions are to remain in place, meaning that tenants could still feasibly resist evictions filed in anticipation of caps on rent increases.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;By 4:30pm, the Mountain View Tenants Coalition (MVTC) had organized a demonstration in front of City Hall to protest the decision. Mountain View’s City Council voted in a closed session to encourage City Attorney Jamie Quinn to accept the temporary restraining order. The CAA is expected to seek an injunction against Measure V in February or March. Until then, tenants will have no legal recourse to protect themselves from rent increases.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The temporary restraining order is effective through February 3, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Median rents in Mountain View have increased by over $1000 in the past five years, with some estimates closer to $2,000. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zillow.com/mountain-view-ca/home-values/&quot;&gt;Zillow&lt;/a&gt; estimates the median home price at $1.4 million.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“[The council] tried to sabotage Measure V by putting a competing measure on the ballot,” said Daniel DeBolt, spokesperson for MVTC. “It was confusing because it was also a rent control measure, but much weaker.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;He credited the grassroots organizing of at least 150 Tenants Coalition volunteers, who were able to pass Measure V with only $43,000 raised in campaign funds.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;DeBolt also insisted that many opponents’ arguments were specious or unsupported by data. Measure V specifically exempts new developments, and allows landlords to pass through capital improvement costs to tenants, which &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yesonvmv.org/faq&quot;&gt;MVTC says&lt;/a&gt; invalidates claims that rent control would hinder construction or disincentivize maintenance of rental properties.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The bottom line is that landlords lost, and the council lost. Now they’re neglecting their duty as public officials to uphold the law, allowing landlords to get this temporary restraining order before we could intervene,” DeBolt continued. “It’s totally shameful.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;DeBolt qualified his criticism by noting that Councilmember Lenny Siegel and Mayor Pat Showalter largely supported Measure V, though the mayor was hesitant to support it as a charter amendment that would be more difficult to amend or repeal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Ironically,” DeBolt added, “the City Council declared Mountain View a ‘human rights city’ this week, but they refuse to honor and defend the renters rights that voters approved on November 8.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover photo by Daniel DeBolt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/court-rules-muni-light-rail-expansion-may-proceed/">
    <title type="text">Court Rules Muni Light-Rail Expansion May Proceed</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:5de72565-0143-3e49-9811-401c74e1ac1f</id>
    <updated>2016-12-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/court-rules-muni-light-rail-expansion-may-proceed/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A relatively quiet decision by California’s First Circuit Court of Appeals may have significant impacts on future lawsuits regarding urban infrastructure. In &lt;em&gt;The Committee for Re-Evaluation of the T-Line Loop v. San Francisco Municipal Transportation Agency, et al,&lt;/em&gt; the appellate court dismissed a suit seeking to require a new Environmental Impact Report (EIR) for the expansion of the T-Line Muni Train into San Francisco’s Bayview neighborhood. Drawing from the precedent of a previous case from this year, &lt;em&gt;Friends of the College of San Mateo Gardens v. San Mateo County Community College District&lt;/em&gt;, the court ruled that the SFMTA could proceed with the project relying on an EIR from 1998, rather than having to submit a new report.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The T-Line Loop was originally designed as part of the Third Street Light Rail Project, which submitted an EIR in 1998. Due to budget shortfalls, the expansion was stalled until 2013, when SFMTA received a $10 million grant from the Federal Transportation Agency to complete infrastructure projects in the Mission Bay and Bayview area.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The particular loop in question would allow trains to turn around midway through the line to accommodate passengers for special events at AT&amp;amp;T Park and other nearby venues. SFMTA submitted memorandums several years ago to the Planning Department asserting that the California Environmental Quality Act (CEQA) did not require an additional EIR to be submitted, and the city agency agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;By definition, opponents of the project did not.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;J.R. Eppler, president of the Potrero Boosters Neighborhood Association, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/muni-t-third-loop-alleviate-overcrowding-simplify-travel/&quot;&gt;told&lt;/a&gt; the San Francisco &lt;em&gt;Examiner&lt;/em&gt; that significant residential development in the Dogpatch neighborhood necessitated further environmental study. He also argued that because loop itself lacked any stop for passengers to board, there may be dangers to pedestrian safety supporting his preference to relocate the loop several blocks South.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Malia Cohen also told the &lt;em&gt;Examiner&lt;/em&gt; that she was sensitive to local residents’ concerns and would help advocate for the alternative loop location.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The appellate court found that the 1998 EIR still met substantial standards of evidence—“that the original environmental document retains some informational value.” The court considered SFMTA’s memorandums to the Planning Department from 2012 and 2014 as satisfactory signs of “informational value.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The decision affirms under the &lt;em&gt;San Mateo Gardens&lt;/em&gt; substantial evidence standard that agencies may continue to rely on previous Environmental Impact Reports (EIRs), regardless of age, so long as they retain information value,” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hklaw.com/publications/Reliance-on-1998-EIR-Under-CEQA-Upheld-Based-on-Substantial-Evidence-12-20-2016/&quot;&gt;writes Jennifer Hernandez&lt;/a&gt;, an attorney at Holland &amp;amp; Knight. The firm is known for releasing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hklaw.com/publications/In-the-Name-of-the-Environment-Litigation-Abuse-Under-CEQA-August-2015/&quot;&gt;numerous studies&lt;/a&gt; on the use/abuse of CEQA to suppress the construction of infill development and transit infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We were advocating for moving the loop several blocks further south, so that there would be stops serving Dogpatch,” Eppler wrote in an email. “We're also concerned about potential reductions in service to Bayview. We were advocating for &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; T-expansion, and smarter, modern, routing of transit.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The decision may set precedent unfavorable to other appeals under CEQA, such as the recent appeal of a project at &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/11/in-stunner-city-strikes-down-major-mission-project/&quot;&gt;1515 South Van Ness Avenue&lt;/a&gt;, in which opponents claimed the Eastern Neighborhood Plan EIR did not address the new dwelling units’ risk of displacement effects. Outgoing Supervisor David Campos led the Board’s unanimous vote to uphold the appeal, despite his observation that the appeal was not yet legally sound.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/on-haight-street-a-noise-music-family-reunion/">
    <title type="text">On Haight Street, a Noise Music &quot;Family Reunion&quot;</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:2d7b4f0e-5345-368e-aa4e-aea41eb64d1e</id>
    <updated>2016-12-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/on-haight-street-a-noise-music-family-reunion/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night at the Second Act Gallery, friends embraced; smiles abounded; outside, some gathered in circular formations to pass around weed and pizza. Oh, yes, and there was music.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Second Act, a stalwart of San Francisco’s experimental and electronic music scenes, now shares its home with another longtime Haight institution, The Bookbinder, which is setting up &lt;a href=&quot;http://hoodline.com/2016/10/booksmith-expanding-into-second-act-space-with-the-bindery&quot;&gt;The Bindery&lt;/a&gt; in the gallery's front space. On this night, musicians and fans gathered to pay homage to the music of &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/in-memoriam-jsun-adrian-mccarty/&quot;&gt;Jsun McCarty&lt;/a&gt;, with all proceeds going to memorialize another victim of the Oakland Ghost Ship Fire, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/in-memoriam-micah-danemayer/&quot;&gt;Micah Danemayer&lt;/a&gt;. Organizers estimated $300 raised for a scholarship fund in Danemayer’s name at his alma mater, the Massachusetts College of Art and Design.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Northern California noise connoisseurs Xome (Sacramento) and Tralphaz (Oakland) headlined with a collaborative set lasting no more than five minutes. The sheer auditory onslaught they delivered beggars description. Having forgotten my earplugs, it should suffice to say that I was able to enjoy the sonic evocations of a satanic root canal in Chernobyl with perfect clarity from outside.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Everyone’s here. People I haven’t seen in ages,” one attendee told me. “It feels like a family reunion.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the several dozen people packed into a small room (with multiple modes of egress, mind you) did make it feel like an intimate gathering.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco-based &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/waxy-tomb&quot;&gt;Waxy Tomb&lt;/a&gt;, the electronic project of Julia Litman-Cleper, opened the night with something between a sceance and an out-of-body experience. Litman-Cleper wove an auditory maze of high-pitched screeches, some feeling barely on the edge of human perception, over an ever-shifting foundation of factory-like rhythms evoking steel mills and broken dial-up modems.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the night’s biggest surprise was &lt;a href=&quot;http://resipiscent.com/midmight/&quot;&gt;Midmight&lt;/a&gt;, a mysterious semi-duo of sound wizards fearlessly toeing the line between deadpan anti-performance and austere, hyper-focused experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/on-haight-street-a-noise-music-family-reunion/midmight2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Midmight at the Second Act, 12/21/16&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mightmight’s leader sat cross-legged on the floor, shielding their face with a massive lampshade of a hat as they cranked out earsplitting textures and pre-recorded samples. At times soothing and mysterious, at others violently loud, a certain levity came about as a second performer dribbled a basketball across the floor. It wasn’t quite clear they were part of the act until they joined the mayhem at a table in the corner equipped with electronic doodads.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Local synth-master &lt;a href=&quot;https://branpos.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Bran(...)Pos&lt;/a&gt; led his new trio with Matt Ingalls and Hans Grusel, dubbed “I Should Have Cut The Eyes Different,” through an equally spectacular but wildly uncategorizable set. While Mr. (…)Pos conducted from behind a makeshift tympani, his fellow musicians provided a live score via woodwinds and keyboards to an eerie, unsettling collage of Christmas cartoons. At several points, the audience seemed unsure if it was time to applaud until more atonal chirping or distorted samples of baroque music interrupted their confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;And what’s left to be said of Xome and Tralphaz? Nothing, really. Their performance was as beautiful and cathartic as one can hope for, a whirlwind run through any and all existent pitches, with unpredictable dynamics eschewing emotion and melody with zero respect for the attendees’ eardrums.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Micah and Jsun would be proud.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Unlike most performances reviewed here, last night’s concert is unique in that it was filmed in its entirety for your viewing pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BQJG44PeHig&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Flyer courtesy of resipiscent&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/race-class-and-place-uneven-impacts-of-the-housing-shortage-audio/">
    <title type="text">Race, Class, and Place: Uneven Impacts of the Housing Shortage (Audio)</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:c673e5b6-0540-359c-9f9e-5778cbfc3d7b</id>
    <updated>2016-12-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/race-class-and-place-uneven-impacts-of-the-housing-shortage-audio/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carlaef.org/resources/&quot;&gt;California Renters Legal Advocacy &amp;amp; Education Fund&lt;/a&gt; (CaRLA) hosted a panel discussion on intersectional justice issues arising from the state's housing shortage. An estimated 130 people attended.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&quot;Yes, zoning restrictions and requiring multiple approvals harms affordability and increases segregation,&quot; said Brian Hanlon, co-founder of CaRLA. Mr. Hanlon gives us the scoop on the four panelists:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As a scholar at UCLA, Michael Lens' research interests vary, but he published a major paper about the effects of land use policies on economic segregation. Professor Lens understands that saying no to housing means saying yes to segregation and denying people access to opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kate Downing not only co-founded a successful YIMBY organization in Palo Alto, she was a former Planning Commissioner who regularly critiqued Palo Alto's exclusionary land use practices, which drove low- and middle-income people away from the city.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As a long-time affordable housing practitioner and now Chief of Staff to the Mayor of Oakland, Tomiquia Moss is uniquely qualified to discuss the effects of the housing shortage in Oakland and the politics of possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Before leading California's Department of Housing and Community Development, Ben Metcalf was an Assistant Secretary at HUD and worked at BRIDGE Housing. Ben understands which legislative changes at the state level could spur housing construction and ease the housing shortage, as well as the complicated politics that have thwarted past efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Stream the recording of this fascinating panel below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/298914402&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;



Michael Lens' presentation:



&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://docs.google.com/gview?url=http://www.carlaef.org/s/SF-Yimby-Dec-2016.pdf&amp;embedded=true&quot; style=&quot;width:718px; height:500px;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/race-class-and-place-uneven-impacts-of-the-housing-shortage-audio/laura-crowd-2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(courtesy: Laura Clark)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kate Downing's  presentation:&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://docs.google.com/gview?url=http://www.carlaef.org/s/CARLA-talk-Kate.pdf&amp;embedded=true&quot; style=&quot;width:718px; height:500px;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover photo by Bobak Esfandiari&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/chiu-seeks-additional-housing-funds-by-ending-real-estate-tax-benefit/">
    <title type="text">Chiu Seeks Additional Housing Funds by Ending Real-Estate Tax Benefit</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:008d02f1-dd5e-3d66-bdbd-1ca526d035f9</id>
    <updated>2016-12-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/chiu-seeks-additional-housing-funds-by-ending-real-estate-tax-benefit/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Californians eager to see additional funds for low-income housing may soon see relief from a proposal to fund such programs with additional tax revenue levied on those with significant real estate assets. Specifically, Assemblymember David Chiu (D – San Francisco) has proposed ending the state’s mortgage interest deduction for owners with a second home.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Chiu’s bill, AB 71, would direct new revenue to fund existing tax credits for the construction of low-income housing. Dubbed the &lt;a href=&quot;http://asmdc.org/members/a17/news-room/press-releases/assemblymember-david-chiu-joins-colleagues-to-announce-bills-to-address-affordable-housing-crisis&quot;&gt;Bring California Home Act&lt;/a&gt;, the bill, co-authored by Assemblymembers Ting (D – SF) and Mullin (D – San Mateo) would bring an additional $300 million to the Low Income Housing Tax Credit (LIHTC).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The bill comes as part of a multi-pronged set of proposals aimed at easing the state's housing woes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Because there's no one solution to the housing crisis, we put forward this package of solutions,” Chiu said in a briefphone interview. “[The package will] increase funding, incentivize and streamline housing creation, and enforce existing housing laws. AB 71 will address the funding, so that's the context this fits into.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The state’s mortgage interest deduction represents California’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lao.ca.gov/handouts/State_Admin/2013/Housing-Tax-Expenditure-031813.pdf&quot;&gt;largest investment in housing&lt;/a&gt;, at a cost of $4.6 billion in 2010. The nonpartisan &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/publications/options-reform-deduction-home-mortgage-interest-1&quot;&gt;Tax Policy Center&lt;/a&gt; think-tank found that the federal tax benefit costs the U.S. Treasury nearly $95.5 billion per year, disproportionately benefiting the top 20% of incomes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though Democrats have since seized a supermajority in the state legislature, California Republicans are not fond of Chiu’s proposal. Assemblymember Marc Steinorth (R – Rancho Cucamonga), leader of the California GOP Caucus, released a statement opposing AB 71, stating in part: “The plan introduced today is simply paying lip service and fails to address the very root cause of the housing crisis we are currently suffering: a lack of housing supply available to first-time homebuyers.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Governor Jerry Brown’s proposal to streamline the construction of new housing failed to gain enough support from the legislature, due in no small part to &lt;a href=&quot;https://ad40.asmrc.org/featured-news/assemblyman-steinorth-says-sacramento%E2%80%99s-newly-unveiled-housing-plan-won%E2%80%99t-resolve&quot;&gt;GOP opposition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Steinorth is the author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billTextClient.xhtml?bill_id=201720180AB53&quot;&gt;AB 53&lt;/a&gt;, the Homeowners Savings Account bill, encouraging new homebuyers to save money in a tax-free account to cover the down payment and closing costs of a first-time home purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-the-golden-door/">
    <title type="text">Op-Ed: The Golden Door</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:584aee32-36ee-3d41-bd05-c543a7ad45de</id>
    <updated>2016-12-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-the-golden-door/" />
    <author>
      <name>Richard Mehlinger</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Send these, the homeless, tempest-tost to me,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I lift my lamp beside the golden door!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;—Emma Lazarus, &quot;The New Colossus&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;So you live in a liberal enclave in a blue state, one of the big progressive cities. One of those places where you're more likely to see a Sumatran tiger than someone who openly backed Donald Trump. One of those Sanctuary Cities. You want to do something, but well, locally it's already about as progressive as it's possible to get... right?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Well, no. There is still plenty of injustice right here to fight, and I want to focus on one of the biggest: housing. Housing prices here are doing real, serious, ongoing harm to local residents, especially minority communities that are being driven out of neighborhoods they've lived in for decades. Landlords and property owners have soaked up most of the riches generated by the tech booms of the past thirty years. 
Meanwhile, the working classes and the poor are being pushed further and further out, forced to make longer and longer commutes, which, besides being devastating to personal and family life, damage the environment and increase strain on our infrastructure. Others are living out of their cars, or on friends’ couches, or in unsafe housing like &lt;a href=&quot;http://wearyourvoicemag.com/more/social-justice/housing-crisis-not-ravers-blame-oakland-fire&quot;&gt;the Oakland Ghost Ship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But there's another group of people harmed by the housing crisis: the people who can't come here. This isn't only about economic opportunity, though the economic damage caused by the inability of people from high unemployment regions to migrate to regions with a labor shortage should not be underestimated. The fact is, Trump’s election has unleashed some very ugly forces. The Klan is on the march. Swastikas are cropping up. There has been a surge in racist, misogynistic, homophobic, and transphobic violence—verbal and physical assaults, arson, beatings, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/news/article/Slaying-fueled-by-hate-unsettles-El-Sobrante-10659150.php&quot;&gt;murder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In short, the forces of bigotry and white supremacy see Trump's victory as their victory. The suicide, homelessness, and abuse rates that queer and especially trans youth suffer are already national scandals. Under President Trump and Vice President Pence, things will get worse for them. And if Trump moves forward with his “deportation force”, immigrant communities across the country will be threatened.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;So we need to provide a shelter from the storm that's coming. We cannot retreat into our enclaves and pull up our drawbridges. No, we need to be the safe spaces that his supporters mock. Trump accuses us of being Sanctuary Cities? Well, so be it. We should wear that badge with Pride. Let us be the shining city on the hill, a beacon to the oppressed. Let us offer a haven to the victims of the coming persecutions.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But we cannot do that if they have no place to live once they arrive. Everyone knows San Francisco's housing prices are outrageous, but the fact is housing is increasingly unaffordable throughout the country, especially in our would-be Sanctuary Cities. New York, DC, LA, Seattle, and Portland are all being severely affected by rising housing prices.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;So how the hell is the trans kid in Oklahoma who got kicked out by their parents going to live here when the rent for a studio is over $2,000 a month? How is the Muslim family that no longer feels safe in Tennessee going to find a home in the Bay when virtually all of the new housing being constructed has only one or two bedrooms? What good is it to the undocumented immigrant that our city claims to be a sanctuary if she cannot afford to pay the rent without working eighty hours a week?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It's great to be nice to the people Trump is beating up, but how can we claim to be welcoming when none of those people can actually afford to live here? No, if we are truly to be Sanctuary Cities, we must build far more housing than we have in recent decades.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;So enough with the contempt for newcomers, the naive fear of &quot;Manhattanization&quot;, the coded pleas to &quot;preserve neighborhood character.&quot; Enough of the soft racism of gentrification, but also enough pretending that gentrification is a matter of personal choice rather than of brute economics. It's time to stop making excuses, and to dismantle the NIMBY power in our communities.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We cannot be the ones to throw up walls. Let us lift the lamp beside the golden door, throw open our golden gates, and show America what a true sanctuary looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Richard Mehlinger is a software engineer (yes, one of those) living in Sunnyvale. He received his master’s degree in history from UC Riverside in 2011, and is firmly of the opinion that the rent is too damn high. You can reach him at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:rmehlinger@gmail.com&quot;&gt;rmehlinger@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/yimby-party-releasing-comic-book-essay/">
    <title type="text">YIMBY Party Releasing Comic Book Essay</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:ad514b37-a2b2-3b04-a0b7-22a8ed29ced0</id>
    <updated>2016-12-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/yimby-party-releasing-comic-book-essay/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Metropolitan Observer&lt;/em&gt; is delving into the world of print publishing with one of the most exciting comic book projects this ragtag team of political nerds could imagine. A quick recap:&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Less than three years ago, local journalist Kim-Mai Cutler blew Bay Area housing politics wide open with her incendiary essay, &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2014/04/14/sf-housing/&quot;&gt;How Burrowing Owls Lead to Vomiting Anarchists&lt;/a&gt;. Cutler sought to redraw alliances where she saw petty, shallow class-warfare rhetoric, and did the math to show how California landowners would profit from the latest employment boom regardless of how much new housing was built. Her sharp, even-handed analysis also called upon free-market faithfuls to consider the plight of those most vulnerable to being displaced, for whom market forces offer no immediate relief.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Thus the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfyimby.org/&quot;&gt;SF YIMBY&lt;/a&gt; Party was born. A formidable alliance of renters &lt;em&gt;qua&lt;/em&gt; renters, defying easy categorization with a broad multipartisan swath of support, the Yes In My Back Yard coalition could hardly have framed the problem so effectively without Cutler’s leadership. The region suffers from a raw &lt;em&gt;housing shortage&lt;/em&gt;, and restricting housing options only helps those who already own rapidly-appreciating real estate equity. Kim-Mai has worked tirelessly to make this crystal-clear for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Enter Oakland-based cartoonist &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.krustywheatfield.com/&quot;&gt;Kelsey Westphal&lt;/a&gt;, who we hired to draw a handful of political comics. Readers expressed delight upon our publication of her much-anticiapted “Atherton Police Blotter” comic (reprinted below), so we decided to get ambitious. Kelsey will burn the midnight oil to produce a graphic novel adaptation of Cutler’s essay, with a planned release date in March 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We know this is ambitious, but we think it’s worth it, and we think our readers will too. You can contribute to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/sfbamo/burrowing-owls-vomiting-anarchists-and-sf-housing&quot;&gt;our Kickstarter&lt;/a&gt; up through January 14th. Artists have bills to pay, as do printers and Post Office employees.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Nothing is free in this life, but right now, we have all have this chance to give the gift of knowledge. That has been our goal since day one.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/in-memoriam-jsun-adrian-mccarty/">
    <title type="text">In Memoriam: Jsun Adrian McCarty</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:b68a8887-5a57-36fb-9b96-528e121c6dc7</id>
    <updated>2016-12-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/in-memoriam-jsun-adrian-mccarty/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Jsun McCarty has been another hard loss for me to process. Out of respect and deference to his family, I refrained from eulogizing him until after his memorial service. And, my goodness, what a memorial service—loved ones from far and wide gathered to spin his favorite records, share stories, and gorge on mac and cheese. Just like Jsun would have wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;(Please consider donating to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youcaring.com/genemccartycolleenmccartyimmediatefamily-719048?fb_action_ids=1693271440914299&amp;amp;fb_action_types=youcaringcom%3Ashare&quot;&gt;this fund&lt;/a&gt; to help his family with travel and other ancillary costs.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Several days after the Ghost Ship tragedy, Jsun appeared in a waking dream to Michael Daddona, his roommate and bandmate of 12 years. He sent his love and regards to everyone, but with one catch: make sure not to misspell his name. It’s Jsun.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Jsun was an artistic genius with the humility to constantly reject such accolades. (I had no idea what a brilliant painter he was until some of his stunning canvasses were displayed at his memorial.) His primary concern was always making sure everyone else was having a good time. Perhaps even more fondly than his performances, I’ll always remember sitting outside with him between acts at various concerts, listening to his stories of driving for six hours from his childhood home in Iowa to see Slayer in Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/in-memoriam-jsun-adrian-mccarty/jsun3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Excerpt from an untitled painting by Jsun McCarty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;He radiated a gentle, gregarious kindness in his personal demeanor, but his musical performances were anything but. Jsun designed all the visual artwork for the three-piece industrial-noise group Styrofoam Sanchez (later dubbed Coral Remains), even authoring a stunning comic book narrating the lyrics of their monumental LP/DVD release, &lt;em&gt;Empire Underwater.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=4123571802/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ratskinrecords.bandcamp.com/album/styrofoam-sanchez-empire-underwater&quot;&gt;STYROFOAM SANCHEZ &amp;quot;Empire Underwater&amp;quot; by Ratskin Records&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/in-memoriam-jsun-adrian-mccarty/jsun4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Untitled drawing by Jsun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A Sanchez performance was not one to be missed. The group was notorious for making a mess in every performance space, mostly from the ritual destruction of the homemade Styrofoam masks covering their faces like a dystopian nuclear fungus. (They were just as notorious for meticulously cleaning up their messes.) When I last saw them, the trio had recruited at least a half-dozen audience members to wear full-bodied Styrofoam suits and mosh aggressively in the crowd, resulting in a furious-yet-mirthful Styrofoam fight.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/in-memoriam-jsun-adrian-mccarty/jsun2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jsun in full Styrofoam Sanchez garb (courtesy: Kevin Brown)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yes, my other fondest memory involves pulling a Styrofoam horn off someone’s face and breaking it over their head, all while Jsun roared unintelligible poetry over distorted drum-machine beats.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;His vision was uncompromising and unrivaled in its depth and detail; his gentle spirit is a constant reminder to embrace our fellow humans ever more earnestly.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We love you, Jsun, and can’t wait to party it up with you in the next realm.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GB19ixZtGhQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover photo by Kevin Brown&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/local-profiles-dorothy-walker-berkeleys-self-taught-planner/">
    <title type="text">Local Profiles: Dorothy Walker, Berkeley's Self-Taught Planner</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:185e8214-2030-3706-b307-412d6e5d73ae</id>
    <updated>2016-12-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/local-profiles-dorothy-walker-berkeleys-self-taught-planner/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Some things never change: for Dorothy Walker, that includes fighting for Berkeley to embrace change. After leading a largely successful city taskforce to desegregate Berkeley’s public schools in the early 1960s, Ms. Walker has hardly rested on her laurels. Instead, she has devoted herself to advocating for a more diverse city overall. The Sisyphean resistance she’s received from the city’s suburban scrooges, even an ostensibly “progressive” coalition originally formed to strengthen tenant protections, would be enough to drive any normal person away.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Not Dorothy Walker. The 86-year-old’s experience also includes chairing the city’s Planning Commission, serving as the founding president of the American Planners Association, and co-founding the local environmental non-profit Livable Berkeley. She remains just as active in her retirement years.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When we met at a local café, I remembered Ms. Walker’s assurance that she’d be easy to recognize—“I’ll be the oldest woman in the room.” As expected, the first woman I approached was not her. Nor the second one.  Finally, she waved me down from a table in the back.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/local-profiles-dorothy-walker-berkeleys-self-taught-planner/dorothy2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dorothy Walker, present-day&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We had initially planned our meeting to discuss a letter to Berkeley’s City Council she had sent in February, in response to a special meeting on housing policy convened by then-Mayor Tom Bates. When the full context of her deeper frustrations set in, our meeting turned into a full-fledged interview.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Walker’s thesis is simple: Berkeley needs more housing. More than that, it needs a significant paradigm shift to address a shortage decades in the making. The City of Berkeley &lt;a href=&quot;http://webserver.ci.berkeley.ca.us/uploadedFiles/Housing/Level_3_-_General/COBHousingElementAdopted12-18-01.pdf&quot;&gt;saw a net gain&lt;/a&gt; of merely 541 housing units between 1980 and 2000. The city even saw a net decrease of units during the 1980s largely due to a loss of secondary units and owner-occupied conversions.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Her letter puts it more diplomatically:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While Berkeley prides itself on being a progressive city, it has continually empowered those whose housing needs have already been met, while making it extremely difficult and expensive to create any new housing, resulting in an increasingly less diverse and more privileged population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Berkeley saw its most dramatic increase in housing construction between 1960 and 1975, largely by apartments replacing single-family homes. To protect more houses from demolition, the city’s voters passed the Neighborhood Preservation Ordinance in 1973, which required a Conditional Use Permit for “absolutely everything,” as Walker puts it. Though initially well-intentioned, Walker describes the Ordinance as an ultimately reactionary policy borne out of an alliance between anti-eviction and rent control advocates with wealthier, landowning “neighborhood preservationists.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The left got in bed with the right, and they’re still together,” Walker says. One can see clear evidence of this in the city’s latest election: newly-elected Mayor Jesse Arreguin, touting the credentials of a “progressive” with a bevy of left-leaning endorsements, was also supported by Shirley Dean, a conservative homeowner from the city’s posh hillside area who presided as mayor over the de facto building moratorium during most of the ‘80s and ‘90s. In her public endorsement, Dean &lt;a href=&quot;http://berkeleydailyplanet.com/issue/2016-10-14/article/45010&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There is no denying we have a need for more housing as well as revenue to help us out of the economic hole that's been growing over the last decade. Solutions aren't easy. However, there is absolutely no need to destroy the community that attracted us to living here in the first place. But given that Berkeley is only about eight square miles and is already the most dense [sic] community in the East Bay, it is essential that we approach development in a thoughtful, managed way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Until this month, the Council held a 6-3 majority of a so-called “moderate,” majority, inverted in this year’s election largely thanks to high-profile progressive endorsements from U.S. Senator Bernie Sanders. Even then, Walker laments, the City Council under Bates made mostly weak, symbolic gestures to address the local and regional housing shortage.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Their meeting ended with them saying, ‘and we have to do this all while protecting the neighborhoods.’ Well, they might as well have cancelled out everything they talked about before,” she says. “You can talk about building near transit all you want, but if you protect some residential neighborhoods from seeing any change, other neighborhoods bear the brunt of it. That is a major equity issue.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ms. Walker’s letter to the council reiterates policy she has been advocating for since the late 1960s: banning single-story commercial buildings and encouraging the construction of a minimum of 4 residential stories atop existing retail. Her letter cites the completion of the North Shattuck Safeway grocery store, and the resistance to dense development around the Ashby BART station, as key examples of Berkeley’s resistance to urban growth.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/local-profiles-dorothy-walker-berkeleys-self-taught-planner/collegeclaremont.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Single-story commercial buildings (and one two-story building) at the intersection of College &amp;amp; Claremont Avenues on the Berkeley/Oakland border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“In the 1960s, you had these Model City programs, designed to empower minorities, especially African-Americans, to take control of their neighborhoods and say what they wanted there,” Walker tells me. (Indeed, Ms. Walker &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2011/03/30/city-council-honors-planning-pioneer-dorothy-walker/&quot;&gt;organized&lt;/a&gt; adamant opposition against plans to tear down Ashby Avenue for a freeway.) “It seems to me that more affluent, white homeowners took ahold of that idea and felt very justified in fighting to preserve what they had.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It was an old pattern she had seen before, during her efforts to draw more inclusive school district boundaries. “What I found was that some people were willing to bus kids around to desegregate schools, but they weren’t willing to desegregate the neighborhoods themselves,” she said. Additionally, she saw many white leftists suddenly sending their children to private schools, “because their curriculums are more progressive, supposedly. But the result was setting desegregation back significantly.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Her next move to desegregate &lt;em&gt;neighborhoods themselves&lt;/em&gt; struck a nerve that is still sensitive today. “When I was on the Planning Commission, I put forward a proposal to rezone the entire city for mixed-use,” she says, briefly beaming before adding: “as you might imagine, that didn’t go over well.” 
While she largely succeeded in redrawing school district boundaries to desegregate the school system, she has not yet succeeded in redrawing the city’s zoning code to desegregate the city itself.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In her letter, Walker adds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Not unlike the now-discredited racial covenants that assured that only white people could live east of Grove Street (now Martin Luther King, Jr. Way), zoning restricted large areas of the City for single family use only—the most expensive kind of housing…Some of the most ardent opponents of new housing live in these protected neighborhoods. They may not be gated, but many of these parts of Berkeley are car-dependent suburban enclaves of increasingly wealthy residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Indeed, not only is Berkeley’s zoning similar to racial covenants; historical evidence shows that the city’s early zoning laws were enacted explicitly for the purposes of racial segregation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In 1916, Berkeley became one of the first cities, along with New York and Los Angeles, to establish a zoning code. It was the first in the country to zone one of its neighborhoods (Elmwood / Claremont in the east) for single-family use. One of the ordinance’s co-authors, Charles H. Cheney, explained its purpose in a letter: single-family zoning “tends to guide and automatically regulate the class of citizens who are settling here,” particularly in order to “prohibit occupation of land by Negroes or Asiatics.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a civic bulletin written the previous year to promote his proposals, Cheney observed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Chinese laundries have always been unwelcome and unprofitable neighbors and the California courts have for many years been dealing with laws against them or restricting them to certain localities…. The location of one laundry near Dwight Way station by permission of the city council a few years ago deteriorated that neighborhood until only negroes and Orientals would rent the nearby buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ms. Walker’s description of zoning as a policy to “increase segregation by exacerbating concentration by affluence” alludes to this dark past without drawing an explicit connection. Instead, it pulls a quiet counterweight to comments from preservationist homeowners bemoaning “greedy developers” and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleydailyplanet.com/issue/2016-06-10/article/44573?headline=Keeping-on-Keepin-On-even-in-the-summertime--Becky-O-Malley&quot;&gt;dismissing new apartments&lt;/a&gt; as being “designed for cramming in as many students who want to party it up without dorm rules as possible.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But even Mayor Arreguin, Walker says, despite being reluctantly branded as a “slow-growth” politician, can’t deny reality. “He fought tooth and nail against the Downtown Plan before it passed in 2010. His &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.greenbelt.org/blog/examiner-com-measure-r-bad-policy-berkeley/&quot;&gt;Measure R in 2014&lt;/a&gt;, co-authored by [now-Councilmember] Sophie Hahn, which would have scrapped much of the downtown plan, lost by over 70%. It lost in every precinct. But then, in his first campaign speech this year, he said he’d preserve the Downtown Plan. So he must know there’s a very clear mandate for the city to grow.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ms. Walker soon hopes to deliver a more refined petition before the new Council urging a greater commitment to mixed-use density.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“They say they’re progressive,” she remarks, “so we need to hold them to it.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/msT23GpsQWU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover photo courtesy of Alan Tobey&lt;/em&gt; / Berkeleyside.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/tweets-from-the-front-affordable-housing-in-forest-hill/">
    <title type="text">Tweets from the Front: Affordable Housing in Forest Hill</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:6764eb3b-ba27-371a-a982-a20db98c5a2d</id>
    <updated>2016-12-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/tweets-from-the-front-affordable-housing-in-forest-hill/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night, local residents met at the Forest Hill Christian Church for an informational session on a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/forest-hill-neighbors-oppose-150-unit-senior-housing-proposal/&quot;&gt;proposed 150-unit apartment building&lt;/a&gt; for low-income seniors. The non-profit developer Christian Church Homes, along with a representative from the mayor's Department of Homelessness &amp;amp; Supportive Services, fielded questions from an often hostile audience over a tense two hours.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Webmaster Sonja Trauss and I reported the meeting live on Twitter, so rather than recap at length, I thought it best to offer highlights from our play-by-play coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Some important fact checks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/11/18/13681294/forest-hill-sf-senior-housing-joe-bravo&quot;&gt;Joe Bravo&lt;/a&gt;, a lawyer and landlord who has &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfgov.org/bdappeal/sites/default/files/Item%204,%20Jurisdiction%20Request%20@%20665%20San%20Jose%20Avenue_2.pdf&quot;&gt;evicted tenants&lt;/a&gt; in the Mission, objected to one comment pointing out the neighborhood's history of discrimination. &quot;Not since the '30s,&quot; he scoffed. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.outsidelands.org/sw5.php&quot;&gt;In 1957&lt;/a&gt;, the iconic baseball player Willie Mays almost had his home purchase revoked in Forest Hill after furious opposition from nearby residents. After racist threats were thrown through their window, Mays and his wife sold their house at 175 Miraloma and returned to New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many neighbors objected to the proposed project being &quot;too tall&quot; and &quot;a giant in the neighborhood.&quot; At six stories, it would be far less of a giant than the ten-story &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.outsidelands.org/sw5.php&quot;&gt;Avalon Sunset Towers&lt;/a&gt; just a few blocks away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;storify&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/forest-hill-neighborhood-meeting-12-15/embed?header=false&amp;template=slideshow&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;750&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/forest-hill-neighborhood-meeting-12-15.js?header=false&amp;template=slideshow&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;noscript&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/forest-hill-neighborhood-meeting-12-15&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;View the story &quot;Forest Hill Neighborhood Meeting 12/15&quot; on Storify&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-real-affordable-housing-activists-dont-oppose-new-housing/">
    <title type="text">Editorial: Real Affordable Housing Activists Don't Oppose New Housing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:4a280e75-2995-3f61-b150-f7a650405114</id>
    <updated>2016-12-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-real-affordable-housing-activists-dont-oppose-new-housing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco’s Council of Community Housing Organizations (CCHO) is against housing, period. That much was made clear when Directors Peter Cohen and Fernando Martí publicly opposed a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.socketsite.com/archives/2016/11/macro-development-of-micro-units-closer-to-reality-in-western-soma.html&quot;&gt;student housing project at 333 12th Street&lt;/a&gt; that invoked California’s State Density Bonus. The project was able to increase the total number of housing units by 35% in exchange for including units price-indexed for Very Low-Income households.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Stated more plainly: self-appointed “affordable housing activists” lobbied for less housing because the balance of income levels living in the building mattered more to them than having more homes, period. They prefer nothing be built rather than anything short of their version of perfection.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;CCHO’s priorities were made even clearer in a recent press release, where Cohen and Martí themselves point out that the net number of Below Market Rate (BMR) units did not change. The organization bemoans that 333 12th Street “added two full floors and 52 additional market-rate units per the state density bonus, [and] effectively reduced the Inclusionary Housing obligation from 18% down to 13%.” Under the original proposal, the project would have included 27 units permanently affordable to Very Low-Income households, out of 148. The project approved by the Planning Commission last week increases the total number to 200, while maintaining 27 units at Below Market Rate prices.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What they fail to mention—but we did mention, because we did our research—was that the project was not required to include any on-site BMR units &lt;em&gt;at all.&lt;/em&gt; So long as the units remain leased to a 501(c)(3) educational non-profit, city law would exempt the developer from any requirement for lower-income housing within the same building. If, however, such a lease were to end, the 18% allotment required by local zoning would be reinstated.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It is a dangerous precedent that takes the City of San Francisco backwards on more than a decade of affordable housing policy,” Cohen writes. Sorry, it is not “dangerous” for a city to finally comply with state law.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We have &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-questioning-priorities-in-the-affordable-housing-community/&quot;&gt;previously criticized&lt;/a&gt; CCHO for stating that their top priority is to tax new development as much as possible to pay for permanently price-indexed dwelling units. They put it in more appealing terms, to “capture the windfall profits resulting from increased land values.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yes, raising the cost of housing for future tenants matters more to the Council of Community Housing Organizations than &lt;em&gt;providing more housing.&lt;/em&gt; Mr. Cohen’s predecessor at CCHO, Calvin Welch, still had the gall to &lt;a href=&quot;http://48hills.org/2016/10/04/obamas-supply-side-toolkit-attacks-local-housing-policy/&quot;&gt;criticize the Obama Administration’s “Housing Toolkit” publication&lt;/a&gt; for neglecting to discuss the paucity of federal subsidies for affordable housing (as though local policy weren’t orthogonal to Congress funding HUD). Why, then, would CCHO not list such policies as their top priority?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/editorial-real-affordable-housing-activists-dont-oppose-new-housing/333cityspaces.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;333 12th Street (source: Panoramic Interests)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Zac Shore, representative of the 333 12th Street developer Panoramic Interests, told us &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lao.ca.gov/reports/2015/finance/housing-costs/housing-costs.aspx&quot;&gt;in an interview&lt;/a&gt; that the State Density Bonus mitigated the financial risk imposed by higher BMR requirements citywide. An &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/san-francisco-approves-200-units-with-state-density-bonus/&quot;&gt;investigation&lt;/a&gt; we conducted earlier this year found fewer units—both at market-rate and below—entering the entitlement process after the passage of Proposition C, which doubled the requirement to 25% of total units.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Greater density makes subsidized housing more feasible, particularly when only the future residents of new development are paying for the subsidy. If this were not the case, Supervisors Peskin and Kim would not have needed to negotiate grandfather clauses for specific projects already underway when crafting their referendum.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;CCHO does not deny that their sole focus is on the &lt;em&gt;percentage&lt;/em&gt; of permanently price-indexed housing built in the city, rather than the total number.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Even that stated intention rests on shaky ground. When San Francisco proposed its own version of the State Density Bonus law, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hoodline.com/2015/11/city-planners-push-plan-for-more-density-affordability-across-sf-neighborhoods&quot;&gt;Affordable Housing Bonus Program&lt;/a&gt; (AHBP), CCHO mounted &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbarf.tumblr.com/post/137295902175/sf-fauxgressives-dont-get-deferred-rewards-or&quot;&gt;vigorous opposition&lt;/a&gt;, despite a &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; allotment of Below Market Rate units than state law or the Western SoMa plan required. Mr. Welch, ever a paragon of self-awareness, &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/01/sf-delays-controversial-housing-law-amidst-opposition-cries-of-ethnic-cleansing/&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; the policy as a form of genocide.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cohen, who, according to public records, recently converted his dwelling unit from a Tenancy-In-Common to a Condominium, would ostensibly feel better about himself if there are more lower-income people filling out income certification paperwork every year. How generous of us to require those holding on to their lottery-allotted housing to continuously prove their poverty. Those caught in the middle, who neither qualify for low-income housing lotteries or are able to afford market prices, are screwed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The crux of the problem is that CCHO fights for higher percentages and lower net unit counts because they believe that market-rate housing is &lt;em&gt;the problem&lt;/em&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;part of&lt;/em&gt; (not the entirety of) the toolkit we need to fix our urban housing crisis. CCHO published these views in their report on “The Filtering Fallacy,” in which they attempt to show that market-rate housing will never meet the city’s raw supply shortage to a degree that would help the most vulnerable in our society. Rather than summarize it, I’ll simply include it below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;embed src=&quot; http://www.sfccho.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/Filtering-Fallacy-Infographic-Final-Web.pdf&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; height=&quot;2100px&quot; /&gt;


    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the worst fallacy is to assume you have found a relevant fallacy at all. CCHO set out to refute a claim that absolutely no one has made: the idea that more market-rate construction &lt;em&gt;alone&lt;/em&gt; will give the Bay Area’s poor and middle-class more options &lt;em&gt;immediately&lt;/em&gt; is, of course, ridiculous. The City Controller recommended an 18% requirement for a reason: it will produce more affordable housing than the current 25%. CCHO does not care to refute this claim; it simply isn’t their top priority.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;However, the opposite scenario is also not true: there is no &lt;em&gt;excess&lt;/em&gt; of private development cushioning the nouveau-riche while actively pricing everyone else out.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;You, reader, can do the homework on this. I’m exhausted, and don’t want to argue with you time and time again. That’s something the folks at CCHO would do. You can read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lao.ca.gov/reports/2015/finance/housing-costs/housing-costs.aspx&quot;&gt;various&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lao.ca.gov/Publications/Report/3470&quot;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt;from the Legislative Analyst’s Office, or not. You, like CCHO, have the freedom to ignore information at your will.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At the very least, perhaps consider the counterfactual: if there were more than enough supply of market-rate development, we would see the city’s vacancy rate rise before rents showed any change. San Francisco’s vacancy rate is at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.deptofnumbers.com/rent/california/san-francisco/#vacancy_rate&quot;&gt;a historic low&lt;/a&gt; of 2.68%, less than half of the national average.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;If fewer people were clamoring to bid on a place to rest their weary head, you would expect to see more vacant units waiting on the market for a bidder. Vexingly, people still want to live in the city. (I live in the East Bay, the better part of the bay, so personally, I don’t get it—but who am I to judge?)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Of course, the regional and statewide shortage of urban housing seems beyond dire. How can we imagine it ever getting better? Well, it might help if CCHO did not continue to actively participate in slowing down the process they then criticize as being too slow to help anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Here, I contend, is where the so-called “activist” establishment must bring their priorities in line with generations who will have to live with the consequences of their policies for far longer. Misanthropy will never make any city more livable.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/east-bay-bbq-joint-will-raise-funds-for-warehouse-fire-safety/">
    <title type="text">East Bay Barbecue Restaurant Will Raise Funds for Warehouse Fire Safety</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:1037a34f-eeda-37e0-b912-9d491d39796a</id>
    <updated>2016-12-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/east-bay-bbq-joint-will-raise-funds-for-warehouse-fire-safety/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Dorothy King has been homeless. She has lived in warehouses. Today, she runs her family business and wants her community to be safe.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;These noble intentions were misunderstood last week after the owner of Everett &amp;amp; Jones Barbecue held a &lt;a href=&quot;http://sanfrancisco.cbslocal.com/2016/12/06/everett-jones-owner-says-oakland-venue-next-to-restaurant-poses-hazard-like-ghost-ship/&quot;&gt;press conference&lt;/a&gt; warning officials over potential fire hazards at the illegal live/work artist warehouse next door, known as the Salt Lick Collective. In the wake of the tragic Ghost Ship fire, with Oakland’s arts community reeling from grief and shock, King’s announcement was met with furious backlash.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This morning, local artists and restauranteurs stood together at a press conference at the Everett &amp;amp; Jones location in Jack London Square to announce their newfound unity. On Saturday, Everett &amp;amp; Jones will host a catered &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/1729224307396666/&quot;&gt;benefit concert&lt;/a&gt; to raise funds for fire safety upgrades, in an effort to prevent displacement throughout Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Some panelists were on the verge of tears as they described the slew of racist emails the restaurant received, which eventually brought the neighbors to meet and collaborate. Nina Moore, Mrs. King’s daughter, explained that the trauma of reading those racial slurs reminded her of the presidential election, and made her feel that Oakland was no longer a safe haven from bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Uncle Bobby” Johnson, the uncle of Oscar Grant, told the audience how he remained steadfast in the face of negative comments after his nephew was murdered by BART Police.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Those divisive comments… they didn’t work,” he declared. “Look at this table now. They brought unity.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/east-bay-bbq-joint-will-raise-funds-for-warehouse-fire-safety/ej2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oakland resident and Salt Lick resident Sam Lefebvre discusses displacement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We realized we had the same goals,” said Sam Lefebvre, a journalist and artist who lives at the Salt Lick. “Housing people safely.”  Lefebvre worked with Everett &amp;amp; Jones to book the concert, and is working with volunteer contractor Ken Houston of the East Oakland Beautification Committee to upgrade his home.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Before Mrs. King arrived, Houston had stood in front of news cameras with Councilmember Noel Gallo, whose district encompasses the former Ghost Ship warehouse. “I don’t care if you’ve lived here your whole life or you just moved here,” he said. “If you’re in Oakland, you’re an Oaklander. Stand up for your city.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Displacement has been a decades-long process in Oakland,” Lefebvre later said. “One that has disproportionately impacted People of Color. No discussion of artists here today can leave that out.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;During her speech, Mrs. King brandished a large, translucent plastic key, a ceremonial “key to the city” given to her by former Mayor Jean Quan. “At first, I thought this key opened nothing. Now this key will open the door to affordable housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Local artist BG Anaraki, who had engaged in a shouting match with Ms. Moore at the previous press conference, held hands with King and Moore as he described “the most beautiful experience of my life” when meeting with the owners. The neighbors quite literally broke bread with each other to settle tensions and plan a common path forward.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/east-bay-bbq-joint-will-raise-funds-for-warehouse-fire-safety/ej3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oakland artist BG Anaraki reads the names of the 36 who perished in the Ghost Ship fire&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“When Mrs. King held me as I cried, my tears were not only for my friends—they were tears of joy,” Anaraki said.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Anaraki also urged the audience to consider the Ghost Ship tragedy’s impact on individual mental health. “To all my friends out there, if you see me, don’t tell me you saw me on TV. Instead, ask me if I’ve taken my pills that day. I’m not good at remembering…Reach out to your friends on medication, and ask their consent to bring up the same question.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“BG, I’m so proud of you,” Ms. Moore said as the press conference neared its end. She gripped his outstretched hand, a solemn Mrs. King between them. “Whenever you need me—I’m here for you, to take that call.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/east-bay-bbq-joint-will-raise-funds-for-warehouse-fire-safety/ejflyer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Anaraki will be performing at the restaurant on Saturday as Braingoat. He will be joined by hardcore punk band No Babies, noise-rock group Ugly, the free-jazz duo Black Spirituals, and local soul singer Dyson. The following day, Everett &amp;amp; Jones will hold a vigil for the victims of the Ghost Ship fire, evoking the city’s former motto: &lt;em&gt;Love Life.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-approves-temporary-moratorium-on-sro-conversions/">
    <title type="text">Oakland Approves Temporary Moratorium on SRO Conversions</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:5a0c5167-5871-3e94-8eb9-71ad3ad476d1</id>
    <updated>2016-12-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-approves-temporary-moratorium-on-sro-conversions/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;By a unanimous vote last night, Oakland’s City Council passed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://oakland.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?ID=2896460&amp;amp;GUID=86EECCD2-2A43-4DCC-8EC3-C685F8219879&amp;amp;Options=&amp;amp;Search=&quot;&gt;45-day moratorium&lt;/a&gt; on the conversion of Single Room Occupancy hotels (SROs) into other uses.  Council chambers were flooded with supporters of the legislation during the special meeting, with many items pertaining to the December 2nd warehouse fire that claimed 36 lives. City Council also renewed the citywide state of emergency declared after the fire.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The emergency ordinance, introduced by Council President Lynette Gibson McElhaney, will be reviewed when the council returns from recess in January. Councilmember-At-Large Rebecca Kaplan further added that she planned to introduce legislation to protect tenants in illegal live/work spaces similar to the Ghost Ship after the recess.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;SROs, a common form of low-rent housing sought by many either homeless and housing-insecure residents, have been the center of local controversy as Oakland’s rents continue to skyrocket. Having lost nearly half of its SRO units since 2004, the city has seen a particular focus on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/last-days-at-downtown-oaklands-hotel-travelers/Content?oid=4799815&quot;&gt;Hotel Travelers&lt;/a&gt;, a downtown SRO building whose new ownership appears to be eager to evict long-term tenants in favor of more profitable ventures.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Danny Haber has earned notoriety with his holding company The Negev, which recently purchased Hotel Travelers, for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.antievictionmap.com/danny-haber-and-alon-gutman/&quot;&gt;evicting low-income tenants&lt;/a&gt; in many properties on both sides of the bay. Orlando Chavez, a resident of the Travelers, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DarwinBondGraha/status/808894790024777730&quot;&gt;testified&lt;/a&gt; that most tenants had already been driven out by harassment.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many speakers at the meeting supported extending SRO protection for an even longer period of time. “SROs are the last line of defense against homelessness,” one woman said. “I want to express my support for this measure and point out that the decrease in SROs corresponds to the increase in homelessness nationally.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;James Vann, representing the Oakland Tenants Union, testified that his group supported the ordinance. Further, he added, “Relocation payments should be made to any people who are found to have to move after they've become permanent residents.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“A city is a place of people all living together in different classes. A suburb is where only people of one class live,” said Judy Elkan of the Mary Weather Gallery. “Oakland is a city; we should be an example to the world of how to stop homelessness.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The most direct appeal of the night came from another man who identified himself as a current resident of a local SRO: “SROs are a fantastic place to live if they're managed well.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For the next 45 days, the city of Oakland categorically agrees with his statement.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/farrells-internet-bill-may-bring-faster-cheaper-broadband-but-also-lawsuits/">
    <title type="text">Farrell's Internet Bill May Bring Faster, Cheaper Broadband (But Also Lawsuits)</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:e50e47c9-6524-34f7-b6c1-dc83a5eb7964</id>
    <updated>2016-12-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/farrells-internet-bill-may-bring-faster-cheaper-broadband-but-also-lawsuits/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;You read this morning’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-poor-housing-and-lackluster-broadband-access-in-san-francisco/&quot;&gt;op-ed&lt;/a&gt; by our webmaster Sonja Trauss. Now for the story:&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Mark Farrell will finalize legislation at today’s Board of Supervisors meeting to mandate equal access for San Francisco tenants to all Internet Service Providers (ISPs) in the area. Farrell’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://sfgov.legistar.com/View.ashx?M=F&amp;amp;ID=4834773&amp;amp;GUID=0DCCBCFF-6110-4276-B446-D4A990723825&quot;&gt;ordinance&lt;/a&gt;, an amendment to the Police Code banning favorable financial agreements between major providers and landlords, was approved by the Board’s Budget and Finance Committee last month, and will now receive its second reading before the full Board.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The ordinance will ban “exclusive access agreements” in which a property owner can arrange with an ISP to offer access to a single service, which the city hopes will enable tenants to choose their broadband connection as freely as property owners themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Critically, the bill's opening salvo reads: “No property owner shall interfere with the right of an occupant to obtain communications services from the communications services provider of the occupant's choice.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Fair market prices for internet access sounds like a no-brainer for such a tech-centric city as San Francisco, but the Supervisors are steeling themselves against much expected blowback. Today’s meeting will be preceded by a closed session with the City Attorney to discuss “anticipated litigation” in response to Farrell’s proposal, widely expected to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;These concerns are not without precedent. For example, Comcast has sued the cities of &lt;a href=&quot;http://arstechnica.com/business/2015/04/comcast-brings-fiber-to-city-that-it-sued-7-years-ago-to-stop-fiber-rollout/&quot;&gt;Chattanooga&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20161026/07362935891/comcast-joins-att-files-lawsuit-against-nashville-to-slow-google-fiber.shtml&quot;&gt;Nashville&lt;/a&gt; in Tennessee to halt the construction of Google  Fiber infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We always like things that encourage competition in this market. This industry has suffered greatly due to monopolies,” said Anders Finn, Director of Technology at the local ISP &lt;a href=&quot;http://monkeybrains.net&quot;&gt;monkeybrains.net&lt;/a&gt;. “Now, I’ve seen some things in this bill that are going to force property owners to pay for upgrades, which I don’t think is completely fair. There’s a lot more market choice for the city’s more affluent residents, so in lower-income areas, we need to see more of a push for better internet.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Finn noted that Monkeybrains is working to install inexpensive broadband services in every unit at Hunters Point East/West, an apartment complex on Oakdale Avenue in the Bayview neighborhood, and that such projects would not be hindered by Farrell’s legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We’d like to see some of the onus to provide higher speeds and lower prices to be on the ISP, not entirely on property owners,” Finn continued. “Say you have a building from the 1920s with old wiring, and suddenly you find out you’re required to install Google Fiber and eat the cost. There are better ways to make that happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The ordinance’s latest amendments appear to have been adjusted to meet these concerns, at least for landlords in multi-unit buildings. Although a property owner is required by Farrell’s bill to notify the ISP if the building lacks the necessary utilities and infrastructure to accommodate upgrades, Section 5208 adds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A property owner is entitled to just and reasonable compensation from a communications services provider that obtains access to a multiple occupancy building from a property owner…to provide communications services to occupants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Just and reasonable compensation” is defined as the “fair market value” of the impact work would have on a building.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though lawsuits may ultimately be unlikely from larger landlords, ISPs could conceivably find themselves sharing grievances with property owners who rent out a room in a single-family home, or may not otherwise qualify for just compensation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-poor-housing-and-lackluster-broadband-access-in-san-francisco/">
    <title type="text">Op-Ed: Poor Housing and Lackluster Broadband Access in San Francisco</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:194b90dd-411b-3646-ae4d-1a0ebe02f80a</id>
    <updated>2016-12-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-poor-housing-and-lackluster-broadband-access-in-san-francisco/" />
    <author>
      <name>Sonja Trauss</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to believe that San Francisco, a city home to a large portion of the Internet, has residents suffering from a lack of quality broadband access— but its does. We live in a state with almost 200 different internet service providers, yet of the 40% of San Franciscans living in apartment buildings or condominiums, only &lt;a href=&quot;http://broadbandnow.com/California/San-Francisco&quot;&gt;3% have access to the fastest broadband technology available&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many landlords and building owners get kickbacks in exchange for steering their tenants to big broadband providers or setting up exclusive contracts with those providers. Effectively, they get to cash in on limiting broadband choices while tenants pay the price. Fewer choices, and the resulting drop in service quality, mean that tenants are left to shell out more money for slower Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Here at the San Francisco Bay Area Renters’ Federation (SFBARF), we find that alarming. The status quo of limited broadband choice benefits landlords, property managers and ISPs, and hurts tenants.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Opponents of the bill claim it is unnecessary, tenants should shop for apartments with an eye towards leases that allow tenants free choice of broadband provider. “We don’t need laws telling us we have to allow any company into our buildings. We have concerns about safety, about the physical space,” said Ken Cleaveland, vice president of public policy for the Building Owners and Managers Association of San Francisco. “We think everything should be dictated by leases — you write what kind of services you provide into the lease.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Of course that is nonsense. Tenants in San Francisco are shopping for apartments with an eye toward affordability, and are in no position currently to be able to bargain with their potential landlords over choice of internet service providers.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Today, December 13th, the San Francisco Board of Supervisors is considering an ordinance by Supervisor Mark Farrell that would make it easier for new ISPs to expand their services in residential buildings, helping spur competition in the broadband market to increase access and reduce prices.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://sfgov.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?ID=2863893&amp;amp;GUID=E010FDC6-4024-4BA7-B282-C0F9DE32D9F4&amp;amp;Options=ID%7cText%7c&amp;amp;Search=&quot;&gt;“Choice of Communications Services Providers in Multiple Occupancy Buildings”&lt;/a&gt; ordinance would ban kickbacks from large ISPs to landlords and property owners, and would help promote the competition necessary for an equitable market and fair prices. The ordinance works for residents and for business—leveling barriers of entry for new ISPs and encouraging all providers to offer fair prices for faster, available internet.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It’s time for a change. Tell your Supervisor to vote “yes” on broadband choice by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.votervoice.net/Engine/campaigns/48219/respond&quot;&gt;signing the petition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sonja Trauss is the Founder of the SF Bay Area Renters' Federation and webmaster for the&lt;/em&gt; Metro Observer.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/in-memoriam-micah-danemayer/">
    <title type="text">In Memoriam: Micah Danemayer</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:6005b4b9-2719-3139-a8dd-fa6503be4cf2</id>
    <updated>2016-12-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/in-memoriam-micah-danemayer/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Micah Danemayer, 28, channeled a life force that even death could not extinguish. Indeed, the Ghost Ship tragedy that claimed his terrestrial existence along with 35 others seems to only have brought me closer to the community Micah himself introduced me to, just a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Micah was one of the first people to introduce themselves to me after I moved to the East Bay in 2014 and started attending local concerts. Between acts at the closing party for Downtown Oakland’s Moco Gallery, Micah simply passed me his bottle of bourbon and started talking to me about music, as though we’d known each other for decades. The feeling persisted, even after his passing, when he appeared to me in a dream this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Micah,” I said, “there are tributes to you all over town. So many good shows—I wish you could be there, man!”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Micah smiled and responded in his habitually cheeky way, sticking his tongue out and flashing the devil-horns hand gesture, shouting &lt;em&gt;slayyy it duder!&lt;/em&gt; I woke from my dream with the image of him smiling and winking, very much in the style of his idol, David Bowie.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At the Ghost Ship, Micah was manning the projector during various performances, conjuring masterful avant-garde splashes of light and color under the moniker Visual Aids, just as he had been last year, during my only visit to the ill-fated venue. I feel immensely fortunate to have experienced his multisensory art firsthand.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It’s impossible to overstate what a pillar Micah was in the local arts community. Last performing under the name &lt;a href=&quot;https://discardedrecords.bandcamp.com/album/paralycyst-damage-done-discarded-007&quot;&gt;Paralycyst&lt;/a&gt;, he combined a penchant for densely-textured industrial sounds with an unabashed love of pure, decadent acid techno. &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/redcellaroakland&quot;&gt;Red Cellar&lt;/a&gt;, his new duo with another local techno master &lt;a href=&quot;https://discardedrecords.bandcamp.com/album/regretamine-headcave-microrave-006&quot;&gt;Regretamine&lt;/a&gt;, was slated to make its live debut next month at Obscura Machina, Micah’s monthly series of curated “micro-rave” concerts. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/1150785288339183/&quot;&gt;The show will go on&lt;/a&gt; in his honor.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Micah’s personal warmth and open heart brought him to introduce me to many other heroes in the Bay Area’s incendiary techno scene including &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/countervulture&quot;&gt;Countervulture&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://discardedrecords.bandcamp.com/album/type-b-discarded-008&quot;&gt;Type B&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://discardedrecords.bandcamp.com/album/forbidden-colors-discarded-004&quot;&gt;Forbidden Colors&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/heartworm&quot;&gt;Heartworm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/hom&quot;&gt;HOM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/404-not-found-4&quot;&gt;404 Not Found&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://discardedrecords.bandcamp.com/album/bonus-beast-discarded-005&quot;&gt;Bonus Beast&lt;/a&gt;, to name but a few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/277770433&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/291549147&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;He was the glue that held us together and continues to inspire us. We love you, Micah.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-francisco-approves-200-units-with-state-density-bonus/">
    <title type="text">San Francisco Approves 200 Units with State Density Bonus</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:87cf3fe1-4905-36a9-a8de-796815141ab6</id>
    <updated>2016-12-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-francisco-approves-200-units-with-state-density-bonus/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a landmark decision last Thursday, the San Francisco Planning Commission voted 5-1 to approve a project with 200 dwelling units at 333 12th Street in the South of Market (SoMa) District. Spearheaded by local developer Panoramic Interests, the project makes local history by being the first development in San Francisco to invoke the State Density Bonus law to add more units to the project.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Dubbed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panoramic.com/cityspaces-location/cityspaces-333-12th-st/&quot;&gt;“CitySpaces 333,”&lt;/a&gt; the eight-story building will contain 200 “micro-unit” apartments, some with up to four bedrooms, with bike storage and two car-sharing spots instead of private parking.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Initially planned solely for student housing, the project would have qualified under the city’s Student Housing Ordinance exempting the developer from including any on-site Below Market Rate (BMR) units. San Francisco recently raised those requirements to 25% BMR for new rental housing under June’s Proposition C, though CitySpaces 333 was grandfathered in under earlier, lower requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It’s a huge step forward,” said Zac Shore of Panoramic Interests. “The State Density Bonus dovetails nicely with our student housing application, enabling us to keep the subsidized units on-site while building 52 additional units of much needed student housing for nonprofit schools.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;CitySpaces 333 qualified for a 35% increase in density in exchange for providing 11% of its units—16 total—at rents permanently affordable to Very Low-Income households, defined as earning up to 50% of the Area Median Income. Should Panoramic end a leasing agreement with a 501(c)(3) educational nonprofit, the building would be required to provide an additional 7% BMR under the Western SoMa neighborhood plan.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In other words, this landmark project will combine student dormitories with subsidized housing for any low-income household that completes the lottery application process through the Mayor’s Office of Housing. Should the project cease to include dorms, more subsidized housing will take their place.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Shore also noted that the two additional floors would change the construction from a wood-frame building  to concrete. “The additional units granted under the state density bonus allow us to make that construction cost increase work financially, while keeping the subsidized units on site,” he said. “The state density bonus seems to be one of the only ways to work with the inclusionary housing requirements brought on by Prop C.” (Earlier this year, a &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/&quot;&gt;investigation&lt;/a&gt; found that fewer residential units had been proposed after the passage of Proposition C.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The state density bonus has been a hot-button issue in San Francisco politics: up throughout this year,  legislators and stakeholders were bitterly divided over the proposed &lt;a href=&quot;http://hoodline.com/2016/06/votes-on-dueling-plans-reveal-what-sf-supervisors-really-believe-about-housing-solutions&quot;&gt;Affordable Housing Bonus Program (AHBP)&lt;/a&gt;, a local implementation of the state density bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Planning Commissioner Dennis Richards voted in favor of the project, but also stated in an interview that he was open-minded to the opponents’ concerns that the density bonus did not adequately maximize affordability. “What we have is a policy issue, and you don’t evaluate policy over a specific project—you make policy to apply to many projects. So I think they got that backwards,” he said. “Now, what do you do to get the maximum number of affordable units you can? That’s what we have to figure out. That’s the policy issue.” Aside from their deliberations on specific projects, Commissioner Richards noted that the Planning Commission is able to send communications to the Board of Supervisors urging any number of policy reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The developer has the law on their side,” Richards added. “We sat there with the seven pages of the law printed out in front of us.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In late September, Governor Jerry Brown approved &lt;a href=&quot;https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billHistoryClient.xhtml?bill_id=201520160AB2501&quot;&gt;AB 2501&lt;/a&gt; a bill proposed by State Assemblymember Richard Bloom (Santa Monica) requiring local municipalities to enact their own standards of compliance to the State Density Bonus. In part, the bill reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&quot;All cities, counties, or cities and counties shall adopt an ordinance that specifies how compliance with this section will be implemented. Failure to adopt an ordinance shall not relieve a city, county, or city and county from complying with this section.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;… &quot;A local government shall not condition the submission, review, or approval of an application pursuant to this chapter on the preparation of an additional report or study that is not otherwise required by state law, including this section.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/in-loving-memory/">
    <title type="text">In Loving Memory</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:018dd771-7335-3a2f-8e74-2e1741b0f53f</id>
    <updated>2016-12-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/in-loving-memory/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Please donate to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youcaring.com/firevictimsofoaklandfiredec232016-706684&quot;&gt;relief fund&lt;/a&gt; for victims of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbaytimes.com/2016/12/03/oakland-massive-fire-at-live-work-space-in-fruitvale-district/&quot;&gt;Ghost Ship&lt;/a&gt; fire in Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Words cannot describe the devastation we feel at the loss of many beloved friends. I personally have lost heroes, mentors, incomparable kindred spirits. While I will remain offline for a few days to process this grief, readers should be aware of many &lt;a href=&quot;https://helpghostship.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;relief efforts&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/1200018936718540/&quot;&gt;benefit concerts&lt;/a&gt;, and other &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/174030323063264/&quot;&gt;fundraisers&lt;/a&gt; to aid those affected and, hopefully, prevent future tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On behalf of those who didn't, we owe it to each other to rise from the ashes. We need each other now more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/planning-commission-approves-senior-housing-in-mission-district/">
    <title type="text">Planning Commission Approves Senior Housing in Mission District</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:20e138a5-2410-3804-9f6a-0bd80a9a09e1</id>
    <updated>2016-12-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/planning-commission-approves-senior-housing-in-mission-district/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After a marathon hearing at the San Francisco Planning Commission, the 9-story apartment project proposed at 1296 Shotwell Street for low-income seniors in the Mission District received its permit approvals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The non-profit developers building the 94-unit project, the Mission Economic Development Agency (MEDA) and the Chinatown Community Development Center, have held community meetings for &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/05/neighbors-of-mission-district-affordable-housing-cry-too-tall/&quot;&gt;over six months&lt;/a&gt; to interface with concerned neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Units in the building will be reserved for senior citizens early 50% of the Area Median Income, with one-fifth further earmarked for formerly homeless seniors.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Craig Weber, an accountant and nearby landlord, objected to the total lack of parking and increased density on a residential street. Weber’s mother, Connie Weber, was the only other speaker testifying against the project. “We have enough big buildings,” she said, adding that she had lived on Shotwell Street for 85 years.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sam Moss, director of the Mission Housing Development Company, testified in response to fears that parking was a serious issue. “We know senior projects work well without parking,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Many local Mission District activists, noted in &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/12/senior-housing-on-shotwell-brings-foes-together/&quot;&gt;Mission Local&lt;/a&gt; as more frequently mobilizing to speak against market-rate developments, rallied to support the development. A variety of elderly Latino residents gave supporting testimony in Spanish, through an interpreter. San Francisco, one speaker insisted, “a beautiful city if it had buildings for all these people.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Laura Clark, founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.growsanfrancisco.org/&quot;&gt;Grow San Francisco&lt;/a&gt;, was pleased with the outcome, but qualified her optimism: “If a perfect project like this, that everyone loves, with 100% affordable housing, still has to go through a five-hour hearing like this and face neighborhood opposition, what hope do we have of fixing the city’s raw housing shortage? I hope this sends a clear message that everyone stands to benefit from serious process reform.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/">
    <title type="text">Editorial: Prop 13, or, California's Progressive Blindspot Illuminated</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:b8a7955f-e081-3b8c-bcf0-7596f08a8da4</id>
    <updated>2016-12-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In 1979, California voters passed Proposition 13. This locked in property tax rates at a maximum rate of 1% of its assessed value, which can change at most 2% per year. Most voters (in the counties labeled green above) hoped to protect homeowners from the market volatility of their own equity values, preventing foreclosures that could occur if tax assessments became more than their incomes could bear. Sounds good, right?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, the ballot measure legislated a de facto caste system benefiting legacy landowners. Ralph McLaughlin, Chief Economist at the real estate website Trulia has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trulia.com/blog/trends/prop-13/&quot;&gt;recently published data to illustrate this&lt;/a&gt;: by comparing current assessments to market values, McLaughlin calculated “effective” property tax rates, essentially the difference between what an established owner pays, and what a new buyer would pay today.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Revolt” sounds too noble to me, even “populist.” I prefer to call it feudalism.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/prop13fig2lao.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: Legislative Analyst's Office)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Prop 13 had further consequences: tax rates could only be reassessed upon sale of the property, whereas before, homes could be reassessed if anyone in the neighborhood sold for a higher price. Additionally, taxes in general became much more difficult to change. The state of California controls all property tax policy, and can only raise taxes with a 2/3 vote from the legislature. Municipalities could only introduce new taxes by referendum, also with a 2/3 margin if they intend to spend revenue for a specific purpose. Schools, infrastructure, and all sorts of public services have since relied on much less stable revenue streams, namely income and sales taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Like most policies enacted in response to fear, Prop 13 has demonstrably done more harm than good. The Legislative Analyst’s Office &lt;a href=&quot;http://lao.ca.gov/Publications/Report/3497&quot;&gt;also reported&lt;/a&gt; what everyone has known for years: the tax burden has inordinately shifted to newer residents. Even within the same neighborhood, owners pay wildly diverging tax rates.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;More damningly, McLaughlin reports: “In 2015 alone, California homeowners received over $12.5 billion in savings from Prop 13, while local governments lost that same amount.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/prop13fig4lao.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: LAO)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, since higher-earning households are more likely to own higher-value properties, the tax break inordinately benefits the wealthiest Californians. Palo Alto, one of the state’s most expensive towns, has the lowest effective rate. Mercifully, Palo Altans do not live in fear of underwater equity.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lucky children who inherit valuable property also inherit their parent’s Prop 13-based tax assessments. Not only does the policy establish a sort of feudalism via subsidy, it also encourages the consolidation of dynastic wealth. New, young computer programmers with six-figure salaries may easy to scapegoat as the emblem of the Bay Area’s 21st Century inequality, but even if they can afford real estate, their privilege is chump change compared to that of pre-1979 homebuyers and their descendants.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/prop13_supportinggraphic_v07-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: Trulia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, renters &lt;em&gt;qua&lt;/em&gt; renters do not get tax benefits for renting a place to sleep, only a place to work. While the state codified price controls for property owners, many renters were stripped of similar protections in 1995 when the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/its-time-to-overturn-the-state-ban-on-rent-control/Content?oid=4229744&quot;&gt;Costa Hawkins Act&lt;/a&gt; banned rent control in dwelling units built after 1977.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Let’s be clear: if your landlord raises your rent, and they’ve owned the building since before either tech boom, they are literally the landed gentry profiting off your serfdom. If that rent increase isn’t limited by rent control, you are being denied a privilege your landlord enjoys.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;You may assume that given this bleak picture, California lawmakers must be scrambling to make fundamental changes to the state’s tax structure, and you would not be wholly incorrect. State Senator Loni Hancock (SD09) has recently proposed a “split-roll” tax reform, which would gradually decouple Prop 13 caps on commercial real estate from those on residential property.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Split-roll reform has its own problems. Skeptics fear that only assessing commercial property at market rates would exacerbate imbalances between jobs and housing by further incentivizing commercial development over residential. But the logic in support is that it’s fairer to raise taxes on Disneyland than grandmothers living on Social Security checks. The cynical logic is that it’s the only politically palatable reform—but even current Governor Jerry Brown has said he won’t touch it.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Before you close out of this article and curse Jerry’s obstinate, some would say overzealous pragmatism, let’s take a look at where the conversation on housing costs &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; gone. Like a feeble stream trickling through a rocky mountainside, the “third rail” of Prop 13 reform keeps the debate over housing reforms locked into tragicomic and ineffective limits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco projects a culture that is, shall we say, not fond of capitalism, and the so-called “progressive” faction has seized on this image, while the ostensible “moderates” remain largely agnostic, or at least anemic. The progressive faction’s rhetorically compassionate, class-warrior-tinged proposals to solve the region’s crippling housing crisis tend to follow this basic narrative:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yes, there is a shortage of housing supply. Yes, more must be built. But without strong protections for incumbent residents, and aggressive price controls to protect everyone without exorbitant incomes, all new privately financed market-rate development must be treated as guilty before proven innocent. New construction, lacking drastic state-wide rent control reform and ever-higher ratios of Below Market Rate units, will be guilty of gentrification and displacement. A shiny new mid-rise in the Mission District will not only fail to fully alleviate a supply shortage on its own, it will also raise median rents in the area such that vulnerable lower-income residents will be forced out. New development is bad until proven good. We need more housing, but let’s not be careless here.*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Reasonable enough, no? No.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I’ll point to the more obvious holes first. Most demand for new construction has concentrated in the Mission District because San Francisco has lower-density zoning in wealthier neighborhoods once explicitly segregated for “whites-only.” When activists rally to protect the Mission, the elephant in the room is that nobody is wringing their hands about gentrification in North Beach, Pac Heights, Bernal Heights, Russian Hill, Forest Hill, and so on—because those neighborhoods &lt;em&gt;are already rich&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;they will be fine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Marina Dwellers will be fine. Telegraph Hill Dwellers will be fine. Developers are not frothing at the mouth to build tall residences all over there for the influx of new workers coming to the city, except, notably, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/designs-released-for-affordable-housing-in-telegraph-hill/&quot;&gt;some low- and middle-income housing planned near the port&lt;/a&gt;. They should be.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In my paraphrase above, did you notice something missing? I used the term “Below Market Rate” (BMR) for what is often called “affordable housing,” but I did not use the term “subsidy.” This is because inclusionary zoning requirements do not provide price-indexed dwelling units with public money. Private development pays for it with a cut on investment returns—a cut that is passed on to market-rate renters.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;How curious, then, that the proposed “progressive” solutions to our housing affordability crisis contain many caveats that may end up being &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/&quot;&gt;a detriment&lt;/a&gt; to longer-term affordability goals. In the context of Proposition 13, this is relevant because inclusionary zoning (or fees paid “in-lieu” of “affordable” units) are a tax, but are much easier to codify, because they are not called a tax. Affordable housing is largely not funded by actual taxes because the vast majority of real estate equity gains are left untouched.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I’m going to shoot the messengers now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Aaron Peskin, who &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/Prop-C-would-raise-new-housing-s-below-market-7388907.php&quot;&gt;coauthored&lt;/a&gt; the new 25% Below Market Rate requirements and &lt;a href=&quot;http://hoodline.com/2015/04/major-8-washington-opponent-backs-peskin-s-d3-supervisor-bid&quot;&gt;opposed development on the city’s waterfront&lt;/a&gt;, was given a duplex in Telegraph Hill by his parents, purchased for $800,000, which was since converted to a single-family residence. Sale prices in that neighborhood often hit the $2 million mark now, but Peskin pays taxes on an assessed value of $1 million. Though also a realtor and landlord, Peskin magnanimously lacks a profit-seeking talent, at least in his role as a public official. During negotiations to sell city-owned real estate, Peskin demanded $7 million higher than the highest bid of $80 million, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/aaron-peskins-art-of-no-deal/&quot;&gt;the deal fell through&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Dean Preston, a tenant defense attorney, recently ran an unsuccessful campaign to replace London Breed as Supervisor for District 5. He has regularly called for restricting density along the transit-rich corridor of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?hl=en&amp;amp;q=http://hoodline.com/2015/10/affordable-divis-group-defines-goals&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1480730509962000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNFPhv5XnzAFsiATQ0Bbfi3dxPfUbQ&quot;&gt;Divisadero Street&lt;/a&gt;, building less housing at the site of a former gas station, and has often &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/London-Breed-Dean-Preston-argue-personal-9283790.php&quot;&gt;condescended&lt;/a&gt; to Breed, a lifelong renter, during the campaign. Preston has admirably called for &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@DeanPreston/rent-control-for-midtown-2dfc435b971c#.db8z27fye&quot;&gt;expanded rent control&lt;/a&gt;, which is particularly admirable given the price controls he enjoys. About that: his home on Alamo Square, purchased by his wife’s parents, is assessed at just under $1.2 million. Homes around Alamo Square regularly fetch between $2-2.5 million sale prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Calvin Welch, who sits on the board of the Haight-Ashbury Neighborhood Council (HANC), recently described the Affordable Housing Bonus Program (AHBP), a density bonus allowing additional floors in new buildings in exchange for higher BMR percentages, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/01/sf-delays-controversial-housing-law-amidst-opposition-cries-of-ethnic-cleansing/&quot;&gt;“ethnic cleansing.”&lt;/a&gt; For &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/video-san-franciscos-pony-tailed-godfather-of-white-paternalism/&quot;&gt;a variety of reasons&lt;/a&gt;, he has been called the “godfather of white paternalism in San Francisco”—for example, after dismissing homeownership as a “bankrupt dream” in the early 1970s, he bought a duplex in the Haight. Its net taxable value hovers around $65,000 in a neighborhood with a median home price of $1.3 million (and that’s for single-family residences).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Zelda Bronstein, an allegedly socialist firebrand, has written at length about &lt;a href=&quot;http://48hills.org/2016/11/28/17209/&quot;&gt;the indignation&lt;/a&gt; she feels about San Francisco’s projected population growth reaching 1 million people without anyone personally requesting her permission. She pays property taxes on an assessed value of $467,790 in a neighborhood where homes regularly fetch $1 million. Her most lauded accomplishment as chair of Berkeley’s Planning Commission is the approval of a park across the street from her house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Becky O’Malley, editor of the &lt;em&gt;Berkeley Daily Planet&lt;/em&gt;, is fond of writing screeds against new development and newer, younger residents in Berkeley. In one editorial, she &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleydailyplanet.com/issue/2016-06-10/article/44573?headline=Keeping-on-Keepin-On-even-in-the-summertime--Becky-O-Malley&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; a planned 7-story apartment building near the UC Berkeley campus as “the kind designed for cramming in as many students who want to party it up without dorm rules as possible.” (The project will be replacing a 2-story commercial building that does not meet seismic safety requirements.) Mr. and Mrs. O’Malley, who founded the &lt;em&gt;Planet&lt;/em&gt; as a retirement project after selling a successful software company for millions, pay taxes on an assessed value of $116,440. Homes regularly surpass the $2 million price in their neighborhood, though the median is closer to $1.5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Joe Bravo, a lawyer and landlord residing in Forest Hills, has publicly opposed a proposal for a five-story housing project for low-income senior citizens. In an &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/11/18/13681294/forest-hill-sf-senior-housing-joe-bravo&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with Curbed SF, Bravo said he objected to the height of the project, and feared that allowing development above zoned height limits would only benefit “high tech” people. Bravo’s home in Forest Hill is assessed at a $1.1 million net taxable value. Homes of a similar size sell for up to $3 million in that neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I made a handy graphic to illustrate this coalition’s approach to housing affordability:&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/editorial-prop-13-or-the-california-progressive-blindspot-illuminated/malthus-lol.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A funny joke inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malthusian_growth_model&quot;&gt;Thomas Malthus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It is a given that the Bay Area does not have enough housing to accommodate population growth. Few deny this. It is also a given that land is finite in coastal cities, and new rental properties so prohibitively expensive, so privately-financed development alone will not ease this crisis for the state’s lesser-privileged residents (or, for that matter, lesser-privileged hopeful migrants).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What is not as commonly agreed upon is who should pay more to bridge that gap between what the market will bear and what people need &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;. Who is holding out on us?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A friend once told me, only halfway joking, that “if you want to eat the rich, it helps to have them living nearby.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Proposition 13, Old Money doesn’t want New Money living nearby. The rest of us are left to pick up the pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/menlo-park-approves-fivefold-increase-in-housing-near-facebook/">
    <title type="text">Menlo Park Approves Fivefold Increase in Housing Near Facebook</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:55a86e1a-7676-3d0b-97ec-d0f89badbbc4</id>
    <updated>2016-11-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/menlo-park-approves-fivefold-increase-in-housing-near-facebook/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At a special meeting last night, Menlo Park’s City Council approved an upgrade to the city’s General Plan by a 4-1 vote, a significant reform to local land-use regulations that have been largely untouched since 1994. After weathering mild controversies over Facebook’s proposal to build workforce housing near their corporate campus, Menlo Park has essentially quintupled its allowable residential capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Known as ConnectMenlo, the plan to encourage mixed-use development in Menlo Park has been a top priority on the City Council’s Work Plan for 2016. These efforts include rezonings that will allow for more “vibrant” uses of land, including entertainment and retail where such establishments were previously not allowed. Crucially, the plan rezones the Bayside area, home to Facebook’s global headquarters, to include 5,500 dwelling units—a net increase of 4,500 units. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.menlopark.org/DocumentCenter/View/12418&quot;&gt;staff report&lt;/a&gt; delivered to the Council, city staff “anticipates working with property owners to aggressively recruit new retail and entertainment uses as soon as the zoning allows.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The plan also includes goals for 20% Below Market Rate units in all new residential developments.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/menlo-park-approves-fivefold-increase-in-housing-near-facebook/g1-connectmenlo_201611231212296985.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(source: ConnectMenlo)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This update is the culmination of over 60 community meetings, in which neighbors and commercial stakeholders met to discuss a “live/work/play” neighborhood plan to revitalize a mostly industrial area. “Transportation was an important concern,” said Adina Levin, a Menlo Park resident and board member of Friends Of Caltrain who attended many meetings. “One of the motivations to approve the plan is that housing is an important transportation solution to help people commute and run errands without driving.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Under new Green and Sustainable Building Standards in the General Plan upgrade, future development will have to conform to requirements for water efficiency and recycling, including dual plumbing and water budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/menlo-park-approves-fivefold-increase-in-housing-near-facebook/mp-far.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In anticipation of an argument that arises time and again in San Francisco’s contentious land-use battles, the rezonings will also require a diversity of units, both for single occupants and families. One of the new districts will implement a “sliding scale” for the Floor Area Ratio (FAR) of units, which staff writes “would help create a mix of appropriately sized units instead of a few units that are very large.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/">
    <title type="text">Tiny Houses, Huge Hurdles: Panoramic and the Future of Supportive Housing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:2bd97aa1-69d1-36cc-9e73-a5e37a407e06</id>
    <updated>2016-11-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Imagine having no place to live in one of the planet’s most expensive metropolitan areas. For many residents of San Francisco, this is a daily reality. Yet while labor and investment capital pours in, the region’s culture of technological “innovation” has failed to improve the livelihoods of our most vulnerable neighbors. Patrick Kennedy wants to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On a rainy Sunday afternoon, the developer at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panoramic.com/cityspaces-location/cityspaces-micropad/&quot;&gt;Panoramic Interests&lt;/a&gt; welcomed us into his MicroPAD™, a prefabricated “micro-unit” dwelling designed to lower the cost of housing the city’s homeless. Panoramic advertises that construction costs are just 40% of conventional costs. He is visibly beaming as he shows us every miniscule feature, an effortless grin glowing brighter than his neon-yellow raincoat.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/pano2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diagram of the MicroPAD (courtesy: Panoramic Interests)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In general, it is striking how modern such cozy accommodations can appear without looking garishly futuristic. The wooden kitchen cabinets and countertop, the latter painted a gentle cream color, could be from any decade. The bathroom, Kennedy’s favorite feature, is far more welcoming than my own: illuminated by a warm blue light, it features two drains, a slip-resistant floor, and is bounded by shatterproof glass.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/micropad_looking-in.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interior view from the entrance, on a sunny day (courtesy: Panoramic)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The microwave doubles as an oven; the closet could fit twice as much clothes as my walk-in closet. I count at least four electrical outlets, each equipped with additional USB ports. Underneath the bed, you can turn on a blue light that kills bedbugs.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kennedy even has me step outside of the unit and scream at the top of my lungs into the closed window. Inside, the group can scarcely hear a mutter—a useful design feature to have on 9th &amp;amp; Mission, the bustling intersection where Panoramic’s sample MicroPAD now sits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/pano1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yours truly, shouting at the window&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kennedy overhears me praise many features in comparison to my own apartment, and immediately discourages me from doing so. “The point is not to compare this to your own home,.” adds Laura Clark, housing advocate and founder of the nonprofit group &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.growsanfrancisco.org/&quot;&gt;Grow San Francisco&lt;/a&gt;. “Compare this to living on the street. Otherwise, many people get turned off.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The 160-square foot units aim to maximize livability and dignity for the city’s nearly 7,000 homeless residents (at the lowest estimate) while minimizing overhead costs. They’re larger than a typical Single-Room Occupancy (SRO) unit, which are operated like hotels and typically have shared facilities rather than private ones.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://modernluxury.com/san-francisco/story/think-small&quot;&gt;Politically, there’s only one problem:&lt;/a&gt; Mr. Kennedy wants to be a landlord.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Panoramic hopes to stack their prefab modular units, manufactured at Chinese steel plants, in structures up to 8 stories high on city-owned land. (Build any higher, says Kennedy, and costs increase dramatically due to necessary fire codes and other structural costs.) Kennedy hopes to finance this by leasing the units out to the city for $1000 per unit per month. Essentially, the City &amp;amp; County of San Francisco would be a master tenant for the thousands of housing-insecure and homeless residents Panoramic hopes to help.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco is both too dogmatically leftist and too old-school industrialist for this to sit well with the political establishment. The city’s so-called “progressive” faction—whose standard-bearers on the Board of Supervisors, David Campos and Aaron Peskin, both own increasingly valuable homes in upscale neighborhoods—are skeptical that investment capital can have any positive impact in such a crisis of inequality. Meanwhile, the so-called “moderate” faction, beholden to many labor unions as a driving force of their threadbare coalition, is hesitant to support anything without generous local-hire guarantees.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The rents he’s proposing, furthermore, have drawn the ire of the nonprofit development community, who are accustomed to remaining in everyone’s good graces by asking for lower prices from the public sector. Kennedy, for his part, was quick to dismiss this faction as “vigilantes” and a “cartel” &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/the-kennedy-touch-one-case-study-in-berkeley-development/Content?oid=1065637&quot;&gt;fifteen years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/tiny-houses-huge-hurdles-panoramic-and-the-future-of-supportive-housing/micropad_looking-towards-door.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interior view from the window, facing the door (courtesy: Panoramic)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Our conversation turns to the looming federal tyranny many San Franciscans fear, a fear that nearly drained this author of all physical energy that very morning.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think Trump has his sights set on us,” Kennedy tells me. “Even if there’s a trade war with China, there’s no domestic industry to protect, as far as our work is concerned.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This is because Panoramic deals with Chinese manufacturers that sweat every detail. “Our manufacturers install everything in the factory. There’s very little you have to do after delivery, but usually with domestic modular construction, a lot of prep work has to be done anyway. Here, they include the coffeemaker and the mugs. The closet came with coat hangers.” But worse case scenario, if a trade war got seriously ugly? “If an American manufacturer were to offer this, we’d be first in line.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite the ossified political gridlock, Panoramic’s idea is gaining traction. Recently, Planning Commissioners Kathryn Moore and Dennis Richards visited the MicroPAD and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfhac.org/san-francisco-planning-commissioners-impressed-micropad/&quot;&gt;spoke at length about its merits at a public hearing&lt;/a&gt;. Kennedy also says Berkeley City Councilmember Kriss Worthington was impressed after his visit.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But the pride Kennedy takes in his work can’t lift the grimness that hangs heavy over our hearts. What does, for the time being, is a piping hot cappuccino at the café next door, which Kennedy treats us to after the tour.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I stare into an ornate leaf pattern drawn into the milk foam. Outside, the haggard figure of a homeless human being pushes a shopping cart past the corner of my eye. What good is wealth if it doesn’t improve human welfare? What good are ideals if they don't proffer real hope?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We’re in this for the money, among other things,” Kennedy says to us before we part ways. (He loves to cheekily confess to that motive quite often.) “You guys,” he says, nodding at Clark, “are in this for the good of it. Because housing is a good thing.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“See you soon,” everyone says to each other, almost at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/open-letter-forest-hill-affordable-housing/">
    <title type="text">Open Letter: Forest Hill Affordable Housing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:cdb18f90-b68c-31d1-ba13-f05946c1028c</id>
    <updated>2016-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/open-letter-forest-hill-affordable-housing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Concerned Citizens</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor's Note: this letter was sent to District 7 Supervisor Norman Yee by constituents who have agreed to publish its contents under the condition of anonymity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Yee,&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As 40+ year residents of San Francisco now living in Parkmerced, we are seniors without a personal need for affordable housing, but there are thousands of people in this city NOT so lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We urge you to support, and allow the other supervisors to support,  the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/forest-hill-neighbors-oppose-150-unit-senior-housing-proposal/&quot;&gt;affordable senior housing development&lt;/a&gt; proposed for the Christian Church site in Forest Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We were homeowners in Forest Hill for 15 years, living near the Forest Hill Clubhouse.  We would support the development if we lived there still.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We understand that the leader of the opposition to the development is an attorney whose property apparently lies on the hillside above the proposed site.  Thus, the development IS more or less in his back yard....and all the arguments he advances in opposition to the development are classic NIMBY arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;You are aware as we are that there is a housing crisis in this city.  That crisis can only be resolved by construction of more housing for the people coming to San Francisco, as we came before the Summer of Love.  The City is never going to be restored to what it was then, regardless of the activities of the faux progressives like Aaron Peskin, who, with his allies, operates an elaborate pay 4 play form of crony capitalism favoring those developers who contribute largely to the campaign funds he favors. Nor should our political leadership support activities that try to restore it to that state.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We encourage you to rise above the narrow political program of those who came to SF years ago and now are primarily interested in preserving the advantages they gained by being early arrivals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In the US, which has free immigration among the States, it is the responsible thing for cities and States to which people migrate to make reasonable efforts to permit enough housing to be built to accommodate everyone... immigrants as well as seniors and lower-income current residents.  Such building, of course, must comply with local zoning and affordability requirements, as, we think,  does the proposed Forest Hill development.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Thank you for rejecting the NIMBY arguments and for your support of a sensible project for a forward-looking San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Concerned Citizens]&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/review-arrival-is-here-but-can-it-please-leave-now/">
    <title type="text">Review: &quot;Arrival&quot; Is Here But Can It Please Leave Now?</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a0aad841-fc84-3b3a-a377-0feb9f5554cf</id>
    <updated>2016-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/review-arrival-is-here-but-can-it-please-leave-now/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For this year’s holiday sendoff, &lt;em&gt;BAMO&lt;/em&gt; reviews &lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt;, Denis Vellevue’s latest dreamy sci-fi flick starring Amy Adams and Jeremy Renner’s biceps.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Arrival” is an interesting word choice for this film title. It is mysterious, vague, and relatively neutral in tone – we don’t have any indication if what happens after the “arrival” will be good or bad. At some level, there is a looming, ominous feeling, just from the sheer scale of the vessels shown in the movie posters and trailer, but little to suggest that sweeping destruction of mankind is imminent.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What we do know, from the trailer at least, is that an extraterrestrial presence has arrived on Earth, in the form of gargantuan metalloid shells floating above the planet’s surface. We know Amy Adams is the protagonist linguistics professor tasked with communicating with the visitors; we know Jeremy Renner will be somehow involved, and it appears Forest Whitaker will take on the role of the irrationally inflexible government/army supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On the last one: I won’t harp on this too much, but if you’ve heard any reviews of &lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt; you have probably heard about the atrocious accent Whitaker adopts for the character – sort of a choppy New Englander/townie inflection, but with 10% commitment and 90% disorientation. Forget interpreting the aliens, can someone please tell me &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tFMo3UJ4B4g#t=00m15s&quot;&gt;what the hell Forrest Whitaker is doing here&lt;/a&gt;? Ok, we can move on.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ineffective accents are a minor failure, but the overall direction and thematic messaging represent the bigger miss. That was especially disappointing because of the promising cast, and the undeniable talent of director Denis Villeneuve. Villeneuve’s &lt;em&gt;Sicario&lt;/em&gt; was one of my favorite movies of last year, a film that confronts its audience with both the expected – humanity at its worst, entangled in drug cartels, violence, greed, power – and the less obvious –  a revolving point of view that casts doubt on our collective, often simplistic judgments about morality. There’s a lot to unpack, and closure remains elusive.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt; offers none of this mystery, ambiguity, or moral digging – it simply slaps a humanist message on a sci-fi-lite plot and calls it a day. We get a very clear point of view; we get closure; we get Jeremy Renner’s biceps. This whole sappy package is force fed to the audience through twinkling, gentle vignettes that leave nothing thematic to the imagination, and a painfully overt motif about “what really matters in life.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/review-arrival-is-here-but-can-it-please-leave-now/amy-adams-arrival.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amy Adams is also tired of this film by this point, but look how pretty the lighting is. Oh, and look who is in the foreground and look what is in the background. Hmm, what might the real focus of this film be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I can’t believe I’m saying this, but M. Night Shyamalan’s 2002 &lt;em&gt;Signs&lt;/em&gt; actually did a far superior job at weaving the human story into the UFO plot. &lt;em&gt;Signs&lt;/em&gt; drops clues throughout the film, and while it is understood how important family is to Mel Gibson’s protagonist in the midst of an alien invasion, there is still a real element of uncertainty regarding the convergence of the two until the very end. The point is, there is a way to intertwine human themes in a science fiction story without rubbing the audience’s face in it like a misbehaved puppy.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Alas, most reviewers are falling over themselves about &lt;em&gt;Arrival.&lt;/em&gt; The main crux of the plot, an academic using linguistics to approach extraterrestrial beings, has delighted critics, in contrast to the more destructive and explosive greeting we generally expect from Hollywood. The government employs Adams to decrypt the language of the alien “heptapods,” creatures which sort of resemble giant elephant squid knuckles, an assignment she performs thoughtfully, gradually, and peacefully. Meanwhile, the army seems to hover on razor’s edge, blistering for a change in tone and more aggressive strategy. So, yes, this was a nice contrast, and a novel offering to an “OMG ALIENS NOW WHAT” plot.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The real essence of the story, while I do not want to give too much away of it, is the artful and complex treatment of time and language revealed through Adams interactions with the heptapods. In case you’ve never read Kurt Vonnegut, time can be non-linear, except that humans perceive time linearly, which means that if you want to imagine a twist to &lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt; you now have all the tools you need.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In fairness, this film is an adaptation of a short story, so my criticisms of the narrative itself can’t be entirely targeted at the direction or cast portrayal. That aside, the direction could have been more subtle, and ultimately rewarding, had the message of the story not been so incessantly pushed at the viewer.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The pros: the film is beautifully shot, and the communicative journey undertaken by Adams and Renner is both creative and realistic. The score is powerful, intense, and thunderous, although like many epic sci-fi films seems to have borrowed heavily from the &lt;em&gt;Inception&lt;/em&gt; theme (BA-WAHHHHH tones. Like that.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Editor's note: Jóhann Jóhannsson is not our preferred film composer, though it is notable that, unlike many contemporaries, his score is bequeathed with approval from the world of Classical Music with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Arrival-Johann-Johannsson/dp/B01LZ4WK2S&quot;&gt;vinyl release&lt;/a&gt; by the&lt;/em&gt; Deutsche Grammophon &lt;em&gt;imprint.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Other, more trivial cons: Jeremy Renner was an odd casting choice. There was no chemistry between him and Adams, and his plucky optimism seemed starkly out of place in a predominantly grey, gloomy piece. Also, pacing. Time is a crucial element of this film, so perhaps this was a very meta-choice, but the film seriously and unnecessarily drags in tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Finally, the hokey conclusion manages to bundle both an unexpected reveal and the most predictable trope storytelling knows.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt; disappoints if you are looking for a planet-smashing sci-fi film, and equally disappoints if you are looking for artistic depth. We award this film a two-story rating.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/review-arrival-is-here-but-can-it-please-leave-now/story.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/trauss-sfbarf-v-city-of-lafayette-petitioners-brief/">
    <title type="text">Trauss, SFBARF v. City of Lafayette: Petitioners' Brief</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:9c3931b5-9102-3519-8d90-4cbcd8659065</id>
    <updated>2016-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/trauss-sfbarf-v-city-of-lafayette-petitioners-brief/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last year, our webmaster Sonja Trauss filed a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carlaef.org/s/FINAL-Second-Amended-Petition-with-exhibits.pdf&quot;&gt;lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; against the City of Lafayette, a wealthy East Bay suburb, for violating state housing law. The suit concerns Homes at Deer Hill, a development of 44 single-family homes estimated to sell for $1.2 million. The developer, O'Brien Homes, had previously proposed a 315-unit apartment complex at the same site, but was met with stiff local opposition. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.modernluxury.com/san-francisco/story/city-housing-activists-test-out-brazen-new-battle-cry-sue-the-suburbs&quot;&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;em&gt;San Francisco Magazine&lt;/em&gt; provides ample background, and the recently filed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carlaef.org/s/Petitioners-Memorandum-of-Points-and-Authorities-in-Support-of-Petition-for-Writ-of-Administrative-M.pdf&quot;&gt;petitioners' brief&lt;/a&gt; is below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;embed src=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/55dbb5e9e4b0703ec759c956/t/583b992cb8a79b774fbdee71/1480300858030/Petitioners%27+Memorandum+of+Points+and+Authorities+in+Support+of+Petition+for+Writ+of+Administrative+Manduamus.pdf&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; height=&quot;2100px&quot; /&gt;
    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/state-and-local-officials-double-down-on-immigrant-protections/">
    <title type="text">State and Local Officials Double Down on Immigrant Protections</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:53e9de37-5fb4-3860-bb32-dbfc538a58d0</id>
    <updated>2016-11-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/state-and-local-officials-double-down-on-immigrant-protections/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In the wake of a perceived federal mandate for legislated xenophobia after the 2016 Election, politicians both in San Francisco and the state of California have begun further publicizing their support for undocumented migrants.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco’s Public Defender Jeff Adachi has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/sf-may-create-legal-team-fight-upcoming-trump-deportations/&quot;&gt;proposed&lt;/a&gt; a “universal representation” program to defend the rights of an estimated 30,000 undocumented immigrants living in the city. Adachi plants to request 30 or 40 attorneys on retainer to represent noncitizens facing deportation, a program modeled after a New York City program implemented in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The City Attorney’s Office has also stated that San Francisco stands by its legal obligation to protect the private information of undocumented residents holding &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/sf-promises-keep-city-ids-undocumented-immigrants-private/?utm_campaign=magnet&amp;amp;utm_source=article_page&amp;amp;utm_medium=recommended_articles&quot;&gt;City ID cards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On the statewide front, Lt. Governor Gavin Newsom has penned an open letter to Chancellors of the University of California, California State University, and California Community College systems urging them to affirm the status of their universities as sanctuary campuses. Newsom advocated for these institutions to protect the information of their students from the federal government, particularly of students with an undocumented immigration status.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last week, the former Mayor of San Francisco gave a rousing press conference on the steps of city hall. Though nominally a celebration of Propositions 63 and 64 passing, Newsom turned to the post-election fears expressed in subsequent protests throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“If we can practice the politics of inclusion,” Newsom said, “if we can try to build bridges and bring people together...we have unlimited potential.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&quot;I think what makes California great…we don’t tolerate our diversity, we celebrate our diversity,” Newsom added. &quot;We believe that inclusive societies are adaptable societies. We believe that adaptability and flexibility are what will allow us not just to survive the 21st century, but to thrive.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At a press conference yesterday in the UCSF Mission Bay Campus, Newsom noted that the country has far fewer than 3 million undocumented immigrants reside in the country, and that the President-elect would likely have to deport non-felons if his stated goals remain in place.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Newsom is widely regarded as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/Gavin-Newsom-leading-candidate-in-18-10614220.php?t=e6e830851a&amp;amp;cmpid=email-premium&quot;&gt;top contender&lt;/a&gt; for Governor in the 2018 race.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/caltrain-begins-construction-to-prepare-for-electrified-rail/">
    <title type="text">Caltrain Begins Construction to Prepare for Electrified Rail</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:17d019ab-d9e3-3026-88a5-8fa257d88d08</id>
    <updated>2016-11-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/caltrain-begins-construction-to-prepare-for-electrified-rail/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After enduring years of litigation, the diesel train system connecting San Francisco to the Peninsula and South Bay cities of San Jose and Gilroy will soon be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/caltrain-begins-3-month-construction-project-anticipation-system-electrification/&quot;&gt;upgraded&lt;/a&gt; to an electric rail system, in preparation for integrating with a future High Speed Rail. As part of the Caltrain Modernization Program (CalMod), the agency will begin work this week on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.caltrain.com/projectsplans/CaltrainModernization/Modernization/PeninsulaCorridorElectrificationProject.html&quot;&gt;Peninsula Corridor Electrification Project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Over the next three months, Caltrain will be upgrading utilities and testing soil along Peninsula stations, with an occasional need for single-tracking trains resulting in reduced service. By mid-2017, the agency expects to begin construction. The Peninsula Corridor portion of CalMod is expected to be completed by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/caltrain-begins-construction-to-prepare-for-electrified-rail/calmod.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;(courtesy: Caltrain)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Among numerous improvements cited, Caltrain expects a 97% reduction in carbon emissions, less noise, and an approximately threefold increase in train service.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/bitter-sf-supes-send-landmark-mission-project-back-to-drawing-board/">
    <title type="text">Bitter SF Supes Send Landmark Mission Project Back to Drawing Board</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:6f068684-3927-3f39-9b14-cc71914a1abc</id>
    <updated>2016-11-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/bitter-sf-supes-send-landmark-mission-project-back-to-drawing-board/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At a bitter and raucous meeting in San Francisco’s City Hall, the Board of Supervisors voted to uphold an appeal and require developers of a project at 1515 South Van Ness Avenue with 157 residential units to go back to the drawing board. By a unanimous 9-0 vote, the Supervisors urged Lennar Multifamily to await further review of economic impacts under the framework of the California Environmental Quality Act (CEQA). (Supervisors Yee and Wiener were absent.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The project will now be remanded to the city’s Planning Department, with instructions to report on the potential impacts of gentrification its market-rate units would bring to the area.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Watch full highlights from the Board meeting below:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/flFLGpnQ-AM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Some supporters of the project objected that the Mission District advocacy group Calle 24 based their appeal on CEQA grounds after failing to obtain enough signatures to appeal the Conditional Use Permit (CUP) itself, which was granted by a unanimous vote of the city’s Planning Commission. Supervisor David Campos echoed these concerns, saying “I don’t think they [the appellants] did a good enough job in many respects,” when explaining his vote to uphold the appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Previously, &lt;em&gt;Mission Local&lt;/em&gt; had &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/08/mission-district-housing-project-reaches-25-percent-affordable/&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that the project at 1515 South Van Ness had reserved 25% of dwelling units for middle- and low-income households, despite being approved before citywide requirements were raised to 25%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Even by San Francisco standards, the special meeting was particularly rife with partisan vitriol. One opponent of the project roared against the Board, accusing Supervisors Farrell and Tang of donning “klan robes.” The man proceeded to call the entire Board “nasty, vile humans” and “whores” before Board President London Breed calmly dismissed him from the dais.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Both sides framed the debate in terms of the need to preserve San Francisco’s sanctuary city status in light of an impending anti-immigrant Presidency, but disagreed on whether the project as currently proposed was conducive or deleterious to those ends.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/bitter-sf-supes-send-landmark-mission-project-back-to-drawing-board/berniepuppet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;An opponent of 1515 South Van Ness speaks through his Bernie Sanders puppet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Local landlord Spike Kahn, who owns multiple rental properties and also rents short-term on Airbnb, decried an impending loss of “a more diverse community” that had initially motivated her to buy a home in the Mission District three decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Another woman speaking in favor of the appeal, a native of the Mission, expressed frustration that some supporters of Lennar’s development had opposed an apartment complex for low-income seniors at 1296 Shotwell Street because it could obstruct views for residents in the wealthier Bernal Heights neighborhood (coincidentally, where Supervisor Campos owns an eight-bedroom home). Though she followed Marie Sorenson of Calle 24, who also opposed the project, Sorenson had &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/05/neighbors-of-mission-district-affordable-housing-cry-too-tall/&quot;&gt;previously stated&lt;/a&gt; her opposition to the senior housing complex, fearing that its height would set a bad precedent for the Mission.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite this rhetoric, Supervisor David Campos attributed his vote to uphold the appeal—a vote which the rest of the Board dutifully supported—on an inflammatory speech decrying perceived nativism. “Someone said this building would be a stranger in the neighborhood, as though it were self-evident that it’s bad…and that disturbed me a lot,” said Sonja Trauss, co-founder of the San Francisco YIMBY Party and webmaster of this publication. Trauss also noted that the City Controller found in a study last year that 84% of residents in new buildings were already residents of San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Campos claimed that Trauss’s speech, along with public comment from Patrick McMillan, CEO of McMillan Electric, about “gangs” and “drug-dealers” that Trauss later described as “unacceptably classist,” for changing his mind.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lennar Multifamily Communities has paid McMillan Electric, the previous occupants at 1515 South Van Ness, to move to a new location on Cesar Chavez Street. McMillan testified before the board that the payoff enabled him to hire 25 new employees.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While many white commenters bemoaned the loss of the neighborhood’s Latino population, others noted that a separate subsidiary of Lennar was involved in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/toxic-soil-scandal-halts-hunters-point-development/&quot;&gt;scandal-ridden development&lt;/a&gt; in the Hunters Point Shipyard, where the Navy’s contractor Tetra Tech was found to have falsified their soil samples intending to decontamination of the radioactive land. (Some commenters erroneously described TetraTech as a contractor hired by Lennar.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Campos, a graduate of Harvard Law School, explained to the other supervisors that he was fully aware his comments could open the city up to litigation. To that admission, he simply added, “Bring it on.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/activists-and-developers-negotiate-in-oakland-chinatown/">
    <title type="text">Activists and Developers Negotiate in Oakland Chinatown</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:7f396066-d5b8-3bea-8b35-1143728a6979</id>
    <updated>2016-11-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/activists-and-developers-negotiate-in-oakland-chinatown/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Oakland’s City Council reviewed an appeal during a special meeting last night contesting the approval of 226 13th Street, a six-story mixed-use project with 262 residential units proposed by local developer Wood Partners. Though no legal basis was cited, a coalition of Chinatown neighborhood groups organized to oppose the project in order to “extract concessions” from the developer in the form of a “community benefits package.” Organized opposition was spearheaded by Lailan Huen, daughter of former Oakland Mayor Jean Quan.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Among a litany of community benefits acquired, Councilmember Abel Guillen cites retail space reserved for small businesses in Oakland's new Black Arts Movement Business District; $100,000 for local construction job training; a 20% local hire goal; a $250,000 contribution to anti-displacement programs; and a 1% “art fee” for the nearby Malonga Center. In total, Wood Partners will grant $1.8 million in community benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/activists-and-developers-negotiate-in-oakland-chinatown/quan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Mayor Jean Quan speaks at City Hall, with her daughter Lailan waiting in line behind her&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;With reference to current debates over immigration policy, Pamela Drake of the Wellstone Democratic Club said, “we also need to be a sanctuary for people who are already here…it’s incumbent upon regular residents to spend hours, days, and months making sure that we actually recognize the needs of our residents.” She urged city staff to find representatives with local experience to incorporate community concerns into the planning process, “not at the other end” after permits are issued.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/abelguillencinco/posts/1878592962372112&quot;&gt;Facebook post&lt;/a&gt;, Guillen elaborated: “Although this project predates the adoption of impact fees in Oakland, the developer will make a $675,000 contribution that will help close the gap necessary to build 60 units of affordable housing in the neighborhood.” The Councilmember added that replacing a surface parking lot with housing was essential for mitigating the housing shortage and curbing car dependence, but that he also intended to promote plans for creating a “historic overlay” to protect Chinatown as a cultural asset.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“This sets a precedent that is really critical…We don’t want to have to fight every development,” Huen said during the public comment period. “We need the city to have more comprehensive development policies.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Oakland’s new &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/Oakland-to-impose-impact-fees-on-new-housing-7280444.php&quot;&gt;impact fee requirements&lt;/a&gt; for market-rate development came into effect on September 1st, before Wood Partners completed the permitting process for the project. Observers have speculated whether or not such policies will indeed satisfy community activists who would otherwise insist on politically bartering with every development that gets proposed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/study-on-tech-shuttles-confirms-more-is-safer-and-greener/">
    <title type="text">Study on “Tech Shuttles” Confirms, More Is Safer (and Greener)</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:ea62d7ae-59e4-3577-8599-331662e7933f</id>
    <updated>2016-11-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/study-on-tech-shuttles-confirms-more-is-safer-and-greener/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Whenever a public agency evaluates the efficacy of a private enterprise, tensions inevitably arise. This dynamic remains true today now that San Francisco’s Municipal Transportation Agency (SFMTA) has released its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfmta.com/sites/default/files/agendaitems/2016/11-15-16%20Item%2011%20Commuter%20Shuttle%20Program%20Mid%20Term%20Status%20Report.PDF&quot;&gt;study on commuter shuttles&lt;/a&gt;, and in a separate report, found major faults with recent proposals to consolidate shuttle stops into a handful of “hubs.” Supporters of widespread commuter shuttle programs were not surprised by the results.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;SFMTA &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfmta.com/sites/default/files/projects/2016/Commuter_Shuttle_Hub_Report_Final.pdf&quot;&gt;evaluated&lt;/a&gt; four potential scenarios for redistributing commuter shuttles throughout the city, finding that each option would result in more commutes taken via personal vehicles. Despite decreasing the number of loading zones in the city by almost half, SFMTA’s initial status report found that their Commuter Shuttle pilot program had nevertheless reduced anticipated carbon emissions and increased ridership by 1,000 daily commuters.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For some political stakeholders, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/city-makes-last-call-tech-shuttle-transit-hubs/&quot;&gt;that isn’t enough&lt;/a&gt;. Though hubs remain a popular option, SFMTA withholds any optimism from such proposals. In their concluding remarks, SFMTA states, “nearly all, or approximately 90%, of those riders who shift modes are expected to switch to driving. This forecast holds true under all scenarios.” The first option studied, a “Single Hub” plan with bus stops clustered around the developing Transbay Terminal, would result in an estimated eightfold increase of Vehicle Miles Traveled (VMT). The remaining three options were all estimated to encourage a fivefold VMT increase. All scenarios would also be expected to increase traffic collisions.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/study-on-tech-shuttles-confirms-more-is-safer-and-greener/shuttlehub2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;source: SFMTA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In other words, workers commuting from San Francisco to jobs on the Peninsula are generally expected to commute via automobile and contribute to increased traffic congestion if deprived of their current shuttle options. Only 10% of those surveyed said they would opt to take some form of public transit, such as Caltrain.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/study-on-tech-shuttles-confirms-more-is-safer-and-greener/shuttlehub1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;source: SFMTA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Other scenarios still involved a significant decrease in the number of permitted shuttle stops: a BART-Oriented Scenario would have five bus hubs located around highly frequented BART stations in the city, namely Embarcadero, Civic Center, 16th &amp;amp; Mission, 24th &amp;amp; Mission, and Balboa Park. A Freeway-Adjacent Scenario would have nine hubs within a quarter-mile of freeway on-ramps, with all but two clustered around the eastern portion of the city. Finally, a Consolidated Network Scenario would preserve the current clustering of shuttle zones while aiming to reduce the total amount by at least half.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Erin McElroy, founder of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.antievictionmap.com/&quot;&gt;Anti-Eviction Mapping Project&lt;/a&gt;, expressed adamant opposition to the shuttle program. She claims her organization’s data shows a strong correlation between shuttle stops, evictions, and rent increases. “It seems as if the city is subsidizing the lives of people who ride the luxury commuter shuttles at the expense of those who don’t,” she stated &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Cutting-tech-shuttle-stops-will-add-cars-in-SF-10610440.php?t=66bdcd6df6&amp;amp;cmpid=twitter-premium&quot;&gt;in an interview&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;em&gt;Chronicle&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Currently, there are 16 commuter shuttle services operating with permits from SFMTA. SFMTA’s current Commuter Shuttle Program has 110 shuttle stops in operation, with the total allowable number capped at 125 (down from over 200 before the program was implemented). Companies operating these shuttles are required to pay a “stop event” fee of $7.31 for every individual stop in a shuttle zone.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;McElroy moved to San Francisco to attend the Center for Integral Studies after receiving a BA in Cultural Studies from Hampshire College and a BA in Studio Art from NYU. In a phone interview, she criticized SFMTA’s analysis for omitting data regarding displacement. “When these stops raise property values,” she argues, the poorer residents displaced by rising rents “are moving to the suburbs, and they’re often driving back into the city for school or work. So you’re still going to see more car use.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When asked what sort of analysis she would prefer to see, McElroy noted that “anyone in Urban Planning 101 can tell you, housing and transportation are very much connected. It’s unethical, I think, for the city to leave housing out of the equation.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As for Caltrain—for many, the only available transit mode connecting the city to the Peninsula—the diesel-powered train that runs once an hour is slated to upgrade its rails to an electrified system after &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/caltrain-electrification-to-proceed-after-atherton-lawsuit-fails/&quot;&gt;prevailing in a lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; that sought to stall High-Speed Rail development.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Adrian Covert, Vice President of Policy at the Bay Area Council, remains hopeful that the report will lead to improved transportation policy in San Francisco.  In his view, a calculated dispersal of shuttle stops throughout the city is critical for improving traffic safety, particularly to avoid bus travel on non-arterial or primarily residential streets. “The numbers speak for themselves,” he said in a phone interview.  “Any time you increase VMT, you minimize the benefits and maximize the impact on neighborhoods.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/analyzing-the-palo-alto-city-council-election/">
    <title type="text">Analyzing the Palo Alto City Council Election</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:4b1ce693-76d6-386c-a434-4aa3cbfd5165</id>
    <updated>2016-11-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/analyzing-the-palo-alto-city-council-election/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After facing a deluge of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/30/us/spotty-cell-reception-in-the-heart-of-silicon-valley.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;national media scrutiny&lt;/a&gt; for its resistance to residential growth, Palo Alto may have begun a new chapter in its history. After so-called “Residentialist” City Council candidates Arthur Keller and Lydia Kou raised upwards of $100,000 to run &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-council-race-gets-greener-but-not-from-grassroots/&quot;&gt;attack ads&lt;/a&gt; on candidates Adrian Fine and Liz Kniss, those in favor of keeping Palo Alto small and quaint now find themselves outnumbered in the city’s legislative body.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Hyperlocal pundits believe that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paloaltoonline.com/news/2016/11/08/kniss-tanaka-kou-and-fine-take-lead-in-council-race&quot;&gt;election&lt;/a&gt; of Adrian Fine, Greg Tanaka, and Liz Kniss—as well as Lydia Kou—now puts the “Not In My Back Yard” cohort of the City Council at a 5-4 minority.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Fine, however, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-candidates-talk-quality-of-life-and-regional-growth-in-forum/&quot;&gt;has remained steadfast&lt;/a&gt; in his refusal to play into any partisan or divisive narrative. “I'm honored and humbled to be elected,” he said in a brief interview. “I think that my message of inclusiveness and our ground game won the day. From day one, I focused on housing and transportation choices, and it really resonated.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Resonated” is one way to put it. In more practical terms, Fine’s success can largely be attributed to effective organizing and voter outreach.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The following map of voting precincts in Palo Alto illustrates the small city’s overall support for pro-housing candidates. The only precincts with a majority of votes going to the “slow-growth” coalition are in Arthur Keller’s neighborhood of Ramos Park, and Lydia Kou’s neighborhood of Barron Park. Curiously, Kou’s home precinct favored the pro-growth slate by 2%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/d/embed?mid=1mlfHeeZHKLcSkhRe7l53Ofqxmxw&amp;hl=en&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;These results could serve as a valuable cautionary tale for would-be public officials: no matter your funding, it always pays to court the vote beyond your own back yard.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-what-this-election-really-means/">
    <title type="text">Op-Ed: What This Election Really Means</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:47736e59-d423-3131-a8d0-20c10f7f3e53</id>
    <updated>2016-11-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/op-ed-what-this-election-really-means/" />
    <author>
      <name>Mike Ege</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In 2017, Donald Trump will be our next president. That means that anything is possible politically, for better or worse.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Trump won in part due to the increasing numbers of people who feel marginalized, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/global-opinions/wp/2016/11/10/im-a-muslim-a-woman-and-an-immigrant-i-voted-for-trump/?wpisrc=nl_most-draw7&amp;amp;wpmm=1&quot;&gt;regardless of background&lt;/a&gt;. The national election was more than anything about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thenation.com/article/inequality-gave-rise-to-donald-trumps-presidency/&quot;&gt;inequality&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://inthesetimes.com/article/19618/listen-leftist-thomas-frank-donald-trump-hillary-clinton-bernie-sanders&quot;&gt;failure of political Progressives&lt;/a&gt; to respond to the marginalized in a meaningful way.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Whether you rent or own, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2014-07-17/housings-30-percent-of-income-rule-is-near-useless&quot;&gt;paying for housing&lt;/a&gt; makes up the biggest chunk of working families’ budgets, and the rising cost of housing, along with stagnant wages, has been a primary engine of inequality in the United States. The result is that a whole range of working people, from food service workers to middle managers, now live in a state of &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedisorderofthings.com/2013/10/12/struggling-with-precarity-from-more-and-better-jobs-to-less-and-lesser-work/&quot;&gt;economic precarity&lt;/a&gt;. This includes many sectors that political Progressives simply &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lrb.co.uk/v16/n07/edward-luttwak/why-fascism-is-the-wave-of-the-future&quot;&gt;don’t care about&lt;/a&gt;, because of the perception that they don’t vote for them.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Housing also figures into the rise of Donald Trump as a public figure. Trump first made a name for himself by taking advantage of New York City’s bankruptcy in 1975 to access redevelopment financing, using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2016/07/trump-files-how-donald-tricked-new-york-huge-deal&quot;&gt;the Grand Hyatt hotel project&lt;/a&gt; to elevate his business away from a portfolio of middle-class rental housing to one of luxury properties. In doing so, he contributed to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/high-income-renters-2016-11&quot;&gt;rising inequality in our cities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;If we are to take Trump’s platform at face value, housing will continue to be an issue. While much of his rhetoric was likely &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/many-of-trumps-sweeping-promises-will-be-hard-if-not-impossible-to-fulfill/2016/11/09/b07867be-a6a9-11e6-ba59-a7d93165c6d4_story.html?wpisrc=nl_most-draw7&amp;amp;wpmm=1&quot;&gt;meant to be an analogy&lt;/a&gt; for an agenda which is at the same time more realistic and unfortunately only slightly less repugnant, that agenda will still exacerbate inequality in America, and housing will play a major role. The downsizing of government payrolls, increases in &lt;a href=&quot;https://newrepublic.com/article/138674/beware-donald-trumps-infrastructure-plan&quot;&gt;infrastructure spending&lt;/a&gt;, and the expansion of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rawstory.com/2016/11/donald-trump-will-be-the-fossil-fuel-industrys-greatest-gift/&quot;&gt;extractive industries&lt;/a&gt; will create another wave of worker migration, putting &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2015-09-29/man-camp-exodus-spurs-real-estate-crisis-across-u-s-shale-towns&quot;&gt;further stress&lt;/a&gt; on regional housing supplies.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Now more than ever, there is a real need to pivot the policy narrative on housing toward its consideration as human infrastructure, and not as an investment commodity. Here in the Bay Area, while the rhetoric will be different, the political obstacles will be the same.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Our region’s “Progressive” and “Neighborhood” movements may pay lip service to a social narrative which is very different from the Trump agenda, but in reality their agenda is equally reactionary.  The primary goals of these local anti-housing movements are to preserve existing wealth and power. This includes the continued assertion of intangible rights (such as to views) in association with property ownership, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2015/12/san-francisco-is-confused-about-the-villain-thats-making-it-unaffordable/422091/&quot;&gt;unequal tax benefits&lt;/a&gt; granted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thenation.com/article/have-california-voters-finally-had-enough-of-prop-13/&quot;&gt;Proposition 13&lt;/a&gt;, and opposition to &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.streetsblog.org/2016/06/14/mission-transit-lane-removal-nudged-closer-to-reality/&quot;&gt;better transit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2016-08-02/san-francisco-progressives-declare-war-on-affordable-housing&quot;&gt;denser housing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the sad news on the national front, the YIMBY movement has scored significant political victories in the Bay Area. San Francisco’s pro-urbanist Supervisor &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nbcbayarea.com/news/local/Scott-Wiener-Captures-State-Senate-Seat-400551351.html&quot;&gt;Scott Wiener&lt;/a&gt; was elected to the State Senate and will continue the fight for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mercurynews.com/2016/09/21/commentary-jerry-browns-by-right-housing-plan-needs-another-try/&quot;&gt;By-Right Development&lt;/a&gt; in Sacramento. A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/news/2016/11/09/sf-board-of-supervisors-housing-policy.html&quot;&gt;pro-housing majority&lt;/a&gt; will likely be restored to the San Francisco Board of Supervisors, and ballot initiatives which would’ve been most harmful to the continued development of affordable housing were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hoodline.com/2016/11/san-francisco-ballot-results-2016-proposition-q-u-v-homeless-soda-tax&quot;&gt;defeated&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, more pro-housing members were elected to the&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mercurynews.com/2016/11/03/palo-alto-city-council-race/&quot;&gt; Palo Alto City Council&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Some may attempt to portray these victories as part of a “Trump Wave.” It will be incumbent upon us to point out who the real Trumpists are.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/bay-area-protests-surge-in-response-to-national-election/">
    <title type="text">Bay Area Protests Surge in Response to National Election</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:457eab73-210c-358e-8237-6ca378922a2d</id>
    <updated>2016-11-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/bay-area-protests-surge-in-response-to-national-election/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Thousands of students in San Francisco walked out of class today to protest the election of an openly white supremacist and misogynist President. These protests follow in the wake of thousands marching along Market Street last night, from the Ferry Building to the Castro, and more confrontational protests &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/videos-photos-massive-crowd-of-anti-donald-trump-protesters-take-over-downtown-oakland/Content?oid=5030347&quot;&gt;in downtown Oakland&lt;/a&gt;. Oakland students also walked out en masse today, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/videos-photos-massive-crowd-of-anti-donald-trump-protesters-take-over-downtown-oakland/Content?oid=5030347&quot;&gt;Berkeley High School&lt;/a&gt; students staged a protest on the UC Berkeley campus yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;State Senator Mark Leno attended today’s demonstration in front of San Francisco City Hall, telling the &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; that he saw historical parallels between this year’s election and the early 1970s. “[This election] makes me remember how Richard Nixon was re-elected with one of the biggest landslides in American history, yet his term was cut short by one of the worst scandals in our history,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mayor Ed Lee's office has announced that they will make contingency plans to prepare for a complete loss of federal funding in order to preserve San Francisco's &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/SF-preparing-in-case-Trump-cuts-federal-funds-10607210.php?t=faa8df36a2&amp;amp;cmpid=twitter-premium&quot;&gt;sanctuary city status&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In deference to the strength and courage of these demonstrators, we present photographs from staff photographer Mike Ege without comment, and encourage our readers to follow coverage by other local journalists such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/11/mission-high-students-join-hundreds-in-anti-trump-protest/&quot;&gt;Joe Rivano Barros&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Mission Local&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/bay-area-protests-surge-in-response-to-national-election/conscientious.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/bay-area-protests-surge-in-response-to-national-election/dumbeldore.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/former-la-mayor-villaraigosa-announces-run-for-governor/">
    <title type="text">Former LA Mayor Villaraigosa Announces Run for Governor</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:6bff0c8b-1b30-38c0-aa45-dea8fa2807d4</id>
    <updated>2016-11-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/former-la-mayor-villaraigosa-announces-run-for-governor/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar-Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Former Mayor of Los Angeles Antonio Villaraigosa announced today that he would be running for Governor of California in 2018. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://antonioforcalifornia.com/&quot;&gt;candidate&lt;/a&gt; will be facing steep opposition in a crowded race that will include current Lt. Governor Gavin Newsom, State Treasurer John Chiang, and former schools superintendent Delaine Eastin.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Raised by a single mother in Boyle Heights, Villaraigosa served for two terms as the first Latino mayor of Los Angeles from 2005 to 2013. During his mayoralty, Los Angeles weathered a revenue shortfall resulting from the 2008 recession. After raising wages for public employees before the recession, Villaraigosa successfully &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.latimes.com/local/california/la-me-villaraigosa-legacy-20130629-dto-story.html&quot;&gt;negotiated&lt;/a&gt; pay cuts with public unions when tightening the city’s budget.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Before the recession, Villaraigosa’s proposals to address the city’s housing affordability crisis involved lobbying state and federal governments to support first-time home purchasing programs. When foreclosures began to soar, the mayor pivoted to focus on tenant protections, supportive housing for the growing homeless population, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rooflines.org/1181/keeping_hope_and_housing_alive_in_la/&quot;&gt;inclusionary zoning requirements&lt;/a&gt; from market-rate development.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;His administration weathered numerous scandals, including an infidelity charge, and Villaraigosa encountered numerous roadblocks to his housing platform. First, a 2010 court ruling known as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.laobserved.com/boyarsky/2010/02/a_city_hall_backstabbing.php&quot;&gt;Palmer decision&lt;/a&gt; invalidated his plan to require a minimum amount of price-indexed units for lower incomes from private developers. The following year, outrage erupted when the city’s former Housing Authority director Rudolf Montiel received a $1.2 million severance package to settle his wrongful termination claim, and the Mayor’s office initially &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailybreeze.com/20111210/editorial-mayor-antonio-villaraigosa-looks-bad-over-housing-authority-head-scandal&quot;&gt;claimed&lt;/a&gt; Villaraigosa was unaware of the payoff.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Antonio Villaraigosa initially considered the gubernatorial race in 2010, before former and current Governor Jerry Brown obtained the Democratic nomination. His nascent campaign is at a monetary disadvantage compared to that of top contender Gavin Newsom, who has been fundraising since announcing his candidacy in February of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The answer to fear is hope,” Villaraigosa said in a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.latimes.com/politics/la-pol-ca-governor-villaraigosa-20161110-story.html&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with the Los Angeles &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt;. “I’ll be as fair as the day is long.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
