<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Bay Area Metropolitan Observer</title>
  <id>urn:uuid:52c4ddef-40d4-3bc8-bbd3-d91037b58706</id>
  <updated>2016-09-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/" />
  <link href="http://sfbamo.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <author>
    <name></name>
  </author>
  <generator uri="https://github.com/ajdavis/lektor-atom" version="0.2">Lektor Atom Plugin</generator>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/breed-succeeds-in-western-addition-housing-project/">
    <title type="text">Breed Succeeds in Western Addition Housing Project</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:4b8b2ec0-d986-36a5-8489-0846a81f152c</id>
    <updated>2016-09-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/breed-succeeds-in-western-addition-housing-project/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;These past few were likely among the most nerve-wracking in Supervisor London Breed’s career. After facing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/Feds-reject-housing-plan-meant-to-help-minorities-9146987.ph&quot;&gt;pushback&lt;/a&gt;p at the federal level against her Neighborhood Preference Ordinance, the Supervisor &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/breed-vows-to-fight-for-neighborhood-preference-ordinance/&quot;&gt;resisted amid rumors&lt;/a&gt; that her opponents had been conspiring with local representatives of the Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD). This week, HUD &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/news/article/Federal-agency-OKs-preferences-at-new-SF-senior-9238463.php?cmpid=twitter-mobile&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that they would allow neighborhood preference to determine the lottery for the Willie B. Kennedy apartments, although they still opposed the legislation overall.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Breed held a press conference this morning in front of the Willie B. Kennedy apartments in the Western Addition to announce the favorable ruling. The lottery for senior housing units in Willie B. Kennedy had been postponed pending HUD’s decision. Now nearby seniors will have drastically improved chances of winning a subsidized apartment, which Breed views as essential to stemming the loss of San Francisco’s black population. (The city’s African-American population has dwindled to around 5%, while also comprising  over 50% of jail inmates.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Passed unanimously by the Board of Supervisors last year, the law gives preference to residents within the supervisorial district (or within a half-mile radius otherwise) in the lottery for Below Market Rate units. Breed lobbied federal officials, including Representative Nancy Pelosi and Senator Diane Feinstein, and flew to Washington, DC with housing officials from Mayor Ed Lee’s office to meet with HUD representatives in defense of her legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Breed also published an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/powdered-milk-moving-vans-fight-affordable-housing/&quot;&gt;op-ed&lt;/a&gt; today in the San Francisco &lt;em&gt;Examiner&lt;/em&gt; excoriating her opponents for criticizing her record on affordable housing. The supervisorial campaign by millionaire homeowner Dean Preston is supported by local tenant groups, which Breed notes were unwilling to help residents of public housing when her own family faced eviction. Supervisor Breed, who was raised in the projects that once stood across from Willie B. Kennedy, noted that her place of residence had just been sold after the landlord’s death.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Even a San Francisco Supervisor who lobbied federal officials in her efforts to curb displacement faces an uncertain future in her city.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/toxic-soil-scandal-halts-hunters-point-development/">
    <title type="text">Toxic Soil Scandal Halts Hunters Point Development</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:5ccdf373-dea0-3da9-8e95-a88defdeeff6</id>
    <updated>2016-09-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/toxic-soil-scandal-halts-hunters-point-development/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Developers at Lennar Urban received a crushing blow to their plans to develop 12,000 new homes and office space at the Hunters Point Shipyard, from none other than the Environmental Protection Agency. The EPA ordered the Mayor’s Office of Housing and the U.S. Navy to halt the transfer of land in the former shipyard after soil tests conducted by Tetra Tech were found to have been falsified.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The former naval yard housed a military research facility for nuclear weapons, leaving behind deadly radioactive soil when it closed in 1994. After two decades of cleanup and even some new apartments filling up with tenants, the Navy has admitted that its contractor, Tetra Tech, took soil samples from a clean site and passed them off as samples from the once-contaminated shipyard. The accusations were &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nrc.gov/docs/ML1604/ML16042A074.pdf&quot;&gt;corroborated&lt;/a&gt; by the U.S. Nuclear Regulatory Commission. Indeed, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/9/22/13013980/hunters-point-radiation-epa&quot;&gt;Curbed SF points out&lt;/a&gt;, Tetra Tech quite literally covered up the dirt.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The federal agency’s understandable caution still provoked concern among city officials struggling to mitigate effects of the regional housing shortage. Mayor Ed Lee and Supervisor Malia Cohen, whose district encompasses Hunters Point, sent a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scribd.com/document/324834306/9-19-16-Mayor-Lee-Sup-Cohen-Hunters-Point-Shipyard-Letter?content=10079&amp;amp;ad_group=Online+Tracking+Link&amp;amp;campaign=Skimbit%2C+Ltd.&amp;amp;keyword=ft500noi&amp;amp;source=impactradius&amp;amp;medium=affiliate&amp;amp;irgwc=1&quot;&gt;letter&lt;/a&gt; to the EPA requesting a (“confidential if necessary”) briefing so they could understand just how long an investigation of Tetra Tech’s soil analysis could take. The 12,000 total units now stalled in the pipeline make up more than 10% of San Francisco’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://archives.sfexaminer.com/sanfrancisco/leveling-sf-housing-field-could-take-100000-new-units/Content?oid=2703869&quot;&gt;estimated housing need&lt;/a&gt;. Currently, plans call for 1,400 new homes to be completed by 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For the thousands of people struggling to find a home in San Francisco, the EPA’s delay spells a stark choice between commuting from distant suburbs, or risking a miniature Chernobyl in their own back yard.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/democratic-central-committee-considers-new-rule-to-handicap-grassroots-organizing/">
    <title type="text">Democratic Central Committee Considers New Rule to Handicap Grassroots Organizing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:9578c32d-0a8c-3f2b-a46a-05329d9de0dc</id>
    <updated>2016-09-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/democratic-central-committee-considers-new-rule-to-handicap-grassroots-organizing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The June 2016 election of the San Francisco Democratic County Central Committee was one of the most expensive in its history, with a record breaking $2.3 million reported spent. However, illustrating the adage that “money don’t vote,” the big spenders’ candidates &lt;a href=&quot;http://48hills.org/2016/06/07/lessons-june-7-election/&quot;&gt;mostly failed to win seats&lt;/a&gt; on the committee.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Reporting by the Reform slate friendly blog &lt;em&gt;48 Hills&lt;/em&gt; decried outsized spending on the Progress slate &lt;a href=&quot;http://48hills.org/2016/05/27/1-million-tech-real-estate-money-pours-june-sf-election/&quot;&gt;by a few donors&lt;/a&gt; - $25K from Ron Conway; $21K from Robert Rosania, developer of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2015/03/the-monster-in-the-mission-makes-its-case/&quot;&gt;“Monster in the Mission”&lt;/a&gt;; $50K each from Google; Facebook; Evan Williams, the founder of Medium; and $30K from Kevin Systrom, founder of Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Having swept the election, two members of the Reform slate, Petra DeJesus and Pratima Gupta, now seek to prevent large donations by amending SF Democratic Party by-laws to prevent donations to candidates in excess of $500. The amendment exempts the candidates themselves from this limitation. The proposed amendment reads,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Section 5:  LIMITS ON CONTRIBUTIONS TO CANDIDATES FOR THE SF DCCC.&lt;br&gt;
No person &lt;em&gt;other than a candidate&lt;/em&gt; shall make, and no campaign treasurer for a candidate committee shall solicit or accept, any contribution which will cause the total amount contributed by such person to such candidate committee in an election to exceed $500.” (emphasis added)
&lt;a href=&quot;https://d3n8a8pro7vhmx.cloudfront.net/sfdemocrats/pages/13/attachments/original/1474328101/SFDCCC_10-day_Notice_Agenda.pdf?1474328101&quot;&gt;See page 19 for full resolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A DCCC member who declined to be named said, “It is ludicrous to say we should have contribution limits and then allow famous (or already rich) people to run - people who don't have to raise a dime to win.” For niche elections like the Democratic County Central Committee, elections are won and lost because of name recognition, which favors established incumbents. 12 of the 24 newly elected DCCC members are current or former Supervisors.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“This resolution would cripple an actual grassroots campaign for the DCCC,” claims Sonja Trauss, local organizer and co-owner of this paper. “A grassroots candidate, with no name recognition, has to canvass heavily in order to win. Time a candidate spends asking for money is time not spent asking for votes. One $5,000 donation saves the candidate from having to ask 10 people for $500, or, more likely, 100 people for $50 each. I wouldn’t argue with a resolution prohibiting actual large donations - $50,000 at a time. Limiting the contributions to small donations protects the people that are introducing the amendment - incumbents.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Another agenda item to watch on Wednesday is Chairperson Cindy Wu’s appointment of a new SF DCCC member due to a vacancy. Leading up the the June DCCC election, a rumour circulated that the DCCC was going to be stacked with high-profile elected officials who, after winning handily without spending any money, would vacate their seats and allow the new chair to replace them with a Democrat of the chair’s choice. The identity of the outgoing DCCC member is not yet known. If it does turn out to be a high profile elected, the rumor will be on its way to being substantiated.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The next DCCC meeting will be held on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfdemocrats.org/meetings&quot;&gt;September 28th, 7pm at 455 Golden Gate Ave.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-modernizes-parking-regulations/">
    <title type="text">Oakland Modernizes Parking Regulations</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:abc3d0e2-b692-3617-b048-44c726013a8b</id>
    <updated>2016-09-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-modernizes-parking-regulations/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night, the Oakland City Council voted unanimously to upgrade its parking requirements for the first time in over 50 years. Oakland last revised its parking requirements for new development in the downtown area back in 1965. Councilmember Abel Guillen celebrated on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Abel_Guillen/status/778454029898612736&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, writing, “Hello 21st Century.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;City staff &lt;a href=&quot;https://oakland.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?ID=2825408&amp;amp;GUID=CA5A731F-E886-4E19-ADBC-EF00056A817C&amp;amp;Options=&amp;amp;Search=&quot;&gt;recommended&lt;/a&gt; the update in accordance with the 1996 Transit First Policy, as well as Oakland’s current Climate Action Plan.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The changes will affect Downtown Oakland most drastically, replacing the previous 1.25:1 minimum parking-to-housing ratio with a 1.25:1 maximum for parking—no minimum. There is an exception for senior housing, which would receive by-right approval to provide one parking space for every four dwelling units. Commercial space is now limited by a maximum of one parking space for every 300 square feet of ground-floor retail.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There are many more nuances to this legislation, including allowances for car-sharing services such as Zipcar. We recommend this summary on local blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://oaktownacorn.com/2016/09/20/reducing-parking-for-increased-affordability/&quot;&gt;The Oaktown Acorn&lt;/a&gt; for the full scoop.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-why-vote-at-16/">
    <title type="text">Dispatches from the Vote16 Campaign: Why Vote at 16?</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:7da21500-9efc-3240-a7b4-4dfc8c11bcc2</id>
    <updated>2016-09-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/dispatches-from-the-vote16-campaign-why-vote-at-16/" />
    <author>
      <name>Cami Doo</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cami Doo is a junior at St. Ignatius College Preparatory and a special correspondent for the Metro Observer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco’s Proposition F, commonly called &lt;a href=&quot;http://vote16sf.org/&quot;&gt;Vote16&lt;/a&gt;, is a ballot measure that seeks to expand voting rights to 16 and 17 year olds in local and school board elections.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This campaign began in January 2015 when the Youth Commission passed a resolution urging the Mayor and Board of Supervisors to lower the voting age to 16. Two months later, , four Supervisors proposed a charter amendment. Fast forward to May 2016, the Board of Supervisors voted 9-2 to add Vote16 to the November 2016 ballot.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This effort is spearheaded by the Youth Empowerment Academy (YEA) and Generation Citizen’s Celi Tamayo-Lee The YEA includes youth ranging from ages 13 to 17 as well as a few adults. Generation Citizen is a nationwide non-profit organization whose goal is to instill long-term civic engagement into young students, and the YEA was born from the SF Youth Commission’s Civic Engagement Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Along the way, the campaign has collected many important endorsements. The San Francisco Democratic Party (DCCC), Nancy Pelosi, and all the Board of Education commissioners stand beside Yes on Prop F.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Prop F’s goal is to increase SF’s historically low voter turnout.  In fact, voter turnout in SF was 29% in Nov. 2013, 53% in Nov. 2014, and 45% in Nov. 2015. Other countries, on the other hand, enjoy a 80-90% voter turnout.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This non-partisan measure hopes to re-energize the electorate’s excitement about voting with a phenomenon known as the “trickle-up effect.” This effect will spread voter participation to parents and peers, increasing turnout all around (McDevitt and Kiousis 2006).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sixteen year-olds are embedded in their communities. 18 is a transitional age; students are moving elsewhere and do not prioritize voting. At 16, however, students can have informed discussions about the election with their teachers and parents. Therefore, when they go to the polls, they should be educated on all perspectives of the ballot issues.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Prop. F is certainly not a panacea for our low voter turnout, but it is a promising step in strengthening our democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-rejecting-bart-bond-would-throw-commuters-under-the-bus/">
    <title type="text">Editorial: Rejecting BART Bond Would Throw Commuters Under the Bus</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:0658c3ba-ab20-3786-b4ee-21985143e73e</id>
    <updated>2016-09-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/editorial-rejecting-bart-bond-would-throw-commuters-under-the-bus/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday of last week, the &lt;em&gt;East Bay Times (EBT)&lt;/em&gt; published an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbaytimes.com/2016/09/13/editorial-reject-barts-3-5-billion-bond-measure-east-bay-times/&quot;&gt;op-ed&lt;/a&gt; opposing Measure RR, a $3.5 billion bond to finance regional BART improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This was an absurd position to take. BART’s weekday ridership has increased by 30% over the last 5 years, now averaging &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/BART-can-t-keep-pace-with-rising-crush-loads-6192950.php&quot;&gt;420,000&lt;/a&gt;. Without sufficient funding, this high demand has faced increasingly frequent train delays, breakdowns, and packed trains. During rush hour trains, commuters are often forced to let several trains pass by before boarding.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Funds for capital improvements are needed yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;East Bay Times tells a boldfaced lie when claiming that up to a third of the bond revenue could go toward offsetting labor costs, rather than system upgrades and improvements. Doing so would violate California &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/cgi-bin/displaycode?section=gov&amp;amp;group=16001-17000&amp;amp;file=16720-16727&quot;&gt;state law&lt;/a&gt;. BART legally cannot use bond funds for anything except for acquisition of capital assets, or grants or loans related to those specific costs.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;BART projects capital needs of $9.6 billion over the next ten years. It has $4.8 billion already lined up, and would use the $3.5 billion bond revenue to cover part of the shortfall. BART is about 50% covered on capital funds needed, and needs taxpayers to help out with the rest. The full $3.5 billion in bond revenues must, by law, go to capital expenditures, i.e. system upgrades and improvements. BART cannot reach into the bond revenue bucket to pay its employees. Calling this “offsetting labor costs” is a pretty big stretch. Put another way, even if BART holds on to $1.2 billion for operating revenues, it would still have a $3.5 billion capital expenditure shortfall. This whole discussion of labor costs is irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As for the timing and tax burden property owners will face as a result of the bond issuance, BART has been forthright and clear about the bond repayment timeline.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;EBT&lt;/em&gt; argues that BART is misleading voters about the bond repayment timeline, since bond payments will actually be spread out over 48 years, and the text of the measure just refers to 30-year bonds. If you don’t look further into it, you might assume the tax will be paid over 30 years. But BART isn’t hiding this timeline at all. This information is included in the text of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acgov.org/rov/elections/20161108/documents/BondMeasureRR.pdf&quot;&gt;the measure itself&lt;/a&gt;, and is publicly available on its website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;BART anticipates that each bond will be paid off within 30 years &lt;em&gt;after it is issued&lt;/em&gt;, but BART won’t issue all of the bonds at the same time. Why borrow money before you need it? Instead, BART projects it will issue the $3.5 billion in bonds in equal installments every two years for eighteen years as the funds are needed to rebuild the aging system. This means that, from start to finish, &lt;em&gt;BART estimates property owners could be helping BART pay off the bonds for 48 years&lt;/em&gt;. (Emphasis added.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Issuing the bonds as needed is actually far more economical than issuing all at once, and is exactly the kind of forward thinking we want from our transportation agencies. By issuing bonds as needed, taxpayers will not have to pay additional interest on bonds that are not yet being used.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;East Bay Times&lt;/em&gt; tells us the tax in question would require property owners to shell out not the $37, $42, and $52 annually initially promised (per city), but potentially twice that. In fact, the total bill could even go up to &lt;em&gt;four&lt;/em&gt; times the anticipated amount, up to $150-200 annually.. 
This might possible in a technical sense; the maximum annual interest rate permitted by law is 12%. However, BART’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bart.gov/sites/default/files/docs/BART%20%243%205%20Billion%20GO%20Bond%20Measure%20Tax%20Analysis%20%284%25%20AV%20Growth%20Assumption%29%20Summary%20FINAL%20WEBSITE%20POSTING%208%2019%2016.pdf&quot;&gt;internal estimates&lt;/a&gt; peg the rate at 5%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What basis does &lt;em&gt;EBT&lt;/em&gt; have for assuming this rate would more than double? Interestingly, the only evidence that backs up the 4x tax claim by the &lt;em&gt;East Bay Times&lt;/em&gt; op-ed is a link to another &lt;em&gt;East Bay Times&lt;/em&gt; article, a page &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbaytimes.com/2016/09/07/borenstein-bart-%E2%80%A6e-original-claim/&quot;&gt;which no longer exists&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Even if the paper’s speculative math were correct, the worst case scenario of this measure is that the people in the Bay Area who own some of the most valuable real estate in the country would have to contribute something like $12-16 a month toward a critical regional service (rather than the forecasted $8-12 per month).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To that point, we all know that a huge driver of our funding gap arises from &lt;a href=&quot;http://lao.ca.gov/Publications/Report/3497&quot;&gt;Proposition 13&lt;/a&gt;, a statewide ballot initiative passed in 1978 that capped property taxes at its assessed value at the time of the sale, with increases limited to 1% each year. Without this necessary funding from corporate landowners and wealthy homeowners, our regional services have gone chronically underfunded. The cumulative impact of this measure nearly four decades later has proven disastrous for many services, including education and transit.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The cap on property taxes has forced the state to rely on nickel-and-dime fundraising strategies, such as increases in the sales tax, income tax, parcel taxes, and bonds to fund many public services. Most of these funding tactics are regressive in nature, putting an additional financial burden on lower-income residents.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Arguing that “BART needs to earn our trust” after past financial blunders is not a grudge we have the luxury of holding. The Bay Area is not going to stop growing. Urban think tank SPUR estimates that at the current rate of ridership growth, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/think-tank-calls-for-second-bart-transbay-tube/&quot;&gt;BART’s capacity will be exceeded by 2024&lt;/a&gt;. Wagging our finger at BART for past mismanagement will not solve our regional mass transit deficiencies.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The bond measure requires the creation of an independent audit committee, comprised of six professionals from various backgrounds, including public accounting, engineering, and project management. Skepticism toward the audit committee’s effectiveness should not undermine the clear need to fund improvements for BART.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Is it possible that BART will not perfectly maximize use of this revenue? Of course. That is a risk with any use of taxpayer money. If you are frustrated about “platinum” labor contracts afforded to BART employees, fine. But trying to stick it to a station agent by withholding tax money for capital improvements doesn’t change the station agent’s salary.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The loser of not passing the BART bond measure isn’t BART - it’s all of us. The BART Bond would benefit everyone, from those commuting on BART to those driving through lighter traffic, grateful that others are taking public transportation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/chinatown-activist-rose-pak-dies-at-68/">
    <title type="text">Chinatown Activist Rose Pak Dies at 68</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:8a39c267-db86-355d-8e99-10db452878dd</id>
    <updated>2016-09-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/chinatown-activist-rose-pak-dies-at-68/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco is in mourning after Chinatown’s iconic political activist Rose Pak passed away in her home on Sunday morning. Ms. Pak, who grew up in Macau and Hong Kong as a Chinese refugee, relocated to San Francisco in 1967, and was involved in the city’s inner political circles ever since. At the mayor’s request, the city’s flags have been lowered to half-staff in her honor today.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As the only Cantonese-speaking reporter for the San Francisco &lt;em&gt;Chronicle&lt;/em&gt;, Pak covered Chinatown with assiduous discipline. Her career as an activist came to dominate the neighborhood after she championed efforts to save Chinese Hospital, a medical facility serving lower-income residents who mostly spoke Cantonese.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Pak was also instrumental in bringing San Francisco’s current Mayor Ed Lee to power. After she lobbied for his appointment to the administration of Mayor Art Agnos, Lee remained an important figure in local politics, and Pak successfully pushed for his appointment as interim mayor to replace Gavin Newsom. She subsequently led the “Run Ed Run” campaign to convince Lee to run for a successful reelection bid.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The relationship between the two &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/A-gravely-ill-Rose-Pak-on-life-death-and-her-6456189.php&quot;&gt;soured&lt;/a&gt; when Lee appointed Julie Christensen over Pak’s chosen favorite, Cindy Wu, to replace David Chiu as Supervisor of District 3. In retaliation, Pak encouraged former Supervisor Aaron Peskin to run for the position, successfully ousting the appointee and rebalancing the Board of Supervisors in favor of the “progressive” faction.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though often labeled a “power broker,” Pak was fond of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/news/article/Rose-Pak-SF-political-powerhouse-dies-9230594.php&quot;&gt;saying&lt;/a&gt;, “if I were white, they’d call me a civic leader.” Pak will be missed dearly for her ribald conversational style and convivial demeanor. You can watch a sample of her fiery speaking style below:&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8KkvLOUZcnk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/">
    <title type="text">Local Profiles: Oakland's Ratskin Records</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:3de522cb-f5d2-3d5e-ae22-e1031c8c5bdd</id>
    <updated>2016-09-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When I returned from vacation in Mexico this January, I rolled my luggage straight to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ratskin.org/&quot;&gt;Ratskin Records&lt;/a&gt; anniversary party in West Oakland. The legendary Bastard Noise played a devastatingly loud set, true to their name, that could be heard with perfect clarity around the block. I finished a bottle of heavily discounted tequila I’d brought straight from the Distrito Federal with several friends, including Mike Daddona, the local impresario who had organized the mini-festival. Since then, he’s released at least ten new albums, hosted a visual art exhibition, and organized several dozen concerts.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;All in his spare time. “I do it to stay sane,” he says sometimes. “I’m not sure I’d know how to stop.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/ratskin1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Michael Daddona, head of Ratskin Records, assembles cassette albums in his home office (edited per subject's request)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Ratskin brand carries some clout in Oakland. The avant-garde, the macabre, the lurid or confrontational musicians especially know, just by word of mouth, “not just &lt;em&gt;anybody&lt;/em&gt; gets on Ratskin.” The catalog has been expanding all while repping almost exclusively the best of the East Bay: the lusty dance-pop icon &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/maya-songbird-writes-music-for-the-wild-and-weird/Content?oid=4647422&quot;&gt;Maya Songbird&lt;/a&gt;, feminist-noise reggaetón duo &lt;a href=&quot;https://ww2.kqed.org/arts/2016/05/04/wrecking-the-patriarchy-with-oakland-reggaeton-duo-las-sucias/&quot;&gt;Las Sucias&lt;/a&gt;, and mystical hip-hop crooner Tyler Holmes are just some examples of local acts the label has touted lately, all who do much more than just make weird noises by turning knobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RDlTgY5n5_c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3974232074/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ratskinrecords.bandcamp.com/album/maya-songbird-queen-of-darkness-ep&quot;&gt;MAYA  SONGBIRD &amp;quot;QUEEN OF DARKNESS&amp;quot; EP by Maya Songbird&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Voltage Drop, the monthly “industrial danceclub” concert series, effectively functions as press releases for new Ratskin releases, with a smattering of unaffiliated but much-revered artists as well. In the coming weeks, Daddona announced with a rare sense of cheer, he’d be hosting “five fucking incredible friends, out-of-this-world talented, like nothing else out there.” Tyler Holmes debuts his new cassette album &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ratskin.org/releases/rsr067.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Invisible Island&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the Legionnaire Saloon on September 30th. On October 15th, the not-even-remotely-secret Oakland Secret Gallery will host a quadruple release party with Maya Songbird, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ratskinrecords.bandcamp.com/album/slanted-square-three-sides-released-oct-15&quot;&gt;Slanted Square&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayexpress.com/oakland/best-tape-loop-manipulator/BestOf?oid=1921316&quot;&gt;Loachfillet&lt;/a&gt;, and Mike’s own industrial noise project Malocculsion.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mike lives in the McClymonds neighborhood of West Oakland, a triangular area bounded by San Pablo, Peralta, and West Grand Avenues. He shares a two-story loft with three roommates, each bedroom separated from shared space with curtains. Still, the oasis of a living room emerges in the middle of several shelves of records and tapes, which stored both his personal collection and his business. The room itself speaks to his endless productivity: next to his desk, there are approximately eight cassette-dubbing machines stacked on top of each other, forming a chain through which he is constantly recording copies of his releases.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&quot;I'll put in tapes while I'm cooking dinner, cleaning the house, sitting around, or doing chores. I can pretty much work on the label whenever I'm home,&quot; he remarked. His living room, in other words, is a small pressing plant.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;He took out a record and started spinning some shrieking black metal from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gzJecjdXXfI&quot;&gt;Gorgoroth&lt;/a&gt;, which made his visibly stressed and jittery roommate sigh and exclaim, “this is such calming music. I feel so relaxed now. Thanks, guys.” A deeply unusual atmosphere of sound came to life in the living room, the trickle of rapidfire trap-beats from the window curdling through the bass-heavy metal riffs.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/mcclymonds.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sunset in West Oakland's McClymonds neighborhood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For its quiet suburban appearance, McClymonds feels much more dense and vibrant than comparably whiter, wealthier districts such as Rockridge. Mike’s neighbors, almost all black, were out on the sidewalks, blasting music out of their cars, or otherwise soaking up the sunset. For all the groceries and amenities readily available in more upscale suburbs, West Oakland’s food desert has the culture and mixed-use density those suburbs lack. Large warehouses adjoin single-family (yet often multi-household) homes, apartments, and parks. Underground music and art spaces flourish in the area’s once-cheap industrial spaces, many landlords being eager to cash in by turning a blind eye to the legal grey area of non-residential zoning.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Artists move to industrial spaces where they can be loud late at night,” former McClymonds resident Max Allstadt told me once. “You can divvy up the square footage with more roommates to split the rent, and neighbors don’t freak out if you cut sheet metal with a saw at 3 A.M.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The neighborhood is both one of opportunity, drawing flocks of migrants for decades, and also limited opportunity, serving as an obvious reference point when discussing the region’s crippling social inequality. Daddona himself moved here for opportunity, from rural Connecticut. “I lived in a tiny town with nothing going on, so one day I just packed up and left. There were other reasons too, that I don’t want to discuss.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;West Oakland became a primarily black neighborhood after postwar industry boomed, attracting floods of African American migrants seeking work in the Port of Oakland and nearby manufacturing hubs. While segregationist &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2014/05/the-racist-housing-policy-that-made-your-neighborhood/371439/&quot;&gt;redlining&lt;/a&gt; prevented Oakland’s black population from moving north, a period of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=The_Rise_and_Fall_of_Seventh_Street_in_Oakland&quot;&gt;“urban renewal”&lt;/a&gt; decimated the community’s economic stability. First, the construction of the 980 freeway isolated West Oakland from the rest of the city, and then entire city blocks were razed for the construction of BART and the massive Post Office. Very little is left of the once-flourishing 7th Street Business District, though traces of the subsequent resistance by the Black Panthers remain in plain sight, primarily in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://qilombo.org/&quot;&gt;Qilombo&lt;/a&gt; community center.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It’s apparent, even in the most insular of the micro-subcultures that inevitably blossom here, that the demographic transition known as “gentrification” occurred before, or concurrently with, the inflation of real estate prices better known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.law.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/stanford-law-policy-review/print/2014/01/mangin_25_stan._l._poly_rev_91.pdf&quot;&gt;“reverse filtering.”&lt;/a&gt; That is, even the most recent transplant, in a warehouse party full of white college-aged carpetbaggers, knows how to allude to some nostalgic Shangri-La past that is rapidly receding.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I thought I had prepared with my most trustworthy stock question for an artist, intended to give a platform for a long, descriptive history of their work. “Did you think when you started this label, you would have expected to be where you are now?” Boom. Perfect. Surely this would prompt him to tell the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;His candor disarmed my clumsy cleverness. “Mm, yeah, I didn’t really think anything, really. We just did it.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Okay, so that didn’t work,” I admitted after an awkward pause. “Just tell me how you started, and, you know, we can go from there.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The “we” refers to his former band Sabreteeth, which technically started the imprint on their own with only minimal input from Daddona at first. They sound somewhat like a more punk-sounding forefather to current band Coral Remains (nee Styrofoam Sanchez), all featuring macabre visuals, psychedelic costumes, and pummeling industrial drumbeats. Coral Remains, a trio of Mike, his roommate JSon, and former roommate Ryan King (a.k.a. Bonus Beast), are notorious for littering the floors of venues across the country with audience-involved Styrofoam-smashing antics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=4123571802/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ratskinrecords.bandcamp.com/album/styrofoam-sanchez-empire-underwater&quot;&gt;STYROFOAM SANCHEZ &amp;quot;Empire Underwater&amp;quot; by Ratskin Records&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ratskin.org/thirteenseconds.html&quot;&gt;Triskaidekaphobia&lt;/a&gt; compilation CD in 2008, the imprint expanded into releasing other artists' material: specifically, 215 artists, each presenting a 13-second song. By the time Styrofoam Sanchez released their monolithic LP/DVD/comic book album &lt;em&gt;Empire Underwater&lt;/em&gt; in 2014, Ratskin was a very different beast. Mike had long since taken over operations after the first handful of Sabreteeth recordings, and his visual art on most album covers was more prevalent than any music he recorded himself.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It was never intentional, Mike insists. It’s as though he didn’t think about what he was doing until he was well into the process of running a record label. “It was just a fun, kind of absurd project. After that, it was mostly other people’s music. It just sort of happened. All of a sudden, I realized, ‘wow, so many of my friends are so talented and so hardworking.’ It just made sense to help them out as much as I could.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What strikes me so often about artists who move to the Bay Area, just as much as those who were born here, is their instinctive yet consciously irrational drive to do so. They just do what they do because they have to, full stop.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To Mike, it’s even “therapeutic.” It occurs to me if so many people are willing to take a financial loss to find purpose through the help of therapy, it seems odd that it is far less taboo to criticize the logical utility of art than that of psychological counseling. Perhaps we recognize it would be rude to interrogate those who seek “treatment” to get “better,” whereas artists and audiences both know that their madness is the treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/ratskin5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent Ratskin releases from Black Dog, Coral Remains, and Black Spirituals, respectively. (courtesy: M. Daddona)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But just to humor myself, I press a bit more on the question of the label’s financial stability. For example, how do his choices of material affect his overhead costs? “There are some things I like about tapes—mostly that they’ll probably last a lot longer than the CD-R….In a lot of ways, I feel like it doesn’t really matter. If we could afford to put everything out on vinyl, we would, but we’re not at that point. Hopefully one day.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Every question from then on became a springboard for some optimistic goal. Mike alludes to upcoming efforts to expand into book projects, one-time art installations, and whatever else he might find worth sharing. The label co-presents the aforementioned monthly DJ night, “Voltage Drop,” at the Legionnaire Saloon in Uptown Oakland. Each party typically features one or two future or upcoming Ratskin-affiliated artists, with a collection of free physical mixtapes available for early bird arrivals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The label itself has ballooned into a planned twenty-album backlog. “There are ten upcoming releases I have confirmed and can announce, and there’s ten I can’t mention just yet.” For a well-established label with multiple paid employees, this isn’t a stretch; for a one-man operation that intentionally takes a loss (with the eventual goal of breaking even, I’m assured), it is an insane amount.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Given this surge in productivity, I questioned an earlier remark he made that the label was guided by an effort to give voice to those who might not always feel comfortable or confident. Had he ever had to actively convince someone to publicize their music?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Well, look—you can’t book everyone, and you can’t release everyone. The label is there as a resource for artists, document works I think should be documented, and push people to do projects they might not feel fit in anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“People like to keep all these secrets in music, and guard their craft, because if you figure out their trick, then they worry that their whole shtick will break down.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“You mean, everyone will realize it’s not that hard, and they can do it too?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, exactly. And that’s good. I mean, I love punk and I love conceptual art, but I also hate punk and I hate conceptual art. I’m just trying to take what’s good out of different artistic movements and…well, archiving is what I’m doing, not even documenting.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At first it doesn’t occur to me what the difference could possibly be. Again, the intentional-yet-intuitive idea comes to mind. Does documenting mean you plan to do it, while archiving is more of a rote act?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In Ratskin’s case, the “archiving” in itself stands out as a deliberate art. At times, he says, it has merely been a matter of a prolific live performer not having access to recording equipment. He calls subsequent relationships a “collaboration,” and it’s in many ways an entry into a deeply connected musical family. Artists on the Ratskin catalogue often cross-promote, tour together, share the stage on local bills&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On the same desk where he cuts covers for new tapes, he has two final remaining copies of a 10-cassette box set, sealed with a piezoelectric contact microphone, with twenty artists each splitting a side of a five-minute tape. He’s almost done making copies for the final box.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/local-profiles-oaklands-ratskin-records/ratskin4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;10-cassette box set sealed with a contact mic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The constant work-in-progress, on a lizard-brain good-vibes level, simply feels like a much better deal for both the consumer and the producer, even though he makes a net loss at press time. An economist reading this might shake their head in disbelief—or maybe it’s just aspiring artists’ concerned parents.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To put it into economic terms, these artists tend not to care if they make a return on capital investments. The transaction itself is the profit. Monetary profit is a far lower priority than the exponentially growing payoff of helping other artists along their way.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There are some artists for whom he is confident he has done his part to help, and have moved beyond any semblance of “needing him.” Oakland’s blistering, explosive free-jazz duo Black Spirituals was recently praised by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/09/24/arts/music/review-black-spirituals-a-duo-that-defies-categories.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rolling Stone&lt;/em&gt;, the latter giving a nod to their Ratskin tape &lt;em&gt;Black Interiors&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Everyone should have their own label,” he adds. “All of the bands I was inspired by did just hack-job shows, driving for hours to play to twenty people… If every Ratskin artist could tour and get paid for every show they played, that would be a great thing. I’m just lucky to have so many talented friends, and that’s the only reason I do the label. All the real work is done by the artist, and I’m just here to contextualize this.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though he is modest about this contextualizing, it’s far from insignificant.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In person, Mike is never shy about Ratskin’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imposemagazine.com/music/ratskin&quot;&gt;principled efforts&lt;/a&gt; to support marginalized communities. He was reticent at first, in light of my newfound status as “the press” asking questions, to go into detail again. It didn’t take long for him to open up on the subject, though, given that Ratskin explicitly foregrounds black and brown voices in the music scene, many being native to the Bay Area.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It was inevitable, really, two straight white dudes sitting on a couch listening to metal, while the sounds of his black neighborhood and their very different music choices poured in constantly. “Sure, I’m a gentrifier,” he says when I bring up the subject. “I mean, look around you. Of course I’m part of this neighborhood changing. But also, these are my friends. We talk to each other, we hang out, share things, like regular human beings. All it takes to not be a bad gentrifier is, you know, just don’t be a fucking idiot.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Indeed, before the interview began in earnest, we passed around a blunt with some neighbors and shot the shit. We were a bit sluggish and dazed when the interview started. After half an hour or so, it didn’t feel right to close ourselves off like that, so we turned off the music and recording equipment, opened the front door, and rolled another one.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It should be easy to not be a “fucking idiot,” but that doesn’t mean it’s not hard work sometimes. The proof is in the bags under Mike’s eyes. On days when he does contracting work, he gets up before 5 A.M. to cross the Bay Bridge before rush-hour traffic. The irregular hours make it easier to be involved in nightlife on the weekends, and tour across the country for a few weeks at a time. When he’s home, he’s dubbing tapes, booking concerts, or recording music.  The spools keep spinning the tape, spinning over and over to stave off the madness.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-candidates-talk-quality-of-life-and-regional-growth-in-forum/">
    <title type="text">Palo Alto Candidates Talk Quality of Life and Regional Growth in Forum</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:bb00e3af-03fd-3a8f-a605-3b1a82739f99</id>
    <updated>2016-09-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-candidates-talk-quality-of-life-and-regional-growth-in-forum/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Palo Alto is the epicenter of entrepreneurship in Silicon Valley, but it has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/opinion/editorials/article/Palo-Alto-decides-it-has-too-much-of-a-good-thing-9200819.php&quot;&gt;too many jobs&lt;/a&gt;. That at least is the tenor of the Peninsula city’s civic mood, where a moratorium on new office development coincides with fierce &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/tweets-from-the-front-palo-alto-city-council-coverage/&quot;&gt;controversy over apartments&lt;/a&gt; near Caltrain with less than one parking spot per resident.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Eleven candidates for city council in Palo Alto gathered in the main chambers of city hall for a moderated &lt;a href=&quot;ttp://www.paloaltoonline.com/news/2016/09/16/council-candidates-make-their-pitches-at-palo-alto-forum&quot;&gt;forum&lt;/a&gt; on September 14th, in which infrastructure and fiscal responsibility dominated what generally amounted to a contest of optimism. Liz Kniss is the only sitting councilmember seeking reelection in this cycle. Young or old, incumbent or newcomer, each couched their plans for addressing Palo Alto’s housing and transportation woes in terms of enduring, positive progress.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Palo Alto native and sitting Planning and Transportation Commission chair &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.votefine.com/&quot;&gt;Adrian Fine&lt;/a&gt; spoke of aiming for a “21st century approach” to transportation, and others joined in his suggestion that Autonomous Vehicles may soon change the paradigm around transportation planning, parking, and traffic. (Fine, a native of Palo Alto, studied city planning at the University of Pennsylvania.) Leonard Ely III, an older candidate, made the further suggestion that the entire Bay Area should consider merging its transit agencies to reduce the cost per person.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Palo Alto’s ratio of jobs to housing is estimated at 3-to-1, with effectively half of its peak population commuting in and out from increasingly distant places. The city’s housing shortage recently came under national scrutiny after Planning Commissioner Kate Downing publicly announce her departure, opting to raise her high-earning dual-income family in the relatively more affordable city of Santa Cruz.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gregtanaka&quot;&gt;Greg Tanaka&lt;/a&gt;, former chair of the Planning Commission, was keen on connecting transportation with the region’s soaring housing costs. He spoke of a need to “minimize impacts through smaller units” and encourage “multiple transportation modalities,” sharing optimistic goals in spite of his hardships as a small business owner struggling to retain rent-burdened employees.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Incumbent Liz Kniss joined others in the forum expressing more caution over the city’s growing pains. “I fear driving down the street one day and seeing only multi-million dollar homes,” Kniss lamented, urging attendees to support more affordable alternatives. (Palo Alto’s median &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zillow.com/palo-alto-ca/home-values/&quot;&gt;home price&lt;/a&gt; is currently $2.4 million.) Referring to the imbalance of office space and housing in the city, Stewart Carl added, “We cannot possibly build that much living space in Palo Alto without compromising our quality of life.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Greer Stone, one of the younger candidates, was quick to parry with positive policy goals of greater housing density and improved public transit. “Let’s build housing near jobs,” he said straightforwardly at one point, “to get people out of their cars.” This idea received pushback from Lydia Kou, who called for the construction of more parking garages along with increased VTA bus service.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Curiously, Stone’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.greerstone.com/&quot;&gt;campaign website&lt;/a&gt; echoes the concerns of several older candidates. His platform reads, in part: “Overdevelopment threatens the continuing success of our schools, impact on traffic, parkland preservation, pollution, parking, and retail. We must balance the need for additional housing with the concerns of the surrounding neighborhoods and the collateral impact on schools, traffic, pollution, and public services.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Current Planning Commission chair Adrian Fine took the most risk in balancing optimistic policy with cold, hard reality. “I grew up in a compassionate place,” he said when the candidates recounted their favorite aspects of living in Palo Alto. “As our teachers, our nurses, our firefighters find it increasingly hard to live here, we risk losing some of that compassion.” Other candidates were quick to pounce on the negative angle, insisting that their community still retained plenty of compassion.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When I reached Fine by phone, my first question was simply a clarification: what did he mean by compassion?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“My compassionate community was a place where I’d clean my neighbor’s car, or where the man down the street had been my mother’s professor. As we’ve seen a reduction in our income, age, and cultural diversity, while becoming a global center for technological innovation, we’ve lost a lot of that.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Fine constantly alluded to a bedrock of principles underlying his campaign, independent of specific policies. “I don’t care about building or not building—the issue is the community values that we share. Issues like diversity, creativity, the environment. If we believe in those, there are some choices we need to make. In order to support a diverse community, we need to have more housing options and we need to invest in transportation.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;His answers came as a rapidfire list of concrete ideas bound tightly to platitudes, like hydrogen bonding with oxygen. The conversation became increasingly candid after that.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We need to make sure that future generations can live out and foster those values,” he reiterated. “I graduated with slightly under 400 students from my high school twelve years ago. There’s now about five of us left in Palo Alto. That’s not normal. So it’s not really about the buildings—that’s the last step, actually.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;What, then, did he see as the first steps?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“In Palo Alto, we built the Oregon Expressway, and we have huge parking lots. Now we’re coming to the conclusion that, gosh, we built our city for cars, there’s a huge environmental and social cost to that. We’re out of space for roads in Palo Alto. Do we use existing infill space for cars or for people?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“My fiancée and I don’t own cars,” he added, “and many of our friends don’t. We take Uber or Lyft, we bike, we walk, we take Caltrain. With ridesharing, autonomous cars, and electric vehicles, that’s progress that’s happening &lt;em&gt;right here&lt;/em&gt;. I think we should be a leader in that.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I followed up by asking if people were ever shocked to discover that he lived in Palo Alto without a car. As a former carless resident of the area myself, I couldn’t imagine it being easy. “Sometimes—well, no, not really,” Fine said. “I live a five-minute bike ride from the train, from groceries. To some of our seniors, that may not be an option—in some neighborhoods they have less commercial access, which is something we need to work on. In Palo Alto, 8% of trips are done by bike. That’s pretty big—after Davis, Portland, maybe Boulder. Palo Alto is very flat, with great bike boulevards. And there’s Stanford, of course.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Stanford can circumvent local government, and has much broader control over its land. Absent those privileges, Fine sees Palo Alto at a crossroads where it must choose regional cooperation. “The Bay Area is 110 cities, nine counties, 24 transit systems—that’s a really hard region to work in. Given our reality, we’ve got to work overtime.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Many communities are envious of Palo Alto’s success, and our quality of life,” he continued. “I believe we need to maintain that and improve it—in some cases that means change. I’m a proponent of managing change effectively.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In our interview, Fine was passionate and animated, yet spoke with the measured cadence of a well-rehearsed veteran politician. Optimism and tempered outrage strike a careful balance in the city’s political atmosphere. The next forum will be held on September 29th, hosted by neighborhood groups, also in council chambers.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo courtesy of Gary Fine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/foster-city-considers-68-units-in-commercial-zone/">
    <title type="text">Foster City Considers 68 Units in Commercial Zone</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:0c0659f6-86d3-33db-bef3-bc0816d889ff</id>
    <updated>2016-09-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/foster-city-considers-68-units-in-commercial-zone/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Foster City managed to go from a landfill to a flourishing planned suburb in less than a century. Last night, the city’s Planning Commission debated how exactly that trajectory might continue on a parcel known as “Phase C” on Triton Drive. Developers at the Sares Regis Group hope to receive a rezoning for the area, largely allotted for office space, in order to provide &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/68-units-proposed-in-foster-city/&quot;&gt;68 townhomes&lt;/a&gt; with a shuttle service to the nearby Caltrain station.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The most vocal members of the Commission voiced concern that rezoning for more housing could slow the city’s commercial growth. The parcel is currently only zoned for 17 residential units. Commissioner and former mayor Richard Wykoff led the charge, arguing that there was “a conflict between downsizing the commercial space and the economic plan.” He strongly favored a compromise suggested by the Planning Department to build a hotel there instead, though no such project has been proposed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/foster-city-considers-68-units-in-commercial-zone/phasecfc.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infographic detailing predicted benefits of the new development (courtesy: Sares Regis)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While some local business owners did express concern over the loss of commercial space, the majority of local residents generally supported the additional townhomes. Commissioner Noemi Avram seemed more receptive to these views, noting that Foster City is the only locality on the Peninsula to require 20% Below Market Rate units on new construction. Foster City currently only has seven such units, so Phase C would effectively triple the amount of permanently affordable housing within city limits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Francisco housing advocate Laura Clark, founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.growsanfrancisco.org/&quot;&gt;Grow SF&lt;/a&gt;, commented on what she perceived as a markedly tone-deaf atmosphere at the meeting. “The Commission, most prominently voiced by Wykoff, showed no concern for the fact that they are only 68% of the way toward meeting the minimum of their &lt;a href=&quot;http://fostercity.org/departmentsanddivisions/communitydevelopment/Features/upload/HOUSING-ELEMENT-ADOPTED-2-2-2015.pdf&quot;&gt;regional housing obligation&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night's meeting was a study session, so no legislative action was taken.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/as-millennium-tower-sinks-blame-game-ensues/">
    <title type="text">As Millennium Tower Sinks, Blame Game Ensues</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:cecf4c42-ee4e-33ad-a603-ef1a42734035</id>
    <updated>2016-09-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/as-millennium-tower-sinks-blame-game-ensues/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Once intended to be Downtown San Francisco’s most appealing luxury condominium high-rise, the Millennium Tower has instead become a convenient symbol of the tragicomic hubris underlying the city’s real estate market. But whose hubris?—This has become the subject of heated debate, embroiling an ever-growing cast of characters in all sectors. According to those involved, who exactly bears the blame for the tower’s unstable property values and physical structure, sinking three inches at its base and sixteen inches on the top floor, is everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Aaron Peskin has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/supervisor-peskin-blames-faulty-millennium-tower-political-interference-plans-lead-investigation/&quot;&gt;called for an investigation&lt;/a&gt; into the tower’s faulty foundation, suggesting that “political interference” may have rushed the building’s approval in 2009. Condo owners in the building launched a &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/class-action-lawsuit-filed-against-millennium-tower-developer/&quot;&gt;class-action lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; alleging negligence on the part of developer Millennium Properties as well as the Transbay Joint Powers Association, which built its new terminal into the foundation of the tower. Both plaintiffs in the suit have blamed each other in decidedly undiplomatic press statements this week.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Transbay agency released a preemptive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CtVteemLin4&quot;&gt;“I didn’t do it”&lt;/a&gt; statement &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/9/14/12919764/millennium-tower-sinking-transbay-powers&quot;&gt;insisting&lt;/a&gt; that after Millennium Properties agreed to donate some of the tower’s space in exchange for “monitoring” its movement, they did exactly that. The TJPA argues that their repeated warnings before their terminal project broke ground went unheeded by the condo developer.  The agency not only shifted the blame for failing to warn owners back to the property managers, it also noted that they “anticipated” being blamed by Millennium Properties.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The agency additionally argued that they had offered an agreement to take on some of Millennium’s liability in exchange for joint record-keeping, which the developer declined. MP vociferously denied that this ever happened.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;MP was quick to fire back, insisting that the building had not sunk beyond “revised predicted ranges” until Transbay began building its adjacent foundation. (Though the developer insists their predicted ranges were safe, they did not specify what they were.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Most alarming among their denials of responsibility, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/9/15/12930402/millennium-towner-sinking-foundation-buildings&quot;&gt;Curbed SF&lt;/a&gt; points out, is the Millennium Partners spokesperson’s comments about other buildings that, like their tower, did not drill their foundations into bedrock. The St. Regis Hotel, SFMOMA, the Embarcadero Center, and many prominent hotels also &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/98836506&quot;&gt;rest on the layer of sand&lt;/a&gt; known as the Colma Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Wherever the blame may ultimately fall, all parties involved can expect significant fallout from legal and legislative actions.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/fearing-rent-increase-child-care-center-buys-building/">
    <title type="text">Fearing Rent Increase, Child Care Center Buys Building</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:348b77fb-16f2-3cb4-b067-ad2f265165cf</id>
    <updated>2016-09-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/fearing-rent-increase-child-care-center-buys-building/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last year had some nail-biter moments for the Mission Child Care Consortium. Facing an end of its lease in 2018, the city’s largest non-profit childcare agency &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/low-income-mission-child-care-center-worries-about-losing-lease/&quot;&gt;expected&lt;/a&gt; a rent hike of nearly double what they were paying, from $28,000 to $50,000 per year, at its current site of 4750 Mission Street. Despite arguments to the contrary from the owner at the time, who insisted he had no intention of disenfranchising the non-profit, Mission Child Care successfully raised $5.6 million to purchase the building.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Consortium is situated between the Balboa Park and Excelsior neighborhoods, and is walking distance from the Balboa Park BART station. The 14 bus, with a stop one block north of the building, runs from Daly City all the way to Embarcadero Station.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ahsha Safaí, who is running to replace John Avalos as District 11 Supervisor, announced the transfer of 4750 Mission Street in a press release. “This victory is the result of 8 years of hard work and another 2 years of community organizing,” he writes, noting that the facility will continue to provide subsidized care for 224 children of working families.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Safaí, a resident of the Excelsior, supported an earlier attempt to purchase the property nine years ago, when he served as deputy director of the Mayor’s Office of Community Development. He also led a signature-gathering campaign in 2015 to raise support for a loan to finance the sale.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/is-a-nonprofit-developer-laundering-money-to-local-campaigns/">
    <title type="text">Is a Non-Profit Developer Laundering Money to Local Campaigns?</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a1f8434c-9038-36c9-9ef5-ef741afb919a</id>
    <updated>2016-09-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/is-a-nonprofit-developer-laundering-money-to-local-campaigns/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This article is the result of our being unable to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vETxuL7Ij3Q&quot;&gt;“follow the money.”&lt;/a&gt; Yerba Buena Neighborhood Consortium, LLC has been a major donor in recent San Francisco elections, most notably the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/prop-c-approval-enables-legislators-set-affordable-housing-requirements/&quot;&gt;Yes On C&lt;/a&gt; committee. John Elberling, Director of affordable housing developer TODCO Group, LLC, founded both LLCs on the same day in 2013. TODCO &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.todco.org/our-housing/&quot;&gt;owns&lt;/a&gt; several senior housing projects, SROs, and Leland Apartments (pictured above), a multifamily apartment complex for disabled residents with Section 8 vouchers.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While TODCO receives income from government grants and property management, YBNC has no discernible source of income. Instead, it appears in a variety of campaign disclosure forms, effectively concealing the true source of donations.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trauss.com/library/EthicsComplaintAgainstElberlingYBNC.pdf&quot;&gt;Ethics Complaint&lt;/a&gt; filed by Oakland resident and &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; co-owner Sonja Trauss alleges “egregious violations” of campaign finance laws. Trauss hopes the complaint will result in an audit which will reveal the source of YBNC’s revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Shell corporations are not a new trend in political campaigns. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/sep/14/corporate-cash-john-doe-files-scott-walker-wisconsin&quot;&gt;Last year&lt;/a&gt;, Wisconsin Governor Scott Walker was investigated for taking potentially criminal donations from a third-party lobbying group funneling money from large corporate donors. Sources close to the &lt;em&gt;Metro Observer&lt;/em&gt; claim that Elberling adopted the same strategy for funding ballot measure campaigns, potentially from money he earned from refinancing TODCO’s low-income housing projects.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Campaign literature for ballot measures is a common way for local political groups to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fec.gov/finance/disclosure/electioneering.shtml&quot;&gt;“electioneer”&lt;/a&gt; for candidates as endorsers, increasing their name recognition while not counting toward the particular candidate’s legal spending limits. In forms filed by the “Affordable Housing for All, Yes on Proposition C” Committee, Yerba Buena Neighborhood Consortium donated a total of $125,000 between January and June of this year. After an initial contribution of $35,000, the Committee added “sponsored by Yerba Buena Consortium” to its name on their filings. Several endorsement mailers sent out on behalf of the Prop C campaign, included in the complaint, provided Supervisor Jane Kim with free publicity.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Although the Yerba Buena Consortium is incorporated as a Limited Liability Corporation, it lists its business practices on incorporation documents as “Nonprofit Community Advocates for San Francisco’s South of Market Neighborhood.” This is possibly an anachronism leftover from YNBC’s earlier incarnation as a tax-exempt 501(c)3 of the same name, which lost its tax-exempt status in 2011 after the IRS found they were negligent in their filings. By law, a registered 501(c)3 is not allowed to spend any money on political campaigns. The relationship between the LLC and 501(c)3 entities remains unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/302-units-proposed-in-el-cerrito/">
    <title type="text">302 Units Proposed in El Cerrito</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:f6c570d5-4a03-315a-9aed-72df773e7c47</id>
    <updated>2016-09-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/302-units-proposed-in-el-cerrito/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The East Bay suburb primarily known as the hometown of classic rockers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Aae_RHRptRg&quot;&gt;Creedence Clearwater Revival&lt;/a&gt; may soon get a taste of multifamily urban housing. Oakland developer Holliday Development and the non-profit BRIDGE Housing have partnered in a plan for two apartment buildings near the El Cerrito Del Norte BART station adjoined by a pathway: a five-story 234-unit market-rate building, and a 4-story, 68-unit building of price-indexed Below Market Rentals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The site of the proposal, known as the Mayfair Block, is bounded by Kearney Street and San Pablo Avenue on the east and west, and Cutting Boulevard and Hill Street to the north and south. The parcel was formerly occupied by AK’s Food Corner. One building will feature 10,000 square feet of ground floor retail on the northern side facing Cutting Boulevard.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/302-units-proposed-in-el-cerrito/mayfairmap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Map of the Mayfair Block adjacent to the El Cerrito Del Norte BART station (source: Google Maps)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a special joint session of the Planning Commission and Design Review Board, the project received overall praise from city officials and the public, despite many proposed revisions. The &lt;em&gt;East Bay Times&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbaytimes.com/2016/09/12/el-cerrito-scrutinizes-del-norte-area-mixed-use-proposal/&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that some community members described the separation of market-rate and affordable housing as “disappointing,” additionally lamenting the presence of “too much space for parking.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;BRIDGE Housing made note of a completed project built at the Pleasant Hill BART station in a partnership with Holliday. The non-profit agency is also &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bridgehousing.com/what-we-do/macarthur-station&quot;&gt;developing&lt;/a&gt; a mixed-use apartment complex next to the MacArthur BART station in Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The city of El Cerrito recently rezoned the area for higher-density development near transit under the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.el-cerrito.org/index.aspx?nid=396&quot;&gt;San Pablo Avenue Specific Plan&lt;/a&gt;, adopted in December 2014. The Planning Department designed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Form-based_code&quot;&gt;Form-Based Code&lt;/a&gt;, as well as pedestrian-friendly transit goals, “[i]n order to increase accessibility and livability while increasing land use intensity.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/">
    <title type="text">Affordable Housing Requirement Has Reduced Production of Affordable Housing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:72175746-36e3-3066-802f-fb38bae8df26</id>
    <updated>2016-09-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;An analysis conducted by the &lt;em&gt;Metropolitan Observer&lt;/em&gt; shows that since &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfgov.org/elections/sites/default/files/Documents/candidates/IHR%20Legal%20Text.pdf&quot;&gt;Proposition C&lt;/a&gt; passed June 6 2016, applications to build new housing have dropped by 58% overall, and applications to build Below Market Rate (BMR), subsidized housing have dropped 20%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/propc1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We looked at the Preliminary Project Applications (PPAs) submitted to the SF Planning Department from June 2016 to September 2016 (post-Prop C passing) and compared those to the PPAs submitted during the same time last year, June 2015 and September 2015, to assess the effect of Prop C.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There were 18 residential projects representing 3,000 housing units proposed between June 2015 and the first week of September 2015. Applying the then-12% BMR requirement to the total number of units proposed results in 350 below market rate units proposed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/over-three-months-prop-c-has-reduced-production-of-affordable-housing/propc2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;12 residential projects representing 1,250 housing units were proposed during the same time period in 2016 - a drop of more than half from the prior year. The total number of affordable units these projects would contribute, is 289 affordable units - 61 fewer affordable units than what was produced in the same time period last year&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot; id=&quot;fnref-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, or a reduction of 20%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Proposition C was a ballot measure passed last June increasing the affordable housing requirement for new construction to 25% of total units. Some skeptics, including Mayor Ed Lee, argued that 25% was arbitrary. Opponents also feared that an excessively high BMR requirement would reduce the overall amount of housing proposed, and thereby reduce the amount of BMR units produced.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Proponents, led by Supervisors Jane Kim and Aaron Peskin, insisted that the measure was necessary to address the city's affordability crisis. The Supervisors further promised that they would be open to amending the requirement if analyses showed the requirement was in fact too high. Our analysis joins that of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/08/san-francisco-affordable-homes-requirement-prop-c.html&quot;&gt;City Controller's office&lt;/a&gt; in showing that the anticipated net production of affordable housing has decreased since this legislation went into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Notably, while the affordable units anticipated from the July and August of 2016 proposals, post-Prop C, exceeds those same months in 2015, approximately 80% of the post-Prop C affordable units would come from just two large projects. That means if those two projects wind up not being approved, the vast majority of potential affordable units go away - down to about 50 total affordable units. So while, for a given project, Prop C might increase the number of affordable units, it still decreases the &lt;em&gt;overall number of large projects&lt;/em&gt; that produce affordable housing at all, concentrating the risk in just a small number of projects&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref-1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/tweets-from-the-front-palo-alto-city-council-coverage/">
    <title type="text">Tweets from the Front: Palo Alto City Council Coverage</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:60c28653-6a17-3605-8414-307f47b53eaa</id>
    <updated>2016-09-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/tweets-from-the-front-palo-alto-city-council-coverage/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night, the Palo Alto City Council conducted a study session reviewing an upcoming proposal for 60 residential units to replace a vacant bus parking lot on El Camino Real, near the California Avenue Caltrain station. We sent our special Peninsula correspondent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.markmollineaux.com/&quot;&gt;Mark Mollineaux&lt;/a&gt; to cover the meeting via Twitter, and have collected important highlights in a Storify feed below. (Readers curious enough to watch the meeting in its entirety can do so &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/5ZxwXIyYuIo?t=9m55s&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Local developer Windy Hill Property Ventures sought input from the council before making a formal proposal to submit to the Planning Department. The parcel at 2755 El Camino Real is currently zoned for Public Facilities, meaning that any development intended for anything other than city use must seek approval for a zoning variance. This project comes after a proposal by Hayes Group Architects for two stories of housing above ground-floor retail was rejected on the grounds that it did not provide enough housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Although complaints were largely procedural in nature, Vice Mayor Greg Scharff underscored the neighbor’s concerns that the project would add to traffic congestion. Under the current proposal, only 45 parking spaces would be provided for 60 units (all studios or one-bedroom apartments), which is below the 1:1 parking ratio required by local zoning. At one point, Scharff suggested to Windy Hill representatives that they may be asked to pay a fee in lieu of the additional parking spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mayor Patrick Burt, however, rebuffed many criticisms pertaining to car use,  encouraging council and the public to consider vast improvements in autonomous vehicle technology, Caltrain rail electrification, and pedestrian-friendly infrastructure. Councilmember Cory Wolbach joined in urging the council to support the project, adding that he believed there was already too much parking proposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;storify&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/palo-alto-city-council-9-12-16/embed?border=false&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;750&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/palo-alto-city-council-9-12-16.js?border=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;noscript&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;//storify.com/MetroObserver/palo-alto-city-council-9-12-16&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;View the story &quot;Palo Alto City Council, 9/12/16&quot; on Storify&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/midtown-terrace-seeks-downzoning-to-preserve-country-living-density/">
    <title type="text">Midtown Terrace Seeks Downzoning to Preserve &quot;Country Living&quot; Density</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:0ffb983d-fc64-3f4b-8a5d-c3cc6d82318e</id>
    <updated>2016-09-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/midtown-terrace-seeks-downzoning-to-preserve-country-living-density/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The neighborhood’s motto &lt;a href=&quot;http://midtownterrace.org/zoning.php&quot;&gt;reads&lt;/a&gt;: “Country living in the heart of San Francisco.” Though the median home price is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zillow.com/midtown-terrace-san-francisco-ca/home-values/&quot;&gt;$1.1 million&lt;/a&gt; in the suburban enclave just south of Twin Peaks, local historian Rex Bell &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=Brief_History_of_Midtown_Terrace&quot;&gt;describes&lt;/a&gt; it as “still a solidly middle-class neighborhood.” Whatever the subjective perceptions may be, organized neighbors are determined to ensure that city law enforces “country living” by amending the local zoning code.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Midtown Terrace homeowners have petitioned the San Francisco Board of Supervisors to amend the area’s zoning &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf-planning.org/sites/default/files/FileCenter/Documents/5358-Residential%20Standards%20Summary%20Table.pdf&quot;&gt;from RH-1 to RH-1 (D)&lt;/a&gt;. Though the differences initially seem subtle and benign, this zoning amendment could effectively render much of the existing built environment illegal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;RH-1(D) zoning prohibits any more than a single dwelling unit per lot, regardless of size. Under current zoning, a 4,500 square foot lot in Midtown Terrace could have at most two units (in other words, a duplex); several lots greater than 7,000 square feet in size allow a triplex.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of District 7, the supervisorial district that encompasses Midtown Terrace, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://localwiki.org/sf/RH-1%28D%29_Zones&quot;&gt;already zoned&lt;/a&gt; RH1(D). If the petition is approved, the new zoning would prohibit anything denser than a single-family home, anywhere in Midtown Terrace. This is particularly significant because there would no longer be density exemptions for Accessory Dwelling Units (ADUs), colloquially known as “backyard cottages”—other single-family neighborhoods in the Twin Peaks and Telegraph Hill Districts retain this exemption. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redfin.com/CA/San-Francisco/91-Aquavista-Way-94131/home/1637155&quot;&gt;Currently unpermitted ADUs&lt;/a&gt; in Midtown Terrace would effectively be illegal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Aside from density restrictions, RH-1(D) zoning also adds restrictions to single-family residences that can be built in the neighborhood. Rather than building to the edge of the property line, as the current zoning allows, new construction would be required to include side yards. It would also apply a minimum lot size of 4,000 square feet, although this would not retroactively apply to the majority of houses in Midtown Terrace, where the zoning currently allows a minimum lot size of 2,500 square feet.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The “D” in RH-1(D) stands for “detached dwellings,” since it bans townhome-style houses with no side yard separation. The Board of Supervisors’ Land Use and Transportation Commission will be considering the residents’ petition on Monday, September 19.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing-sep-9-san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing/">
    <title type="text">San Francisco Finds Unlikely Partnership in Ford for City Bike Sharing</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:76cee8a3-73c7-3250-b49e-e064e517a9b4</id>
    <updated>2016-09-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing-sep-9-san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://media.ford.com/content/fordmedia/fna/us/en/news/2016/09/09/ford-partnering-with-global-cities-on-new-transportation--chario.html&quot;&gt;press release today&lt;/a&gt;, Ford announced that it would be partnering with a number of global cities on new transportation initiatives, starting with our own San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The automaker giant - an unlikely advocate for transit - will be sponsoring the Bay Area’s bike share program, expanding the fleet from its current volume of 700 up to 7,000 by the end of 2018. San Francisco’s share of this increase will be 4,500, up from its current, fledgling 328. And in another transit-friendly move, Ford has acquired Chariot, a San Francisco private commuter shuttle service (and lone survivor among Leap and other similarly positioned services), with plans to expand those point-to-point services as well.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ford is working with Motivate, a leading global bike share company, and city officials to add new stations and ramp up the volume of city bikes over the next two years. The program’s footprint won’t be limited to San Francisco either - the plans will include East Bay, including Oakland, Berkeley, and Emerville, and San Jose. Ford will be rebranding the Bay Area Bike Share program as “Ford GoBike” -  which users will be able to access through its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fordpass.com/en_us/home.html&quot;&gt;FordPass&lt;/a&gt; platform, which it touts as a one-stop mobility shop for a variety of transportation needs.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While the image of riding around in a public bike splashed with corporate logos may not appeal to the average San Franciscan, the bike-share sponsorship is undoubtedly good news for the city as a whole, and the Bay Area at large. Ford’s support will infuse the program with capital that may not otherwise be available through city coffers, and increase the availability of city-share bikes, hopefully easing the number of single-rider car trips and congestion on buses. The expansion into East and South Bay shows similar promise.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing-sep-9-san-francisco-finds-unlikely-partnership-in-ford-for-city-bike-sharing/batesbike.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Berkeley Mayor Tom Bates speaks in favor of the program in front of San Francisco City Hall (courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bikeeastbay.org/campaigns/bike-share-all&quot;&gt;Bike East Bay&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;To that point, city officials around  the Bay have broadly expressed enthusiasm for this partnership. Berkeley Mayor Tom Bates spoke at an announcement outside City Hall earlier today, and was &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SFBayBikeShare/status/774297091162058752&quot;&gt;quoted&lt;/a&gt; by Bay Area Bike Share as “extremely excited about the prospect of getting these incredible bicycles to East Bay...This is the future!” Emeryville Mayor Dianne Martinez showed similar support on her &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BikeEastBay/status/774303788177907712&quot;&gt;Twitter account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Further, the extension of Chariot, while lower on the green transit totem pole than bicycling, also represents positive change for San Franciscans, in widening the assortment of transportation options for commuters. For parts of the city that are underserved by MUNI, BART, and other city-run transit systems, its advocates argue, this type of dynamic shuttle service can ease commuter pain at a cost competitive with Uber and Lyft - though still higher-priced than public transit options. And from an environmental perspective, if commuters can carpool in larger “pools” than shared Lyft or Uber rides, this would reduce the emissions related to those trips.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The first new bike stations are expected to arrive in spring of next year, with further expansion coming online through 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/affordable-housing-planned-for-16th-and-mission/">
    <title type="text">Affordable Housing Planned for 16th &amp; Mission</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:229590d3-0cf1-377b-9b98-34377edec995</id>
    <updated>2016-09-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/affordable-housing-planned-for-16th-and-mission/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, the Planning Commission received permit applications for an affordable housing project at &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionhousing.org/1950-mission-st-affordable-housing-takes-next-steps/&quot;&gt;1950 Mission Street&lt;/a&gt;. The project is an ambitious proposal with 157 apartments, architecture and amenities being designed by a steady stream of community input. The partnership between two nonprofits, Mission Housing Development Corporation (MHDC) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bridgehousing.com/&quot;&gt;BRIDGE Housing&lt;/a&gt;, will reserve 20% of its units (31 apartments) for formerly homeless families, and rents will be price-indexed for households earning 45% to 60% of Area Median Income.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Planned amenities include a rooftop garden, a communal living room and kitchen, and a bike maintenance workshop for neighborhood youth. The site lies between 15th and 16th Streets on Mission, a short walk from the 16th St &amp;amp; Mission BART station.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/affordable-housing-planned-for-16th-and-mission/1950aerial.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Artist rendering of 1950 Mission, aerial view&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;1950 Mission Street will replace a newly operational “navigation center” for the city’s homeless center, a pilot project run by the mayor’s Office of Housing and Community Development. This currently occupies the abandoned site of the former Phoenix Continuation High School, which was vacated and listed as surplus property by the school district in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cervantesdesignassociates.com/&quot;&gt;Cervantes Design Associates&lt;/a&gt; and the Latino advocacy group &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.podersf.org/&quot;&gt;PODER&lt;/a&gt; spearheaded a community engagement process to design the building and its amenities. MHDC Director Sam Moss described community-based planning as a “guiding principle” behind the project. Aside from organizing several workshops among local stakeholders, PODER and Cervantes have also convened a 1950 Mission Community Advisory Committee to foster the relationship between neighbors and the project sponsors.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;BRIDGE and MHDC plan on breaking ground in 2017. San Francisco’s local &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfgov2.org/ftp/uploadedfiles/elections/candidates/Nov2015/AffordableHousing_Text.pdf&quot;&gt;housing bond&lt;/a&gt; will finance the $80 million project, along with federal funds from low-income tax credits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/sf-controller-repeats-prop-c-is-too-damn-high/">
    <title type="text">SF Controller Repeats, Prop C Is Too Damn High</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a5eeb7b0-d251-3085-af3e-b42ebb1e19bb</id>
    <updated>2016-09-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/sf-controller-repeats-prop-c-is-too-damn-high/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night, the city controller’s office of San Francisco reaffirmed earlier recommendations curbing the price-indexed affordability requirements of market-rate development passed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/San_Francisco,_California,_Affordable_Housing_Requirements_Charter_Amendment,_Proposition_C_(June_2016&quot;&gt;Proposition C&lt;/a&gt;) last year. During the monthly meeting with the office’s advisory committee, Controller Ben Rosenfield supported lowering the percentages of Below Market Rental units required in new private development to be set at 14-18% per year, with a 0.5% increase each year. Under these non-binding recommendations, condominium development would have a 17-20% requirement as well.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Proposition C was co-authored by Supervisors Aaron Peskin and Jane Kim, who both assured critics they would reevaluate the affordability requirements per the Controller’s recommendation. Rosenfield has argued that any requirement above 18% Below Market would stifle overall housing production. Roland Li at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/09/prop-c-affordable-housing-study-for-sf.html?ana=twt&quot;&gt;San Francisco Business Times&lt;/a&gt; attended the meeting and provides the full scoop.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/london-housing-crisis-proves-nostradamus-writes-for-the-onion/">
    <title type="text">London Housing Crisis Proves Nostradamus Writes For &quot;The Onion&quot;</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:44e93955-636d-37ce-97a6-527f0f87c876</id>
    <updated>2016-09-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/london-housing-crisis-proves-nostradamus-writes-for-the-onion/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;News readers around the globe know the American satirical site The Onion as a steady source of prescient, incisive commentary on our modern society. Their hyperbolic headlines often reflect our deepest fears or ugliest biases, but seldom do we see life outright imitating their art. Amid a global surge in urban real estate prices, the particularly crisis-level housing shortage in London has prompted just that.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/aug/31/londons-elite-pushed-out-of-exclusive-postcodes-by-super-rich?CMP=Share_iOSApp_Other&quot;&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; reported on August 31st: “London’s elite pushed out of exclusive post-codes by super-rich.” Sound familiar? In 2008, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theonion.com/article/report-nations-gentrified-neighborhoods-threatened-2419&quot;&gt;The Onion&lt;/a&gt; ran the satirical headline: “Nation's Gentrified Neighborhoods Threatened By Aristocratization.” It’s real. It’s happening. This is not a drill.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Researchers from the London School of Economics’ (LSE) International Inequalities Institute have found that a surge of hyper-wealthy buyers have prompted the formerly elite establishment of lawyers, doctors, and other white-collar professionals “to buy in areas they previously considered undesirable.” Similarly, The Onion's article described how “the enormous treasure-based wealth of the aristocracy makes it impossible for those living on modest trust funds to hold onto their co-ops and converted factory loft spaces.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The similarities are uncanny. Dr. Luna Glucksberg—the totally real, non-parodic researcher at the LSE— warned of “ripple effects” from the displacement of high-income workers to areas further down the market in price, a gentrification wave that could harm affordability for all Londoners. “The study shows that the wealthy individuals and families that live in London’s most exclusive areas no longer feel able to compete at the top end of the capital’s property market,” she told The Guardian.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The aristocrats in the older, um, fictional article voiced a similar concern. The new landed gentry, writes The Onion, “deflected blame onto regification, a process by which they say they were priced out of their vast rural holdings by kings who wished to consolidate property and develop monumental palatial estates.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The process known as “reverse filtering” is very real, and is outlined in John Mangin’s seminal study “&lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.law.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/stanford-law-policy-review/print/2014/01/mangin_25_stan._l._poly_rev_91.pdf&quot;&gt;The New Exclusionary Zoning&lt;/a&gt;” (2014). “In areas with a capped supply and increasing demand,” Mangin writes, housing in effect ‘filters up’—housing formerly occupied by low-income people becomes housing for high-income people. If high-income people are unable to build new housing for themselves, they will buy existing housing and fix it up.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Just yesterday, California’s Legislative Analyst’s Office &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lao.ca.gov/LAOEconTax/Article/Detail/201&quot;&gt;made note&lt;/a&gt; of several analyses showing that real wage and population growth was receding from high-opportunity coastal areas to lower-income inland regions. “In part,” the LAO writes, “we suspect, due to California's lack of new residential housing supply and resulting high costs in coastal areas, a large portion of California's population growth occurred in areas of the state with incomes below the statewide median since 1990.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Perhaps The Onion was not being prescient so much as merely observing longstanding trends. Again, it’s worth repeating: This. Is. Not. A. Drill.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/telegraph-avenue-plan-prioritizes-berkeleys-pedestrians/">
    <title type="text">Telegraph Avenue Plan Prioritizes Berkeley's Pedestrians</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:04f0ecef-e2f5-3e41-b948-672b08e7dee1</id>
    <updated>2016-09-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/telegraph-avenue-plan-prioritizes-berkeleys-pedestrians/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/09/07/realm-plan-calls-for-pedestrian-oriented-telegraph-avenue/&quot;&gt;plans&lt;/a&gt; by Taecker Planning and Design present an ambitious &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/Telegraph-Public-Realm-Plan-Final-Low-Res.pdf&quot;&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt; for Berkeley’s bustling Telegraph Avenue corridor. Already the city’s densest area outside of the downtown, the main artery of the “Southside” neighborhood would be revamped to ease traffic congestion and create an environment more welcoming of pedestrians.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;After efforts to preserve a two-story structure from the 1970s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/06/20/berkeley-council-denies-landmark-status-for-the-village/&quot;&gt;failed&lt;/a&gt; to stave off a seven-story apartment project, the Telegraph Public Realm Plan seeks to further adjust to the influx of students to the area—an ever-growing source of sales tax revenue for the city—as well as regional population growth. Local businesses have recently been welcoming of increased density, though transit improvements have been slow to reach the corridor after Councilmember Jesse Arreguin delivered a &lt;a href=&quot;https://oaklandliving.wordpress.com/2010/05/12/joel-ramos-car-enthusiasts-kill-brt-in-berkeley/&quot;&gt;decisive&lt;/a&gt; “abstain” vote against an environmental study of the proposed Bus Rapid Transit program in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Although Arreguin &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ebyd.org/site/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/EBYD-Questionnaire-Jesse-Arreguin.pdf&quot;&gt;stated&lt;/a&gt; at the time that he “was concerned about the loss of local service and the impacts that could have on senior and disabled bus riders” and would have supported a “better plan” with “dedicated lanes during rush hour,” his abstention resulted in only Downtown and East Oakland breaking ground on dedicated BRT lanes and passenger loading islands.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At the time, Berkeley City Council effectively approved a “no-build” alternative resulting in very little change for bus transit on Telegraph Avenue. Six years later, there is still no sign of protected lanes, but the Public Realm Plan does offer what the designers call “Shared Streets,” accommodating motorists, cyclists, and pedestrians.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/telegraph-avenue-plan-prioritizes-berkeleys-pedestrians/dwighttriangle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Dwight &amp;amp; Telegraph triangular intersection optimized for pedestrians (source: Taecker Planning)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Taecker describes the concept as “a plaza-like place with a single ground plane, storefront to storefront, without being interrupted by a curb.” These streets would periodically be closed off to cars for event such as street fairs, which already occur on two blocks of the corridor, between the Durant and Haste intersections.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The plan will also be expanding piloted “Scramble Intersections” beyond the current Bancroft intersection, where a pedestrian-only traffic light allowsthose on foot to cross the intersection diagonally.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/telegraph-avenue-plan-prioritizes-berkeleys-pedestrians/durantplaza.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durant Plaza proposal for public art installations at the current Bank of America building&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sidewalks between the intersections of Bancroft and Dwight Way would be enhanced by public art, modular trash and recycling bins, and retrofitted street lighting. The corner of Durant Avenue, with wider sidewalks than adjacent streets, would host a plaza with public art and a parklet dedicated to exhibiting the rich history of Telegraph Avenue. The “Dwight Triangle,” in turn, would provide a southern gateway with another pedestrian-friendly plaza.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Demonstration projects are planned to be completed by 2017 at the latest. Depending on public reception, the plan could take anywhere from three to ten years, according to local news site Berkeleyside.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/courts-strike-down-eviction-protection-for-teachers/">
    <title type="text">Courts Strike Down Eviction Protection for Teachers</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:35379255-1e94-3218-bed4-26a4caa33695</id>
    <updated>2016-09-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/courts-strike-down-eviction-protection-for-teachers/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last week, a Superior Court judge struck down legislation from Supervisor David Campos intended to protect school employees from no-fault evictions during the school year. As an extension of tenant protections already available to families with school-age children, the Campos &lt;a href=&quot;https://sfgov.legistar.com/View.ashx?M=F&amp;amp;ID=4384428&amp;amp;GUID=995CE4CE-1094-4BFB-BC9C-1301F971D14A&quot;&gt;bill&lt;/a&gt; passed the Board of Supervisors unanimously, but was felled by a lawsuit from the San Francisco Apartment Association and the Small Property Owners of San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The ruling comes amid a slew of bad news for anti-displacement measures in the city, after Supervisor London Breed met with federal officials &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/08/supervisor-to-meet-with-feds-over-citys-anti-displacement-plan/&quot;&gt;to defend&lt;/a&gt; her “neighborhood preference” ordinance. The Department of Housing and Urban Development recently suggested that Breed’s legislation, which would give locals in a particular district priority in lotteries for Below Market Rental units, could violate the 1968 Fair Housing Act.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Legal counsel for the litigating property owners’ groups called Campos’s eviction protection for teachers “short-sighted” and “counterproductive” in light of the city’s raw housing shortage. Judge Ronald Quidachay agreed with this argument, calling it “invalid,” “preempted by state law,” and “unenforceable.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Campos, in turn, opined that the court was enforcing statutes that were out of touch with local needs. “We take a long view,” he told the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/politics/article/Judge-tosses-SF-law-preventing-teacher-evictions-9198849.php&quot;&gt;Chronicle&lt;/a&gt;. “You have a set of laws and systems that are not designed to deal with the housing crisis we are facing.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://projects.sfchronicle.com/2016/teacher-pay/&quot;&gt;analysis&lt;/a&gt; by the same paper found that median rents in San Francisco could take up to 64% of a standard teacher’s salary, more than double what the federal government recommends.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-ramps-up-oakland-office-project-with-dollar8-million-renovation-permit/">
    <title type="text">Oakland Ramps Up Oakland Office Project with $8 Million Renovation Permit</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:e60435fb-84f2-3e75-bb2b-bc485be6c992</id>
    <updated>2016-09-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/oakland-ramps-up-oakland-office-project-with-dollar8-million-renovation-permit/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Perhaps no single real estate deal has been more emblematic of the Bay Area tech boom’s highs and lows than Uber’s purchase of the historic Sears building in Oakland. The ridesharing giant purchased the vacant building, now known as Uptown Station, from Lane Partners, a developer that had purchased it in 2014 for $24 million with ambitious redevelopment plans. Uber &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2015/09/uber-oakland-lane-partners-walton-street-capital.html&quot;&gt;paid&lt;/a&gt; $123.5 million for the property, which they plan to use for expanded headquarters—approximately half the square footage price of office space in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Uber &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildzoom.com/property-info/1955-broadway-oakland-ca&quot;&gt;filed&lt;/a&gt; a permit application last week for interior remodeling, primarily for “structural upgrades at first floor atrium” and repairing stairs on the third and fifth floors. Observers expect many more filings to come as the company looks to convert the former department store into a modern tech office.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though initially expected to open in the spring, Uber says it now expects the new offices to open in late 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The office’s expected influx of tech employees has already shaped the narrative of real estate in Oakland’s Uptown District, which has already seen a resurgence of retail, restaurants, and music venues in the past decades. A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.redoakrealty.com/east-bay-real-estate-mls/OAKLAND-property-for-sale-3881-Martin-Luther-King-Jr-Way-OAKLAND-CA-94609?mlsid=40718150&quot;&gt;listing&lt;/a&gt; in the nearby Longfellow neighborhood two miles away advertises an empty lot as a “Developer’s dream come true,” urging bidders to “[p]ick this one up before others get the word that Uber is coming to town.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/los-gatos-council-denies-320-unit-mixed-use-project-at-north-40/">
    <title type="text">Los Gatos Council Denies 320-Unit Mixed-Use Project at North 40</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:0cf23116-588f-36a4-ab5a-cb65af1ecbf4</id>
    <updated>2016-09-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/los-gatos-council-denies-320-unit-mixed-use-project-at-north-40/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last night, the Los Gatos Town Council voted 3-2 to deny a permit application to construct 320 residential units and 66,800 square feet of retail space, known as North 40. The decision had been deferred from an earlier council meeting to this special session.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite objections by the developer, Grosvenor Homes, Mayor Barbara Spector spearheaded the motion to deny based on its failure to comply with &lt;a href=&quot;https://legistarweb-production.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/attachment/pdf/21407/Staff_Report_-_N40_FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;particular features&lt;/a&gt; of the town’s Specific Plan for the area. Although it is compliant with local zoning, with the implementation of the State Density Bonus, locals objected primarily on the grounds that the North 40 project did not provide enough senior housing for the area’s aging population. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://legistarweb-production.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/attachment/pdf/23957/081616.pdf&quot;&gt;minutes&lt;/a&gt; from a previous meeting on the project, the mayor cited the Specific Plan’s mandate that “the development should address Los Gatos unmet needs,
identified as Generation Y and Baby Boomers.” 50 of the 320 units would be price-indexed units reserved for senior citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There were also broader objections to changing the character of a municipality with a small-town feel that has nevertheless faced impacts of the regional economic boom, particularly in the form of freeway traffic. The aesthetic concerns, combined with objections based on the Specific Plan, coalesced around the local citizens’ group Town Not City.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Councilmember Steven Leonardis expressed concerns over traffic near the hospital, which he said already faced significant congestion. “If we’re going to add more capacity…I’m wondering how that would be addressed, if there would be any monetary contributions, or add a right of way with a third lane going northbound,” Leonardis remarked.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Confusion abounded over the state’s HCD memo emphasizing that denial of the project could only be based on “objective standards.” Leonardis asked city staff, “does that mean we can’t recommend changes and improvements?” Under the interpretation of state law, staff said, architectural improvements would not be considered a breach of state law if they were incorporated into a subsequent proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Councilmember Marcia Jensen objected to what she considered excessive perfectionism in mandating specific details of an otherwise zoning-compliant project. Her final comment before the vote questioned the assumption that the Town Council “can cause a property owner to come to us with exactly what we want, in exactly the way we want it, at exactly the time we want…We cannot mandate exactly what the application is,” she concluded. Jensen urged the council whether this could negatively impact the overall production of housing in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Sonja Trauss, founder of the San Francisco Bay Area Renters' Federation and co-founder of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://carlaef.org/&quot;&gt;California Renters Legal Advocacy and Education Fund&lt;/a&gt; (CaRLA), provided a brief statement. &quot;Los Gatos is out of compliance with the state's Housing Accountability Act, and we will be suing them to enforce the law and ensure that this project gets built.&quot; Trauss is currently spearheading an ongoing lawsuit in Lafayette on similar grounds.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Pilar Lorenzana-Campo, Policy Director of &lt;a href=&quot;http://siliconvalleyathome.org/&quot;&gt;Silicon Valley At Home&lt;/a&gt;, was watching the live video stream last night. The Santa Clara County-based advocacy group has been speaking in favor of the North 40 project since it was first proposed. “We’re really disappointed with last night’s decision in the face of the housing crisis we have right now,” she said in a phone interview. “We really need every community to step up and make sure they build enough housing, including market-rate and affordable housing, to meet the needs of their workers. There’s not enough housing to go around, so their decision to deny this application after years of engagement is really disappointing.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lorenzana-Campo also echoed Councilmember Jensen’s sentiments that the denial represented undue perfectionism in the face of a severe shortage. “This is the project that has been before them for a few years ago. The fact is that they entertained the proposal and were working with the developers, with the project design in question—they needed to take action to improve housing conditions in Los Gatos. In denying the project, they are just making the housing crisis worse, not only for their residents and workers, and for other residents in their region. Now some other community is going to have to provide the extra housing to make up for the unmet need. This is a regional issue, and Los Gatos needs to shoulder their fair share, as do all the other cities in Santa Clara County.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-jose-tenants-face-uphill-battle-against-rent-hike/">
    <title type="text">San Jose Tenants Face Uphill Battle Against Rent Hike</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:63702444-1553-3fe4-888d-532c0b128989</id>
    <updated>2016-09-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-jose-tenants-face-uphill-battle-against-rent-hike/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Two San Jose tenants face an increasingly Sisyphean struggle to hold off a crushing rent increase that could force them to move. Through an arcane loophole in the city’s rent control law, landlords were allowed to raise rents beyond the legal cap in order to pass through interest rates of new mortgage loans onto tenants.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Although San Jose &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbamo.com/news/san-jose-eliminates-mortgage-interest-loophole-in-rent-control/&quot;&gt;amended&lt;/a&gt; the law to close this loophole in June, in the three-month period before it took effect, the city saw fifteen Debt Pass-Through Petitions filed, as many as had been filed in the last five years. City Councilmember Raul Peralez confirmed this statistic in a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/JesseGaryKTVU2/videos/1572902493016105/&quot;&gt;interview with KTVU&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite receiving an unfavorable ruling from a hearing officer, residents Keith Jones and Julie Allen of 85 East Taylor Street plan to appeal their case. Under the current court decision, rent on the studio apartment the couple shares will increase from slightly over $1000 per month to $1595. The couple has lived at their current residence for six years.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While San Francisco’s displacement epidemic has garnered national media attention, San Jose’s equally disastrous housing crisis has received little beyond lip service outside of the South Bay. The city recently found itself legally unable to halt the single &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sanjoseinside.com/2016/06/29/mass-eviction-san-joses-largest-to-displace-670-people/&quot;&gt;largest eviction&lt;/a&gt; in the Bay Area, with a developer slated to tear down 216 units of low-income units for three times as many market-rate apartments.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though the legal process will be costly, Jones and Allen do not consider the hike in rent to be any less of a burden. “To be honest, we could potentially pay this,” Allen said over the phone. “But we would be rent-burdened. It would be another $600 a month that could go to our savings, especially if we decided we wanted to purchase something.” She also noted that Jones, at 57, is approaching conventional retirement age. “We have to think about our future and our retirement. We like to travel, we like to enjoy life. And in emergencies, if someone has to go to the hospital or something, it would really cut into it. It’s a huge increase in the cost of living now, coupled with the fact that salaries aren’t rising to keep up.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/san-jose-tenants-face-uphill-battle-against-rent-hike/kj2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keith Jones and Julie Allen in front of their apartment at 85 East Taylor Street&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Allen also stressed that it would be “virtually impossible” to find something within a similar price range in the area. “We would be looking into moving out of the area, even out of the state.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Jones was frustrated that everyone from city officials to pro-bono legal aid from the Law Foundation encouraged him to negotiate with the landlord, a paradigm he says places undue pressure on vulnerable tenants. “More than likely, I will probably do [the appeal] on my own,” Jones added. “We can’t afford to pay the fees for a new attorney. If I bring the landlord into court, we may have to pay for the landlord’s attorney fees.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Historically, it’s very rare that tenants win in these kinds of cases,” Allen added. “We actually were able to explain our situation at the last hearing…but the whole thing that we initially heard about was landlord hardship. They never talked about tenant hardship.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite the cost burden, Jones pointed to significant technical oversights he was confident could help him win in an appeal. His main frustrations stems from the fact that the court’s hearing officer initially sided with Jones, only to abruptly change her mind. In the court’s opinion, the debt pass-through was not based on the mortgage itself, but an amortization of the clerical fees from applying for the mortgage.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“In the decision,” Jones explained, “she sided with the new landlord, though the ordinance clearly states that you need 60+ months in mortgage payments. The landlord only made 59. The decision  isn’t supported by what her argument is. 59 versus 60 payments is very clear.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Jones also disputed that the landlord had adequately documented the terms of their recent loan. “That the fees were amortized over 15 years—there is no documentation, no support as to whether the loan that the new landlord took out is amortized over 15 years. The only thing that is supporting that is a letter from the bank stating that the loan is amortized for 15 years. On all other documents, it says it’s amortized for 5 years plus a balloon payment.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Because Jones and Allen both work full-time, Councilmember Raul Peralez was only able to schedule a meeting with them at the end of this month, after numerous attempts to meet with them in early afternoon hours.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/30-van-ness-will-return-to-market-without-listed-price/">
    <title type="text">30 Van Ness Will Return to Market Without Listed Price</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:f11e0eb9-bff0-330c-9f5e-f67a3050d5c0</id>
    <updated>2016-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/30-van-ness-will-return-to-market-without-listed-price/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On December 8, 2015, Supervisor Aaron Peskin’s first day back on the board, Peskin celebrated by reneging a deal made by the city's &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfgov.org/realestate/&quot;&gt;Real Estate Division&lt;/a&gt; to sell 30 Van Ness for $80 million, potentially creating a $60 million liability for the city.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The city-owned site at 30 Van Ness Avenue will go back on the market on September 6th with no listing price. Roland Li at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/09/30-van-ness-san-francisco-housing-development.html?ana=twt&quot;&gt;Business Times&lt;/a&gt; reported the San Francisco Real Estate Division’s announcement earlier today, which has been widely anticipated since Supervisor Aaron Peskin &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfyimby.com/news/2016/8/2/aaron-peskins-art-of-no-deal&quot;&gt;blocked&lt;/a&gt; a proposed sale ten months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;30 Van Ness is currently a 6-story city office building. With an impending $60 million in seismic upgrades required to continue its office use, along with the revenue potential from its current zoning for 40 stories, the city decided put the parcel on the market. After vetting 15 offers from large developers, the  Office of Real Estate reached an agreement with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.relatedcalifornia.com/&quot;&gt;Related California&lt;/a&gt; to sell the property for $80 million and for the property to set aside 20% for affordable housing. Related proposed to build 40 stories with 500 dwelling units (400 rented at market rate, 100 Below Market Rentals) with one single entrance (no &quot;poor door&quot;) on prime transit-accessible land,. Related also planned to lease at least 5000 square feet of the space for a new child care center.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite having completed a competitive bidding process, several supervisors claimed to believe there was still another developer with a potentially better offer.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Peskin, bolstered by factional “progressive” allies Campos, Mar, and Kim, raised doubts that the $80 million offer from Related California was the highest return the city could obtain. The deal included an allotment for 25% Below Market Rental units if the proposed &lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/San_Francisco,_California,_Affordable_Housing_Requirements_Charter_Amendment,_Proposition_C_(June_2016&quot;&gt;Proposition C&lt;/a&gt;) requirements passed (which they did), with city funds paying the difference to increase the price-indexed unit ratio to 33%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;During a marathon 9-hour meeting on December 8, 2015, Supervisors Mar and Kim both made statements to the effect that there was a “better deal to be had.” Supervisor Campos, representing the Mission District in Bernal Heights, chimed in: “Is this really, not even the best deal, but is this a good deal for the city and our district? I don’t know if I could say that…I think this is one of those things that in a very short time, we're going to look back and say, 'What the heck were we thinking?'&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I say this as somebody who has spent most of his adult life in the business of real property sale and acquisition that we, respectfully, are leaving a bit too much money on the table,” Peskin declared.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Our fundamental job,” the Supervisor continued, “is to get as much for our shareholders, the people of the city and county of San Francisco, as we can. And with all due respect to our department of real estate, we have not gotten that.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A city official testifying at the meeting informed the Board that all other bids were significantly lower than the $80 million Related was offering. After the sale was voted down, no higher offer came before the city.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;John Updike, director of the city’s real estate department, expects that the city will make a decision among future bids by the end of the year. The developer would have to pay for seismic upgrades, and would have the option to maintain its current use as office space.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/kim-hosts-town-hall-highlights-housing-proposals/">
    <title type="text">Kim Hosts Town Hall, Highlights Housing Proposals</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:8fc4b231-d8ab-33ba-b357-52232620c6eb</id>
    <updated>2016-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/kim-hosts-town-hall-highlights-housing-proposals/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Jane Kim buoyed a relatively positive atmosphere in a town hall meeting on housing policy, easily San Francisco’s most severe and contentious political issue this year. Joined on a panel by former Los Angeles Mayor Antonio Villaraigosa and BART Board candidate Lateefah Simon, Kim’s forum, hosted by Salon magazine co-founder David Talbot, highlighted the city’s crisis-level wave of displacement along with the Supervisor’s policy objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Before the forum began, Villaraigosa told Tim Redmond of &lt;a href=&quot;http://48hills.org/2016/08/31/kim-packs-housing-forum-former-la-mayor-hints-gov-run/&quot;&gt;48 Hills&lt;/a&gt; that he would “make an announcement in November” regarding his potential run for Governor. Villaraigosa is widely expected to run for the office against former San Francisco mayor and current Lieutenant Governor Gavin Newsom.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/kim-hosts-town-hall-highlights-housing-proposals/scottkimprotest.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/kim-hosts-town-hall-highlights-housing-proposals/scottkimprotest2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supporters of Scott Wiener picketing outside Mission High School&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Outside Mission High School, with an auditorium capacity of over 1,000, supporters of Supervisor Scott Wiener, Kim’s rival candidate for State Senate, picketed before the event began. Protesters held signs, many in Chinese, criticizing what they saw as empty promises from Supervisor Kim in spite of an inconsistent record on housing. Signs such as “Housing Not Tents” in particular referred to Kim’s opposition to a sales tax to fund homeless services, which she considered a regressive tax, as well as her &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/tempers-flare-homeless-tent-encampment-ballot-measure/&quot;&gt;legislation&lt;/a&gt; requiring seven-days’ notice and temporary shelter before clearing tent encampments.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kim remained optimistic about her policy goals, in particular touting her efforts at increasing inclusionary requirements in new market-rate developments. Without requiring price-indexed units in new buildings, &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/08/supervisors-forum-considers-housing-and-transportation/&quot;&gt;she argued&lt;/a&gt;, market-rate condos in the city were only affordable to families making at least $270,000 per year.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The Supervisor boasts in her campaign promotions that she successfully negotiated higher percentages of affordable housing from developers, namely a 40% Below Market Rate set-aside in the controversial 5M project.  This qualification has recently come under criticism for basing the percentage off a smaller denominator than the total amount of units. Rather than a full 40%, Joe Eskenazi of &lt;a href=&quot;http://modernluxury.com/san-francisco/story/how-supervisor-kims-new-affordability-law-lets-developers-the-hook&quot;&gt;San Francisco Magazine&lt;/a&gt; reported that the number would be closer to 35%.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kim’s flagship 2015 ballot measure Proposition C has also seen recent criticism for requiring 25% of units be price-indexed for low- and middle-income households, a ratio Mayor Ed Lee called “arbitrary” at the time it was proposed. San Francisco’s City Controller released a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/08/san-francisco-affordable-homes-requirement-prop-c.html&quot;&gt;draft report&lt;/a&gt; last month suggesting that a requirement above 18% had the potential to slow down overall housing production. Kim and Prop C co-author Supervisor Aaron Peskin had promised to recalculate the requirements pending the Controller’s final analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Kim’s newest ballot measure proposal, Proposition X, has also been &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/07/sf-made-san-francisco-ballot-pdr-jane-kim.html&quot;&gt;criticized&lt;/a&gt; as “arbitrary” in its requirements. If passed by voters, the measure would require the developers to preserve 50-100% of “PDR” space (production, distribution, and repair) in industrial zones. SF Made, a union of 650 manufacturers in the city, publicly opposed the measure. They argue the measure would needlessly slow housing production by forcing new projects to be leased for lower-revenue uses, and have advocated for housing industrial tenants in larger spaces instead. Kim made a brief mention of Proposition X at the forum, stating that it was an important strategy to preserve blue-collar jobs in San Francsico.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Housing itself was just a starting point for panelist Lateefah Simon’s broader vision for socioeconomic equity. Simon, a native of the city’s Fillmore District, now lives in Oakland due to the cost of rent. A lower-income worker forced to move to Richmond, she noted, would pay upwards of $300 per month in BART fares to and from their job in the city. Transportation and housing, in her view, were inextricably linked in her progressive policy goals for social justice.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Villaraigosa, several years out of the political limelight, stumbled on a few recent issues when describing his experiences trying to grow the affordable housing stock in Los Angeles. “There was a real problem of people saying, ‘we don't want those people in our neighborhood,’” he remarked. He proceeded to outline hypothetical policies that happened to coincide with the Governor Brown recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/08/unions-against-gov-browns-as-of-right-housing-plan.html&quot;&gt;“by-right”&lt;/a&gt; proposal—a policy he later admitted he had been unfamiliar with until that night. Kim had voted in favor of Supervisor Aaron Peskin’s resolution opposing the legislation, which Mayor Lee quickly vetoed.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It was a rally masquerading as a forum,” said Laura Clark, founder of housing advocacy group Grow SF. “The host just lobbed softballs at her the whole time. I can’t complain though; it was a really good rally.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/art-installations-will-repurpose-abandoned-military-bunkers/">
    <title type="text">Art Installations Will Repurpose Abandoned Military Bunkers</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:4c8e81ac-6322-32a1-96ce-5aaf4753cf5a</id>
    <updated>2016-08-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/art-installations-will-repurpose-abandoned-military-bunkers/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Fort Winfield Scott is home to long-abandoned concrete structures with an austere past, once occupied by 17 gun batteries and a central headquarters for Harbor Defenses San Francisco (HDSF). After World War II, the Presidio site housed the Army’s Coast Artillery School after it moved from Fort Monroe, Virginia in 1946. The air force and hydrogen bombs soon rendered the coast artillery network obsolete, and the school closed in 1950. Fort Scott officially closed as a military outpost in 1956.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;125 years after the first batteries were built, and in anticipation of the centennial anniversary of the National Park Service, local art group the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.for-site.org/&quot;&gt;FOR-SITE Foundation&lt;/a&gt; has developed ambitious &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.for-site.org/&quot;&gt;plans&lt;/a&gt; for repurposing the site. The group is most widely known for their recent Ai Weiwei exhibition on Alcatraz Island. Their project, entitled &lt;a href=&quot;http://files.ctctcdn.com/fc32f3de501/902e1519-9841-4c8d-bd36-fcb92899bad4.pdf&quot;&gt;Home Land Security&lt;/a&gt;, will bring 16 artists from around the world to present installations in the vacant batteries, each exploring the bellicose themes that the site evokes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/art-installations-will-repurpose-abandoned-military-bunkers/do_ho_suh-_5759-sm_-5133451420-.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do Ho Suh's installation &quot;Bridging Home&quot; (2010) in Liverpool, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Installations will include local sculptor &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alfarrow.com/al-farrow-bio.html&quot;&gt;Al Farrow&lt;/a&gt;’s scale models of a church and mosque made of spent ammunitions; Korean artist &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.art21.org/artists/do-ho-suh&quot;&gt;Do Ho Suh&lt;/a&gt;’s massive suit of armor made from military tags; Iranian performer &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.davoodemdadian.com/&quot;&gt;Yashar Azar Emdadian&lt;/a&gt;’s film Des-Integration (2010), in which he shaves his torso in public; and war-themed paintings by Syrian artist &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ayyamgallery.com/artists/tammam-azzam&quot;&gt;Tamman Azzam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The exhibition will open on September 10th.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/granny-flat-law-may-ease-states-housing-woes/">
    <title type="text">Granny Flat Law May Ease State's Housing Woes</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:7d69910b-2ec2-39e3-ab2c-7274059da9fa</id>
    <updated>2016-08-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/granny-flat-law-may-ease-states-housing-woes/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As the legislative session came to an end this past Monday, one important housing law that made it past the Senate was &lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/49/ShippingContainerCottage.jpg&quot;&gt;SB 1069&lt;/a&gt;, a bill that would ease local requirements on “granny” or Accessory Dwelling Units.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Presently, local governments can impose a number of restrictions on granny-units, including requirements related to parking, setbacks, and installation of utility connections, hurdles that often prove too costly or onerous for primary unit owners to implement. By prohibiting these restrictions, the law has the potential to ease the state’s housing crunch by opening up many existing units for renting out. This is considered a relatively unobstructive change to current state land use policy that will allow cities, particularly urban centers, to accommodate more residents.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Several cities, in fact, have already loosened secondary unit requirements, including San Francisco, Berkeley, and Oakland. In 2015, the Board of Supervisors approved &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/sf-oks-new-housing-units/&quot;&gt;legislation&lt;/a&gt; to legalize in-law units in Districts 3 and 8 of San Francisco, covering North Beach, Chinatown, and the Castro and Noe Valley, respectively, under proposals introduced by supervisors Scott Wiener and then-supervisor Julie Christensen. In January of this year, Oakland passed an ordinance eliminating the additional parking space requirement for any secondary units located within a half-mile of a BART station or other major transit stops.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Even with many cities taking initiative with respect to increasing secondary unit availability, a broader-sweeping, state law offers much more punch toward the cause. The bill includes encouraging language toward the end of increased housing availability, declaring accessory dwelling units an “essential component of housing supply” in California. That state lawmakers recognize and are enacting measures to ease the housing crunch is a promising sign for California, and an indication that local housing challenges can be at least partially resolved at the state level.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Governor Jerry Brown has endorsed the bill and is expected to sign it into law. 
State Assembly, Jerry Brown, Accessory Dwelling Units&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/popcorn-for-planners-this-weeks-best-yimby-videos/">
    <title type="text">Popcorn For Planners: This Week's Best YIMBY Videos</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:0fdb6ff7-7bfc-3a96-a200-61a8a61f252e</id>
    <updated>2016-08-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/popcorn-for-planners-this-weeks-best-yimby-videos/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We started this news site with the wholly altruistic (pinkie promise) intentions of spreading far and wide our cheeky obsession with videos of local government hearings. It's easy for us to forget in the Bay Area that this top-notch prime-time viewing happens all over the country, even the rest of the non-American world. With pro-pedestrian, density-loving nerds extolling the entertainment value of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.oaklandnet.com/government/o/CityCouncil/index.htm&quot;&gt;#oakmtg&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ci.berkeley.ca.us/Clerk/City_Council/City_Council__Agenda_Index.aspx&quot;&gt;#berkmtg&lt;/a&gt; all over the Internet, we found it necessary to breathe some fresh air into this lurid subculture by showing some love for our friends in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;These brave, snarky tricksters over at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCiKFyG2M8e62HOrDDJ7HYbw&quot;&gt;Wedge LIVE!&lt;/a&gt; have compiled some of the best footage from planning meetings in the Minneapolis &amp;amp; St. Paul metro area on YouTube for your viewing pleasure. Watch some highlights below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FuE4ZwQeCdo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/n6qaVzK-xzs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/podcast-an-autopsy-of-governor-browns-by-right-bill/">
    <title type="text">Podcast: An Autopsy of Governor Brown's &quot;By-Right&quot; Bill</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:ce597b74-dfaa-3b22-b4e5-354d4b89b973</id>
    <updated>2016-08-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/podcast-an-autopsy-of-governor-browns-by-right-bill/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We implore our readers to forgive the recent shortage of in-depth, eyebrow-raising content. As the sole editor and writer for this publication, output is contingent on my health; when I can scarcely get out of bed, it follows that my words will struggle to reach your eyes. Thankfully we have some respite for you today.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As I lounge around in my rent-controlled apartment, banishing the fears of what may happen if anyone finds out I'm not on the lease, I had the austere pleasure of listening to this analysis of Governor Jerry Brown's &quot;By-Right&quot; Trailer Bill, how it could have streamlined the production of housing, and why it failed to gain support among stakeholders. The defunct legislation is covered starting at the 35-minute mark on John Myers' California Politics podcast, linked below.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/280086524&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/seeking-to-stop-high-rise-berkeley-grandstanders-find-shaky-footing-in-court/">
    <title type="text">Seeking to Stop High-Rise, Berkeley Grandstanders Find Shaky Footing in Court</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:02178a54-f849-3271-b575-0e882bdbd1af</id>
    <updated>2016-08-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/seeking-to-stop-high-rise-berkeley-grandstanders-find-shaky-footing-in-court/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguillar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Last year, the saga of Berkeley’s controversial &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/01/14/lawsuit-filed-to-stop-building-of-harold-way-complex/&quot;&gt;2211 Harold Way&lt;/a&gt; project appeared to have ended with a cliffhanger. City Council voted to uphold approval of the 302-unit building, which plans to replace Shattuck Cinemas with a new theater and contribute $10.5 million into the city’s Housing Trust Fund. Development consultant and former Planning Commissioner Mark Rhoades noted that this money could be leveraged to construct 100 permanently Below Market Rental (BMR) units. Neighborhood opponents vowed a reprisal, and two subsequent lawsuits alleging improper Environmental Impact Reports delayed groundbreaking indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In addition to 177 underground parking spots, community benefits cited include 10,000 square feet of commercial space and a 10-screen movie theater replacing Shattuck Cinemas. The project will also provide $1 million into an arts fund, with $250,000 going to assist the Habitot children’s museum in its relocation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The lawsuits filed independently by Kelly Hammargren and James Hendry under the California Environmental Quality Act (CEQA) were merged into a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/08/29/court-considers-challenge-to-berkeleys-2211-harold-way-project/&quot;&gt;joint hearing&lt;/a&gt; at the Alameda County Superior Court. Local news source Berkeleyside provided full coverage of the lengthy hearing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For four hours on Friday, Hammargren and Hendry presented their arguments over the project’s environmental impacts, frequently digressing into political remarks against developers. Judge Frank Roesch had to instruct the audience not to cheer and applaud Hammargren’s speeches. “We don’t think that political speeches are very helpful in solving the puzzle,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/seeking-to-stop-high-rise-berkeley-grandstanders-find-shaky-footing-in-court/haroldwaynimbys.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supporters of Hammargren and Hendry's lawsuit, notorious for opposing any new development in Berkeley, dubbed &quot;the fabulous fighting forty&quot; by local housing advocates (source: Berkeleyside)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Hammargren and Hendry displayed a conspicuous lack of legal experience in their self-representation. At one point, Judge Roesch denied Hammargren’s motion to introduce a map of the building’s western environs, which she claimed would show adverse health impacts due to the construction site’s proximity to Berkeley High School. The court only allowed evidence that had been included in the administrative record, which included 15,000 pages of documentation and video from 37 public hearings.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Attorneys from Manatt Phelps &amp;amp; Phillips represented developers HSR Berkeley Investments and Rhoades Development Group. Zach Cowan, City Attorney of Berkeley, also presented arguments. Hendry cited his experience attending administrative legal hearings as a motivation to represent himself.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When reached by phone for comment, developer and planner Mark Rhoades bitterly decried what he saw as a vindictive, anti-democratic process. “As a Berkeley resident, an urban planner, and a housing provider, this saddens me. This is exactly why Berkeley—and the state of California in general—has the housing crisis that we do. People have choices to make. They can continue to fight when they are in the voting minority and hold up the rest of the democratic process, or they can choose to respect the democratic process.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When asked what he meant, he elaborated: “What’s being done here has no respect for the democratic process; it’s a demand for their own way. They’re holding a project hostage …The units are held up, the Housing Trust Fund money is held up, a state of the art movie theater is held up, money for Habitot is held up. It’s all held up by two residents because they’re aggrieved, first by Berkeley’s vote on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2010/10/20/18024/&quot;&gt;2010 Measure R&lt;/a&gt;, and also how the city implemented that.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Rhoades also noted that the initial impact fee requirement was only $6.2 million. The city asked for, and the applicant agreed, to provide an additional $4 million in additional community benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At the end of the hearing, Judge Roesch announced that he would deliver his ruling on the CEQA suit within 90 days.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/legislature-may-strengthen-californias-anti-nimby-law/">
    <title type="text">Legislature Strengthens California's 'Anti-NIMBY' Law</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:436710e2-48ef-369c-a1ca-45b9b9561204</id>
    <updated>2016-08-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/legislature-may-strengthen-californias-anti-nimby-law/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Readers may recall the Housing Accountability Act, a little-known state law that made headlines last year in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/news/article/City-activists-brazen-new-battle-cry-Sue-the-6485289.php&quot;&gt;lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; against Lafayette. The California Renters Legal Advocacy and Education Fund (CaRLA) decided to sue the East Bay suburb after it goaded a developer into downsizing a housing project from a 300-unit apartment complex into 44 single-family homes. In its current form, the law gives standing to applicants and potential tenants to sue a municipality for rejecting a zoning-compliant housing project for less-than-“objective” standards.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The California State Legislature passed an amendment on Tuesday that could expand the power of this law. Under new language introduced by Assemblymember Tom Daly, organizations representing tenants and housing projects could also sue to enforce the law. The State Senate passed the bill unanimously, and it will next go to the Assembly before reaching the Governor’s desk.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Housing groups around the state have praised the amendment as a boon to their advocacy efforts. In a letter supporting the bill, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://caanet.org/tool-enforcing-pro-housing-law-advances-governor/&quot;&gt;California Apartment Association&lt;/a&gt; noted that “[o]ne of the most significant barriers to the construction of new affordable housing is unjustified local resistance from NIMBY (Not In My Backyard) groups.” They went on to describe the amendment as applying “appropriate pressure” to municipalities hesitant to more housing in the midst of a statewide shortage.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Ryan Patterson, legal counsel for CaRLA in the Lafayette suit, was cautiously optimistic. When reached by email, he offered the following comment: “Previously, nonprofit housing organizations lacked standing to file lawsuits on their own behalf. Although its scope is modest, this law gives advocacy organizations a new tool to support housing development proposals.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/berkeleys-homeless-mayoral-candidate-hits-the-airwaves/">
    <title type="text">Berkeley's Homeless Mayoral Candidate Hits the Airwaves</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:ed7f2655-df40-3b79-9a2d-a4e534d1383b</id>
    <updated>2016-08-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/berkeleys-homeless-mayoral-candidate-hits-the-airwaves/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Three cigarettes light up an otherwise dim, intentionally-dingy room. Over the next few hours, they will burn out and be replaced. It occurs to me that the popular idiom has become reality—I am literally in a smoke-filled room, observing local politics unfold. “I should warn you,” one of the hosts says, “my views are distinctly non-progressive. I’m going to be trying to poke holes in all your views.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;His guest laughs. “All I can say is, bring it. I'm ready.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mike Lee lives on the streets of Berkeley. You can catch him at the downtown Starbucks, or at Au Coquelet, and sometimes at the YMCA.  He’s happy to talk about his mayoral campaign to anyone who will listen. Passers-by can spot his campaign posters, advertising “A New Vision For A New Future” all over downtown. Sporting a Whitmanian grey beard which somehow amplifies his steady baritone pipes, he looks—by early 20th Century Marxist standards, anyway—like much more of a statesman than his cleanshaven opponents: Councilmembers Laurie Capitelli, Jesse Arreguin, Kriss Worthington, in his view the “only serious candidates” besides &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oldbumformayor.org/&quot;&gt;himself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;By the gracious invitation of the disc jockeys, I came to an undisclosed location to observe his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mixcloud.com/christopher-lexx-stanley/mike-lee-dr-vee-wlexxx-1041fm-sf-live-in-studio-8-19-2016/&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; on a local pirate radio station. DJ Christopher “Lexxx” Stanley, a personal friend I also run into all over Berkeley, declined to mention me save as a “member of the audience,” but by the end, my inquisitiveness got the best of me, and I was allowed to ask questions over the air.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/berkeleys-homeless-mayoral-candidate-hits-the-airwaves/leead.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A defaced ad for Mike Lee in Downtown Berkeley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Political debate began in earnest well before the interview. While DJ Lexxx played anything from disco hits to punk rock obscurities, his co-host “Dr. V” grilled Lee, though he called it “prepping.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Though he only moved back to Berkeley &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/06/29/would-a-homeless-mayor-in-berkeley-make-a-difference-for-the-homeless/&quot;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt; (from Las Vegas), Lee has a storied history in Berkeley. In 1991, he was one of the four protesters sued by UC Berkeley for disrupting the University’s attempt to pave over People’s Park. Along with Bob Sparks, Carol Denney, and David Nadel, Lee was named as a “key leader” in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.caroldenney.com/slapp.pdf&quot;&gt;protests&lt;/a&gt; UC police had failed to shut down by violent reprisal. (People’s Park, now a historic landmark, is a legendary flashpoint for protests ever since the city demolished low-income housing on the site via eminent domain in 1967. The resulting protests, in a sense, created the park.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lee still boasts that he regularly disobeys a court injunction preventing him from setting foot in People’s Park, “because I don’t recognize [the university’s] authority.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It is fascinating to see him and Dr. V spar casually, like veteran boxers who don’t care if anyone wins. Lee is quick to call him a “libertarian,” and it is clear that the two share anti-authoritarian sentiments from opposite sides of the political spectrum. Dr. V attempts to guide Lee into a discussion of economic rent, and asks whether Lee considers local land-use policies as an example of it. “’Rent’ is wealth extraction by political means—restrictions on an otherwise free market,” he clarifies.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I think those who would want a free market realized it wouldn’t work in our society,” Lee answers.  “So they set up a political process to make sure they benefited from it.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I worked on prisoner stuff during that time—[Leonard] Peltier, Mumia [Abdul-Jamal],” he says when the conversation drifts back to People’s Park. His episode with the park seems to inform most of his policy positions, revolving around his insistence that local government bodies, including the Planning Commission, be “community based.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It’s bullshit that the [Zoning Adjustments Board] has so much authority. I think zoning is bullshit anyway because it’s not community based.” What then, I ask, would his answer be? His answer is one I press him to clarify throughout the subsequent interview: any developer wishing to build in Berkeley, under a Lee administration, would need 80% approval (“not popular vote,” he clarifies: “approval rating, by polls”) from the council District before being built. Districts, furthermore, would be subdivided into “neighborhood councils” of a 10-by-10 block area.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;More surprising was his suggestion that community opinion could sway his own policy positions: “Despite my reservations about the minimum wage increase, it’s clearly what the community wanted, and I respect that.” Later in the interview, he would describe his interactions with local small businesses that would not be able to absorb the cost. Strangely, his position on the popular soda tax is not swayed by the electorate, and he dismissed the measure as “the stupidest idea.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;He was quick to dismiss &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bengould.org/&quot;&gt;Ben Gould&lt;/a&gt;, a UC Berkeley graduate student also running, as “an apprentice to developers” for views he has dubbed “market urbanism.” I asked him about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.laurieforberkeleymayor.com/&quot;&gt;Laurie Capitelli&lt;/a&gt;, a retired realtor and current Councilmember whom many consider the top contender for mayor. Here he adopted a more conciliatory tone.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“We’re going to agree to disagree on a lot of things, but we want to improve the quality of life for everyone. That’s attitude that I’ve carried for years,” he said. “[City Council], they wish I would go away. But they find me a reasonable and rational individual. [City] staff takes notice.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I asked him how, despite his disagreements, he was able to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/08/12/op-ed-its-not-rocket-science-to-solve-homelessness/&quot;&gt;collaborate&lt;/a&gt; with Capitelli on piloting a Tiny Homes project, with labor donated by the local carpenters’ union. “He knows my attitude to him—I openly call him Crookitelli. He laughs and says, ‘oh shit, it’s Mike Lee!’ We have mutual repsect for each other’s positions. When we first met, I said to him, ‘Understand that whatever I say on this campaign, it’s not personal. This is business, this is politics.’ That’s how we got Tiny Houses.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The interview did not cover much related to land-use. Lee’s campaign promises had more to do with the police: “My first day in office, I will announce, racial profiling in Berkeley ends today.’” He cited the December 7, 2014 Black Lives Matter protests in Berkeley as an instance of undue violence against peaceful protesters, which BPD openly boasted of in their meetings with the Police Review Commission. His top priority, he said, would be to strengthen the authority of an independent Police Review Commission.  “They killed Bob [Sparks], but they can’t get rid of me,” he said in another allusion to the 1991 suit. He went on to detail grisly episodes of profiling by Berkeley police, both against communities of color and the poor in general.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lee did not hold back on his scorn for every other mayoral candidate, including Capitelli’s lead opponent, Jesse Arreguin. “You walk around Downtown Berkeley and it looks like a third-world country. It’s dusty, it’s dirty…obviously, as a professional politician, he hasn’t done very well. We have New York-sized city rats running around. And when we look at the type of development that’s going on downtown, he’s not protecting the interests of his constituency in District 4.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;(Curiously, Arreguin voted against the controversial &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2015/12/09/berkeley-approves-construction-of-harold-way-high-rise/&quot;&gt;2211 Harold Way project&lt;/a&gt;, citing among many objections that the $10 million the project would be contributing to the city’s Housing Trust Fund was not enough. However, the council voted unanimously to approve a $13 million tax rebate for a new &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2016/05/27/new-334-room-downtown-berkeley-hotel-gets-the-go-ahead/&quot;&gt;hotel&lt;/a&gt; above the downtown Bank of America, which Lee was also quick to criticize.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Of his “buddy” Capitelli, he simply said that it was “inappropriate” for a realtor to be making any land-use decisions on the city council. “If he wins, we all better buy tents, because we won’t be able to afford 4, 5, 6 thousand dollar rents.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lee also dismissed contender Kriss Worthington’s statement that “Berkeley does not need to move to the right on any issue” as “a lot of flim-flam.” Why? “We need to move to the right to fiscal responsibility…because of the fact that we are $1 billion underfunded on just two areas: labor, and infrastructure. We need a half a billion dollars just to fix the infrastructure…Based on that statement, I don’t want [Worthington] sitting in the mayor’s chair.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;One of Lee’s more unique policy positions is providing Council representation for UC Berkeley students. Comparing their lack of representation to the Boston Tea Party, he insisted that such a vital part of Berkeley’s sales tax revenue needed its own legislative representation. Currently, students can only vote if they are residents within the city of Berkeley, though many remain registered at their parents’ place of residence.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;As an advocate for his fellow homeless residents, Lee held Arreguin’s recently championed Homeless Task Force in vast contempt. Berkeley’s current homeless policy, in his view, consisted of “criminalization, or a baloney sandwich and a pat on the head.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The worst thing I find about City Council is that they have right now on their desk two proposals that would reduce homelessness by 20% at no cost to the city. They ignore it because they can’t get any political capital out of it.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;He found the report of the Homeless Task Force to be particularly offensive because it overlooked basic issues of sustenance and breaking the cycle of poverty. “In the report, they included Maslow’s triangle. At the bottom, food and shelter; at the top, yoga and meditation.” (The &lt;a href=&quot;http://cityofberkeley.info/uploadedFiles/Council_4/2015-06-23%20WS%20Item%2001%20Homeless%20Task.pdf&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; posted on Arreguin’s website has no mention of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maslow%27s_hierarchy_of_needs&quot;&gt;Maslow’s Hierarchy of Needs&lt;/a&gt;, but does include recommendations to increase public restrooms in the downtown area, funded in part by imposing a vacancy tax.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lee also praised the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yeah-berkeley.org/&quot;&gt;YEAH&lt;/a&gt; youth shelter in Berkeley. In his view, it was the only homeless service in town that had complete accountability, and “Jackie [Grant, Executive Director] can get you the numbers in thirty seconds.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lee has butted heads with a different Jackie, who I initially had conflated: Jacquelyn McCormick, former mayoral candidate and now Arreguin's campaign manager. McCormick excoriated Lee in the past over a sit-in Lee organized to protest Council’s inaction on police and homeless issues. “I hope you realize that anything that lasts more than one day or overnight will be used against Jesse,” McCormick wrote in an email, which Lee then posted in its entirety on the Capitelli campaign’s Facebook page. “This will play right into Capitelli’s hand.” Lee replied with his characteristic candor: “That’s a load of crap and you know it. Me publicizing this email will do more damage. If Jesse loses it’s because someone else won, not because a homeless man protested.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mike Lee is no stranger to controversy on Facebook. An anonymous source sent us screenshots of Lee implying a call to assassinate current Berkeley mayor Tom Bates, which Lee dismissed as an intentionally inflammatory joke.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/berkeleys-homeless-mayoral-candidate-hits-the-airwaves/leefb.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mike Lee (Facebook alias Sam Spade) posts incendiary comments about Mayor Tom Bates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The candidate is firm that he is the only candidate who walks the districts and talks to the community. He pointed in particular to the hypocrisy of claiming lowered vacancies in Downtown Berkeley, while many storefronts remain vacant on Solano Avenue.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Community is a very nice word,” Dr. V added. “But if somebody acts in the name of the community, it’s a very flexible word that all sorts of specific interests can take control of—you get back to the Platonic question of who will guard the guardians?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Dr. V went on to describe Berkeley as a “class-based” and “Tory” community that wants “strict zoning…and a jacked up minimum wage to feel good about themselves.” This was where I jumped in.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lee’s housing platform is ambitious and uncompromising. In addition to his 80% approval standard, he would impose a requirement of either 50% of new dwelling units be “affordable” (price-indexed to local incomes), or that 50% of profits be donated to the city. “If people say that will make it so nobody wants to build in Berkeley, fine by me,” he added. I think we have enough luxury housing anyway.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;If Lee proposed total local autonomy, I asked, how could he guarantee that North Berkeley wouldn’t become an even more exclusionary community than it already is?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For context, I live within walking distance of the North Berkeley BART station, which is surrounded by an entire block of surface parking. I have yet to see any new multifamily housing development being built north of University Avenue. Why should North Berkeley neighborhoods have the same autonomy that South Berkeley craves to ward off new market-rate construction? In the strongly-held opinion I expressed, the restricted density of North Berkeley’s zoning unduly shifts the burden of surging regional demand onto much poorer parts of Berkeley, which largely remained poor enclaves thanks to historic redlining and blatant racism. This is a unique point of agreement I have found with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.berkeleyside.com/2015/08/05/friends-of-adeline-our-future-shall-be-determined-by-us/&quot;&gt;Friends Of Adeline&lt;/a&gt;, a neighborhood group with close ties to Lee.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The candidate remained firm that his solution would maximize fairness. “We are organized to defend our community…” He insisted that this would in no way let North Berkeley “off the hook” in demand for new construction. Dr. V, in turn, took the hardline libertarian stance that abolishing zoning could undermine regulatory capture by wealthy neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“If somebody wanted to develop,” Lee said, “the only place where they can do that, especially if you’re talking about 21 stories… is North Berkeley.” I was blown away by his answer, and said so, but Lee wasn’t done yet. He went on to describe Solano Avenue business owners who told him they were only in business thanks to foot traffic from the CVS. “Mr. Capitelli, I’m coming after you,” he said without any hint of humor. “Why is it that we aren’t taxing these vacant storefronts? Why aren’t these high-rise buildings coming up [on Solano]? Instead of building so much on Shattuck and down on Adeline, why don’t we build it in your neighborhood?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/berkeleys-homeless-mayoral-candidate-hits-the-airwaves/oakstheater.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The vacant Oaks Theater on Solano Avenue (source: Google Maps)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;I left the undisclosed location with a bit of a cough after inhaling so much tobacco smoke. Nevertheless, part of me was glad to have escaped the puritan milieu of Berkeley to somewhere people could smoke indoors. In parting, Lee offered a firm handshake and his eagerness to stay in touch throughout the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At press time, the Tiny Homes project with Capitelli remains on hold until after the election.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/berkeley-faces-federal-lawsuit-over-post-office-sale/">
    <title type="text">Berkeley Faces Federal Lawsuit Over Post Office Sale</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:efa8c710-d3fb-377e-b7d2-24cb451ea86e</id>
    <updated>2016-08-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/berkeley-faces-federal-lawsuit-over-post-office-sale/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The debate over Berkeley’s historic downtown post office has reached new heights. The United States Postal Service filed a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trauss.com/pdfs/berkpostofficesuit.pdf&quot;&gt;lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; in federal court yesterday alleging that Berkeley’s zoning changes in the neighborhood prevented them from selling their property to generate much-needed revenue. (As of 3:00 PM today, the Berkeley City Attorney’s office says they have not been formally served.)&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In 2012, the Postal Service put its property at 2000 Allston Way up for sale, noting that it only used 4,000 square feet of the 57,000 square foot building. Amid possibilities of new development, Berkeley locals launched a vociferous &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.savethebpo.com/&quot;&gt;Save the Post Office&lt;/a&gt; campaign to block the sale of the property. This campaign gathered signatures for what eventually became the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/City_of_Berkeley_Zoning_Ordinance_Amendments,_Measure_R_(November_2014&quot;&gt;2014 Measure R&lt;/a&gt;), a ballot measure to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.greenbelt.org/blog/examiner-com-measure-r-bad-policy-berkeley/&quot;&gt;lower height limits&lt;/a&gt; in Downtown Berkeley, drafted largely by Councilmember Jesse Arreguin and Zoning Board Member Sophie Hahn.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The heated tensions of downtown development ignited over what initially appeared to be an innocuous transaction. The Postal Service has been hamstrung by federal regulations requiring the agency to prepay its pension plans, while also being prevented from raising its prices to compensate. In response, the USPS has put dozens of historic real estate assets on the market. The recent “historic” overlay in the zoning of Berkeley’s Civic Center District effectively prevented its sale for most viable commercial or residential purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Initially, that didn’t stop the Postal Service from trying: in 2014, local developer Hudson McDonald offered to buy the property and keep it publicly accessible, but then retreated due to “uncertainty” in the surrounding community.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The City of Berkeley then sued the federal agency to force them to drop any attempted sale. Although the suit was thrown out of court, Berkeley succeeded in its goal, only to engender threats of litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The United States Postal Service was not bluffing. In their suit, the plaintiff alleges: “Enacted primarily to prevent the sale of the Berkeley Main Post Office, the Zoning Ordinance limits the Property to civic or nonprofit uses. By prohibiting any commercially viable uses, the…Zoning Ordinance therefore prevents the Postal Service from fulfilling its responsibilities under federal law, and is invalid under the Supremacy Clause of the United States Constitution...”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The suit goes on to detail the many ways in which, despite engagement with the local community, the Postal Service’s efforts at compromise were stonewalled by the City. Offers to preserve the historic façade of the building were rejected as insufficient by what the plaintiff depicts as byzantine bureaucratic standards.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;At press time, no hearing date has been set for the lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/city-controller-says-18-is-the-new-25-for-sfs-prop-c/">
    <title type="text">City Controller Says 18 Is the New 25 for SF's Prop C</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:640568cc-3617-341f-b244-53c34b59babd</id>
    <updated>2016-08-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/city-controller-says-18-is-the-new-25-for-sfs-prop-c/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The project at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfchronicle.com/politics/article/Development-with-25-percent-affordable-housing-9157776.php&quot;&gt;1515 South Van Ness&lt;/a&gt; (pictured above) struck a deal with the city to provide 25% Below Market Rate units. Some supporters called it unprecedented, while others insist it should be the new citywide standard. Under &lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/San_Francisco,_California,_Affordable_Housing_Requirements_Charter_Amendment,_Proposition_C_(June_2016&quot;&gt;Proposition C&lt;/a&gt;), that may now be the case, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/politics/article/Affordable-rent-demand-could-slow-construction-in-9178589.php?utm_source=twitterfeed&amp;amp;utm_medium=twitter&quot;&gt;new evidence&lt;/a&gt; suggests that may not be a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisors Jane Kim and Aaron Peskin were adamant last year that their ballot measure set an economically sound baseline for affordable housing requirements in the nation’s most expensive city. Requiring 25% of units to be indexed Below Market Rate in any new project was not an arbitrary standard, they claimed, but one assiduously negotiated between the Supervisors and developers to maximize subsidies without slowing housing construction. According to city comptroller Ben Rosenfield, their math is off.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Mayor Ed Lee withdrew his opposition to the “arbitrary” requirement of Prop C on the condition that Kim and Peskin would adjust the requirements after a feasibility analysis. Rosenfield’s recently published draft feasibility analysis recommends a lower threshold, but one that should be applied equally across the city. While this urging is likely to incense local activists who insist on higher percentages in higher-demand areas such as the Mission, Rosenfield also recommends increasing required in-lieu fees to incentivize the construction of more units.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“New apartment buildings can rent a maximum of 18 percent affordable units before new housing is likely to be impeded,” the draft report concludes. Neither Peskin nor Kim’s offices could be reached for immediate comment.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-mayor-gives-interview-we-give-up/">
    <title type="text">Palo Alto Mayor Gives Interview, We Give Up</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:1e586c0d-677c-30f8-b5ca-f91714cd01ed</id>
    <updated>2016-08-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/palo-alto-mayor-gives-interview-we-give-up/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Local resident Kate V. Downing recently made &lt;a href=&quot;http://sanfrancisco.cbslocal.com/2016/08/12/kate-vershov-downing-palo-alto-planning-commission-pricey-housing/&quot;&gt;headlines&lt;/a&gt; after delivering her very public resignation from Palo Alto's Planning Commission. Mayor Patrick Burt responded to the media firestorm in an interview with Curbed published today and... we just can't even. We can't. Read it for yourself &lt;a href=&quot;http://sf.curbed.com/2016/8/23/12603188/palo-alto-mayor-housing-interview&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/new-project-with-ample-parking-planned-for-uptown-oakland/">
    <title type="text">New Project With Ample Parking Planned for Uptown Oakland</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:0a7ea00f-ae82-36ef-a07c-fc3750ec8a12</id>
    <updated>2016-08-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/new-project-with-ample-parking-planned-for-uptown-oakland/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A 7-story apartment &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eastbayredeveloped.com/2016/08/oakland-1750-webster-7-story-mixed-user.html&quot;&gt;complex&lt;/a&gt; may soon break ground at the intersection of 19th &amp;amp; Harrison in Oakland, mere blocks from the 19th Street BART Station. Developers at Lennar have proposed 224 residential units above 3,700 square feet of ground-floor retail at 1750 Webster, which would include 219 parking spaces despite its proximity to transit.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The new building would share a block with a proposed 24-story mixed-use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2015/05/oakland-housing-tower-gerding-edlen-perkins-will.html&quot;&gt;tower&lt;/a&gt; at 1700 Webster. At only 206 units, the “vertical neighborhood” designed by Perkins + Will, the architecture firm that renovated San Francisco’s Ferry Building, would be less dense than Lennar’s mid-rise project. As the Oakland market becomes more competitive and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/real-estate/2016/01/oakland-development-few-land-deals-housing.html&quot;&gt;difficult to finance&lt;/a&gt;, the 1700 Webster tower managed to secure full financing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Lennar is also currently developing a similar mid-rise project in Berkeley, known as Parker Place.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/two-new-projects-coming-to-mission-street/">
    <title type="text">Two New Projects Coming to Mission Street</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:a42bd60f-12cc-30ae-b4cb-bd3d6a942446</id>
    <updated>2016-08-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/two-new-projects-coming-to-mission-street/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In a San Francisco neighborhood plagued by electrical fires and a lack of sprinkler systems, two five-story phoenixes may soon rise from the ashes. A 16-unit building has been proposed for the now-vacant lot at 2630 Mission Street, 5 feet under the 65-foot height limit, but a full three stories above the surrounding buildings. The lot was left vacant (pictured above) when a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/20/arts/television/dick-assman-briefly-a-late-show-celebrity-dies-at-82.html&quot;&gt;5-alarm fire&lt;/a&gt; destroyed the Big House discount store in late 2014. Project sponsors Gabriel Ng + Architects have not specified if they will provide on-site Below Market Rental units or pay an impact fee, as required by the city.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The building at 2610 Mission Street may soon see significant renovations that would add 4 stories (with only 8 dwelling units) above ground-floor retail. The building had been home to Anna’s Linens, which recently filed for bankruptcy. The master tenant, which had been subletting to Anna’s Linens, recently accepted a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.socketsite.com/archives/2016/03/tenant-buyout-clears-the-way-to-raise-the-roof-on-mission.html&quot;&gt;buyout offer&lt;/a&gt; to truncate the remaining 30 years of a 99-year lease. At 8 units, the project falls below the 10-unit city threshold to require a fee or BMR units, and it also will not require approval by the Planning Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/a-moment-of-silence-for-governors-by-right-proposal/">
    <title type="text">A Moment of Silence for Governor's By-Right Proposal</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:85fb2b5f-bef9-3493-b2c0-a3164190d810</id>
    <updated>2016-08-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/a-moment-of-silence-for-governors-by-right-proposal/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A long, sad trombone note echoes through our SF YIMBY office today as we mourn Governor Edmund G. “Jerry” Brown’s by-right housing bill, a legislative beacon of housing hope taken from us far too soon.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Imagery aside, this truly does mark a disappointing move by the State Assembly, and a backward step toward solving the state’s acute housing shortage. Jerry Brown’s proposal would have streamlined construction that complied with local zoning and planning requirements and included a portion of below-market-rate housing, removing additional layers of local review that add to lengthy timelines and ultimately, increase housing costs. Not only that, the bill included a $400 million appropriation for affordable housing, funding California has been starved for.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;While approving a compliant, affordable housing-inclusive project should sound like a no-brainer, the bill was vehemently opposed by labor groups, environmentalists, and tenant activists, whose demands appear to have eventually taken down the proposal. Several weeks ago, environmentalists and unions walked away from negotiations with the governor’s office before a compromise could be reached, and it didn’t take much longer before the bill was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sacbee.com/news/politics-government/capitol-alert/article96492302.html?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;amp;utm_medium=twitter&quot;&gt;deemed “dead”&lt;/a&gt; for the year by Assembly leader Anthony Rendon.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We applaud Jerry Brown for initiating this bill. Addressing the housing shortage at the state level is one of our best hopes at increasing our housing supply, as local land use restrictions have increasingly transferred decision-making power to wealthy, incumbent homeowners, at the expense of those in need of housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, a bill of this nature will rise from the ashes next year.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/designs-released-for-affordable-housing-in-telegraph-hill/">
    <title type="text">Designs Released for Affordable Housing in Telegraph Hill</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:3577ee25-145e-324a-bf3d-ee60284c3466</id>
    <updated>2016-08-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/designs-released-for-affordable-housing-in-telegraph-hill/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Architects at Leddy Maytum Stacy recently &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfport.com/88-broadway-seawall-lot-322-1&quot;&gt;released&lt;/a&gt; their plans for a 6-story building with 186 units of affordable housing at 88 Broadway Street, at the base of Telegraph Hill. Known as Seawall Lot 322-1, the project has been described by the Port of San Francisco as “the greatest affordable housing development opportunity among the Port’s seawall lots in the northeastern waterfront.” Nevertheless, the project has faced stiff opposition from incumbent neighborhood groups, including the Telegraph Hill Dwellers, over the specific parameters of affordability.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In the current plan, 11,400 square feet of ground-floor retail would replace what is currently a parking lot. Above it, BRIDGE Housing and the John Stewart Company will be partnering to build 150 residential units for households making 40-120% of the Area Median Income, with an additional 32 units reserved for senior citizens earning 40-70% AMI. The project would also include a mixed-income childcare center run by the YMCA of San Francisco. Lutheran Social Services will also provide on-site support for 37 apartments reserved by subsidies for formerly homeless households.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A coalition of local groups such as the Barbary Coast Neighborhood Association and the Telegraph Hill Dwellers successfully forced developers and the city to include units for households earning 80-120% of Area Median Income. Barbary Coast president Robert Harrer told the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/morning_call/2015/03/telegraph-hill-port-parking-lot-affordable-housing.html&quot;&gt;Business Times&lt;/a&gt;, “We don't want to be a neighborhood that ends up with just the rich and poor. We want a neighborhood that's for everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The median home price in Telegraph Hill is listed as $1.1 million on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zillow.com/telegraph-hill-san-francisco-ca/home-values/&quot;&gt;Zillow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/third-candidate-joins-district-9-bart-board-race/">
    <title type="text">Third Candidate Joins District 9 BART Board Race</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:14f5b47e-e7a2-323e-96c6-29a2bef1c503</id>
    <updated>2016-08-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/third-candidate-joins-district-9-bart-board-race/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Outside of California, voters don’t elect their transit officials. That changed for San Francisco in 1972, and now BART District races can be as competitive as elections for State Assembly. Shortly before the filing deadline, Gwyneth Borden threw her hat in the ring for the BART Board of Directors election in District 9. Voters will now choose between local activist Michael Petrelis, former Supervisor Bevan Dufty, and Borden.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Borden currently serves as Director of the SFMTA, and is a Commissioner on the Parking Authority. She is also Executive Director of the Golden Gate Restaurant Association, a nonprofit representing regional restaurants, and formerly worked at IBM.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Borden has been a steadfast advocate for car-alternative infrastructure during her tenure with the SFMTA. Just this week, as opponents railed against the bus-only red lanes on Mission Street as “ethnic cleansing,” Borden fired back with a diplomatic resolve to diminish the perception of a “malicious intent” by the transit authority.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Primarily people of color are disproportionately impacted by the time it takes to get from where they live…to where there is more activity,” she said, insisting that SFMTA had designed the lanes as part of a broader MUNI Equity Study. “I take that bus every single day…I don’t have a car,” she noted. She described an experience of riding “packed” buses along Mission Street, filled mostly with senior citizens and people of color commuting to work.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Business is down this year and we don’t know why,” she added, noting that the city's port had also reported revenue losses that year, regardless of new bus lanes. “The intent was right,” she reiterated. “This is a start…This is not about trying to push people out. This is about trying to include and bring more people to where they need to go more quickly.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Whatever one’s opinion on the bus lanes may be, it is beyond any doubt that Dufty and Petrelis now face stiff competition.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/yes-even-hollywood-liberals-love-sprawl/">
    <title type="text">Yes, Even Hollywood Liberals Love Sprawl</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:75cfa2c1-14bd-37a2-91ef-4436f86fee1c</id>
    <updated>2016-08-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/yes-even-hollywood-liberals-love-sprawl/" />
    <author>
      <name>Leigha Beckman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leigha Beckman is a Special Contributor to SF YIMBY.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Los Angeles – that bastion of car-centric metro sprawl, has lately made surprising progress toward smart, urban growth in recent years. It has dramatically increased residential density downtown with some 22,000 new units under construction; its car ridership is trending downward, and LA Metro plans to raise $120 billion with a sales tax measure on projects like Bus Rapid Transit (“BRT”) corridors and light rail extensions.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Things have been looking good for Los Angeles – until now.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;And before I go any further, I must say that admitting anything positive about LA as a San Franciscan is heresy, obviously; even worse if you are from the perennially blaspheming Orange County like me, and NorCal apostasy is your thing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;But for once, being from Orange County doesn’t make me the villain in this story. No, that award goes to the likes of shiny blue medalists Leonardo DiCaprio, Kirsten Dunst, and Joaquin Phoenix, amongst other Hollywood stars who are backing a conservative, regressive anti-growth measure called the “Neighborhood Integrity Initiative”. These celebrities, whose well-informed opinions about urban planning policy surely matter, decided to lend their “famous people I like support this” credence to the proposal’s merits.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The appealingly monikered “Neighborhood Integrity Initiative” is a proposed ballot measure that would severely inhibit development in LA by essentially banning any deviations from the existing General Plan (a restrictive and outdated framework responsible for heavy downzoning and the sprawling mess we see today), and worst of all place a two-year moratorium on any development project that requires an exemption from the area's height requirement (which would be most of them).&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Franciscans – sound familiar? Remember Prop I from last November?&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;If you know anything about local politics—in virtually any locality—you should know that something called the “Neighborhood Integrity Initiative” is pretty much guaranteed to lack integrity, and far more likely to favor paranoid incumbency and fear-mongering over common sense or forward thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let’s take a closer look at the 23-page measure itself, rather than skimming emotionally charged aphorisms from biased sources, because the text of the bill is what actually matters, not a slogan on Leo’s T-shirt. (Not that Leo wears t-shirts.) As with most ballot measures of this nature, it begins with a slew of dramatized findings that allegedly characterize our present, but follows those findings with backward looking solutions as the irrefutable fix.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In fairness, the initiative does capitalize on a truth of Los Angeles’s planning system, which is that existing design perimeters (height limits and zoning restrictions, in particular) can be maneuvered through various workarounds in the planning code. What it fails to do is address those shortcomings in a method beneficial to the overall urban planning landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;For example, this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Piecemeal amendment of the City’s General Plan violates principles of comprehensiveness and long-term general planning embedded in the City’s Charter…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;is a fair objection. Why have a General Plan if you’re going to bypass its requirements with each new project? But this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“The development of projects containing a significant component of multifamily housing has an adverse impact on health and safety when such projects are approved in areas that are not currently zoned for housing on such a scale or which do not currently permit housing on such a scale under the General Plan…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;is misleading and reactionary. The implication that apartment buildings should only go up where we zoned for them to decades ago – never mind any changes in planning needs, population growth, or new academic literature that may better inform our decision-making – flies in the face of the desperate housing needs of a growing number of young adults, newcomers, renters, and otherwise non-comfortably housed LA residents.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;80 to 85% of Los Angeles is zoned for single-family homes. While that sounds great it you already a single-family homeowner – an increasingly exclusive privilege – it severely limits the ability to find housing for everyone else. This zoning system leaves just 15-20% of LA’s zoned areas available for everything else, including multifamily residences.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;So rather than acknowledge that perhaps zoning laws need to be updated, the measure invokes a protectionist “get off my lawn” attitude toward newcomers, or even existing residents who are being choked by the region’s exorbitant housing costs.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It is worth reiterating that car ridership is declining. The initiative would probably undo that, by calcifying parking space requirements for new developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“…under no circumstances may the required on-site parking be reduced by more than one-third (including by remote off-site parking) from the number of spaces otherwise required to be provided by any other applicable provisions of the Los Angeles Municipal Code.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This is especially ironic given that one of the measure’s chief concerns is that new residents strain existing roads and other infrastructure, so rather than looking for ways to promote bicycling and other less impactful forms of transit, they instead double-down on maintaining (or limiting the reduction of) existing parking requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;And finally, if you think you are being green by blocking new development in dense, urban areas, empirical evidence would like a word with you. We need population growth to take place in already-developed, preferably urban locations – otherwise we sprawl outward in energy-draining, polluting, increasingly unsustainable ways. Living in cities is far better for the environment than the low-density system of sprawl the NII folks seem to prefer: the average carbon footprint of households living in the center of large, population-dense urban cities is about 50 percent below average, while households in distant suburbs are up to twice the average.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This is a dismaying display of reactionary, old-guard NIMBYism, and just as dismaying that ostensibly left-leaning, well-meaning Hollywood names are behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Now is not the time for LA to lock in an outdated planning code. If the planning system is broken, let’s apply forward-looking fixes – not an unwanted sequel of the failed past.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/breed-vows-to-fight-for-neighborhood-preference-ordinance/">
    <title type="text">Breed Vows to Fight for Neighborhood Preference Ordinance</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:abe3304d-8684-31c8-80f6-fa16111d7814</id>
    <updated>2016-08-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/breed-vows-to-fight-for-neighborhood-preference-ordinance/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;This morning, Supervisor London Breed called a press conference in the Western Addition neighborhood to engage the public in her resolve to protect her Neighborhood Preference &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/san-francisco-adopts-neighborhood-preference-for-affordable-housing-lottery/&quot;&gt;legislation&lt;/a&gt; in the face of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfexaminer.com/san-francisco-adopts-neighborhood-preference-for-affordable-housing-lottery/&quot;&gt;federal pushback&lt;/a&gt;. Breed’s ordinance, passed last year, would reserve 40% of Below Market Rentals built in San Francisco for residents living within the same supervisorial district, or a half-mile away. The Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) said recently that they considered giving priority to local residents in a highly competitive lottery to be a potential violation of the Fair Housing Act.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Surrounded by African-American community leaders, in the shadow of the Willie B. Kennedy Apartments with 98 units for seniors, Breed capitalized on the vagueness of HUD’s decree to underscore its hypocrisy. In her view, it was not segregation to give preference to local residents, but rather an effort to fight back against decades of segregation and economic isolation. She had strategically located the press conference across the street from the public housing where she had grown up, and walking distance from other housing projects that had also benefited from neighborhood preference.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/breed-vows-to-fight-for-neighborhood-preference-ordinance/western-addition.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A southern view of the Western Addition neighborhood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Even Willie Mays was not allowed to live in Forest Hills,” noted the Rev. Amos Brown, president of the local NAACP Chapter. He described how the Western Addition had become a hub for the local African American community, which had lost 60,000 residents since 1970, because of restrictive covenants preventing them from living in other neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Malia Cohen, also in attendance, added that the ordinance was designed to help other disadvantaged communities in San Francisco, including Latinos and Pacific Islanders. “It is not exclusionary…it is reversing a pattern of exclusion.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor Breed noted that the Neighborhood Preference ordinance was already in effect at the nearby housing project at 55 Laguna Street. Additionally, she pointed to New York City’s longstanding policy of neighborhood preference as a successful strategy for stemming gentrification and displacement. She also described plans to work with the Mayor’s Office of Housing to “hit the streets and get the word out” to help as many local residents in need to fill out applications. Cathy Davis, Executive Director of Bayview Senior Services, said she would be leading volunteers 7 days a week in helping locals apply for housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Breed insisted that San Francisco’s shrinking black population had “no fair chance” to access new affordable housing units. She described a process in which a competitive advantage is gained by organizing thousands of applicants to flood the lottery. The neighborhood’s largely poor and black residents, she said, could not compete with these resources. “There are people here I see daily who are struggling to live here…who has time to complete an application when you’re struggling?”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“San Francisco has been living a lie,” the Reverend Dr. Amos Brown declared. “This mayor and the Board have sought to tell the truth.” He criticized HUD’s judgment as an example of “left-brained bureaucracy…without compassion.” Further, the SF Chapter President promised that the NAACP would plan to file an injunction to stop further rentals until they could negotiate with HUD officials. He urged all those in attendance to join his efforts and “stop this hemorrhaging and loss of the black community in San Francisco.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Breed was far more diplomatic in announcing her plan, saying that she planned to meet with Senator Dianne Feinstein and Representative Nancy Pelosi. She had also already given Julian Castro, current Secretary of HUD, a walking tour of the Western Addition.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;It was also noted that the Western Addition had lost 30,000 residents during the period of Redevelopment in the 1970s, when many public housing projects were torn down and never replaced. In later remarks, Breed made mention of the “Pink Palace” apartments that had once been at the same location—an apartment where Dianne Feinstein, as mayor in the 70s, had managed to prioritize senior housing with neighborhood preference.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisors Breed and Cohen were later joined by local activist Rico Hamilton. As a resident of the Western Addition, he described the local community as being “in disbelief” at HUD’s opinion, given the area’s history of racial segregation and concentrated poverty. He also noted that he was “technically homeless” as he was not leasing his current place of residence.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When asked about the comparison to New York City’s longstanding policy, Breed said that she did not know why HUD had decided to impugn her legislation, less than a year old. “They did not said they know, or think—they believe it might be in violation of the Fair Housing Act.” HUD’s indictment of her policy appeared to be a mere hunch, in her interpretation. “We can’t live on a hunch,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Dr. Amos Brown then stepped in to described what he believed to be a local conspiracy to undermine Breed’s legislation. “I have it on good authority that there are people in this city who are opposed to the ordinance, who have HUD’s ear,” he said. “The enemy is in the camp.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;When reached by phone, Dr. Brown was unable to elaborate on his sources or any further details. But he did add further lurid allegations: “All I can tell you is there was organized opposition to [Breed’s ordinance]. The regional HUD office knew about the adversary group stacking applications against [locals]. They also told developers that they didn’t have to advertise in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbayview.com/&quot;&gt;Bay View&lt;/a&gt;, and other black newspapers…They [regional HUD office] knew this was going on, and then tell us that we can’t pursue a measure that would help to ensure this hemorrhaging stops.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/feds-strike-down-san-franciscos-neighborhood-preference-policy/">
    <title type="text">Feds Strike Down San Francisco's Neighborhood Preference Policy</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:ebedd2fa-c897-390b-ae62-a4745a73003b</id>
    <updated>2016-08-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/feds-strike-down-san-franciscos-neighborhood-preference-policy/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Late last year, Board of Supervisors President London Breed touted the passage of a neighborhood preference ordinance intended to protect vulnerable residents of color from displacement. Under the ordinance, 40 percent of all new Below Market Rentals would be reserved for income-certified people already living in the supervisorial district in which a new project was being built, or within a half-mile of the project. The federal government just declared that ordinance &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trauss.com/pdfs/WBK_neighborhood_preference.pdf&quot;&gt;illegal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Gustavo Velasquez, the Department of Housing and Urban Development’s assistant secretary for fair housing and equal opportunity , penned a letter to the mayor’s Office of Housing and Community Development, which said that Breed’s plan could “limit equal access to housing and perpetuate segregation” in violation of the 1968 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair_Housing_Act&quot;&gt;Fair Housing Act&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The ordinance was intended to give the city’s poorer incumbent residents, particularly African Americans, a local advantage in affordable housing lotteries. Supporters noted that although San Francisco’s population has sharply declined, from 13.7% in 1970 to just 5.7% today, only 4.7% of new privately subsidized units went to African Americans. Meanwhile, 56% of the city-county’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/S-F-jail-inmates-56-black-4744799.php&quot;&gt;jail inmates&lt;/a&gt; are black.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“It is the best first step that we have,” Supervisor Malia Cohen had said at the time, saying it “was not the perfect solution.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;HUD’s decision will have an immediate impact on those seeking affordable housing. Because of its dependence on federal funding, local residents will no longer receive preference in the lottery for the Willie B. Kennedy development at the Turk and Webster intersection in the Western Addition, a 98-unit senior housing development. The Tenderloin Neighborhood Development Corporation, the non-profit developer that plans to open the project in the fall, received $15.2 million from the federal agency, which will also subsidize rents exceeding 30% of future residents’ income.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supervisor London Breed, a native of the Western Addition who was raised in public housing, described it as a “devastating blow” to San Francisco’s black population. “I’m not giving up that easy,” she added in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LondonBreed/status/765936705559855104&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/los-gatos-delays-decision-on-320-units/">
    <title type="text">Los Gatos Delays Decision on 320 Units</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:c035aaf7-8014-37d7-b16e-1600c3c6a1a5</id>
    <updated>2016-08-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/los-gatos-delays-decision-on-320-units/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;We reported last month that Los Gatos would be facing a contentious decision on a mixed-use apartment development in the North 40 area, at the intersection of two highways. Last night, the Los Gatos Town Council voted to postpone thei decision on the 320-unit project until September.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Spearheaded by Eden Housing and SummerHill Homes, the dwelling units come as part of a broader development by Grosvernor Americas which would also include 66,381 square feet of retail space and open, walkable plazas decorated with local flora.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/los-gatos-delays-decision-on-320-units/n40.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Map of the proposed North 40 project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Councilmember Marcia Jensen urged an unsuccessful motion to approve the project. She cited the region’s dire need for new housing, mentioning both Kate Downing’s recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://shift.newco.co/letter-of-resignation-from-the-palo-alto-planning-and-transportation-commission-f7b6facd94f5#.g3y6hlb57&quot;&gt;resignation&lt;/a&gt; from the Palo Alto Planning Commission, as well as local litigation group &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carlaef.org/&quot;&gt;CaRLA&lt;/a&gt;’s threat to sue under the Housing Accountability Act.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“Beauty is in the eye of the beholder,” she argued. “That’s a subjective standard.” She later reminded the audience, “we all live in houses that used to be an orchard.” She also delivered scathing rebuttals to those who scoffed at the threat of litigation. “Lots of you said, 'don't worry about litigation, we'll deal with that.' …Threatening to sue is not bullying,” she insisted. “Bullying is being called a murderer in a town council meeting. Bullying is getting cars broken into and trashed.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Jensen seemed to be fully aware that her unpopular opinion could face blowback. “I recognize that saying what I'm saying now, there are personal consequences to that.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite the controversy, a contesting motion by Mayor Barbara Spector to deny approval of the project also failed to pass. After further discussion, the mayor expressed her primary concern to be the cost of market-rate rentals, not the density, and suggested she could support the project if it included Below Market Rentals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Eventually a motion to delay the decision did pass, on the condition that Los Gatos would consult with the California Department of Housing &amp;amp; Community Development on the city’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abag.ca.gov/planning/housingneeds/pdfs/comments/6-21-12%20RHNA%20Comments_Los%20Gatos.pdf&quot;&gt;Regional Housing Needs Allocation&lt;/a&gt;, and study the “economics” of the situation. The project is expected to return before the council in September.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-jose-approves-102-temporary-housing-units/">
    <title type="text">San Jose Approves 102 Temporary Housing Units</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:2ba24fec-6656-3bee-8e1c-7694ac1d3438</id>
    <updated>2016-08-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-jose-approves-102-temporary-housing-units/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;San Jose’s City Council voted yesterday to approve a temporary modular housing project on Evans Lane, amid vocal criticism in support of a permanent alternative. The proposal passed by an 8-3 vote, with Pierluigi Oliverio, Manh Nguyen and Johnny Khamis opposed in the dissent.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The site on Evans lane lies in the Willow Glen neighborhood of South San Jose, just off the Almaden Expressway. Oliverio (pictured above), whose district covers the site, insisted that he would prefer to see high-density apartments built on the 6 acres of city-owned land. He stated that “housing 1,000 people in the long term versus 102 people in the short term is the better option,” adding that the temporary project would worsen problems in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/san-jose-approves-102-temporary-housing-units/almaden_expressway.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almaden Expressway, San Jose&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;There will be 102 temporary modular homes in the approved project, which could house at least two people each, as opposed to the 446 permanent units in the alternative proposal. Staff emphasized that only half of the 446 would be “affordable.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;City staff recommended the temporary modular units, provided by non-profit developers Abode Servoces, on the basis of greater financial feasibility and more immediate relief in the midst of the city’s shelter crisis. Abode’s project would cost $15 million in city funds and open in the summer of 2017 until 2032; the previous permanent proposal would be completed in 2022 and cost $109 million, with city funds leveraged with state and federal subsidies. Oliverio objected to this projection in moving to pass the permanent alternative, suggesting that many developers would be interested in building o”n the site, “by my discussions, faster than the timeline staff has provided.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;In their presentation, city staff urged the council to not consider the alternatives to be at cross purposes. “If you approve this…we will continue to build permanent affordable housing,” said city housing director Jacky Morales-Ferrand. In staff’s assessment, the interim housing would merely “prep them” to move into move into “permanent, supportive” housing after more is built.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Permanent housing for the homeless population, according to staff, “will lag because of need for financing”—moreover, they urged council to view the 102 modular units as an investment in the quality of the neighborhood. Morales-Ferrand spoke of “bringing more amenities” to a neighborhood which she admitted “has been left behind.” The Adobe project will include a dog park, small library and community garden.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A Willow Glen resident speaking in favor of the permanent option described his neighborhood as a proud working-class Latino &amp;amp; Vietnamese community that focused on their families after working long weekday hours. Temporary residents, on the other hand, “would leave after nine months…and if people don’t care about the community, they don’t care about the neighborhood.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Approval came late in the night, with the meeting lasting a total of seven and a half hours.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Residents will share the site with four case managers and two property managers, and will have 24-hour security. Adobe Services plans on the land from the city for $1 a year, as well as passing on any net profit the project may yield.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/at-planning-commission-debates-over-diversity-and-affordability/">
    <title type="text">At Planning Commission, Debates Over Diversity And Affordability</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:f3cf29e6-309d-3115-9fdf-0a27921f873f</id>
    <updated>2016-08-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/at-planning-commission-debates-over-diversity-and-affordability/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Two mixed-use construction &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/08/mission-district-housing-project-reaches-25-percent-affordable/&quot;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; in the Mission came before the Planning Commission last Thursday, facing a broad spectrum of reactions from the local community. The proposal at 2600 Harrison Street, replacing an empty warehouse with 19 dwelling units and ground-floor industrial space, was largely welcomed. Subsequently, a larger project at 1515 South Van Ness Avenue (pictured above) faced staunch opposition from neighborhood groups, despite an unprecedented 25% of the units reserved for Below Market Rentals.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Supporters speaking in favor of 2600 Harrison noted that it could be a strong catalyst for the city’s languishing Small Sites Acquisition Program, with the potential to “preserve the existing fabric of the community.” Rather than including on-site Below Market Rental units, the developer will be providing $1.1 million to the city’s program, which buys existing buildings to protect tenants living in affordable housing.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Commission vice-president Dennis Richards noted how unusual the tenor of this particular hearing was. “I think this is a great project. I never thought I’d see people from this part of town get up and talk about their support of this project.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Local activists cited the project as a model for how neighbors and developers could better collaborate in the future. “This is the kind of process we’d like to see,” said Peter Papadopolous of the Cultural Action Network. In contrast, Cultural Action Network had previously coalesced in opposition to a much larger project at &lt;a href=&quot;http://missionlocal.org/2016/06/after-years-of-delay-bryant-street-housing-project-moves-forward/&quot;&gt;2000 Bryant Street&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Papadopolous and Erick Arguello, president of Calle 24, were more lukewarm in their reception of the 157-unit project at 1515 South Van Ness, saying they needed more time to negotiate with the developer. Arguello insisted that local stakeholders wanted to see the Below Market Rental allotment ideally raised to 30-35%. Yet supporters noted that the developer, Lennar Corporation, had made the unprecedented move of offering 25%. “This project has the highest level of affordable housing on-site that we’ve seen,” Commissioner Rich Hills stated. In his estimation, no project had reserved a greater proportion of permanently affordable units without government subsidies or zoning changes.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Previous community negotiations had nearly doubled the percentage from an earlier 13.5%. Local residents in opposition still bemoaned that the new units would “change the demographic” of the Mission District. The project now offers 25% Below Market Rentals even though it was grandfathered into the earlier 12% requirement, before the passage of Proposition C.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;A local resident who grew up a block away from the project said it would be “fantastic” to see a “beautiful” structure at the site. He described the location as consisting of three gas stations and a phone-booth bar during his childhood. Another supporter urged the commission to approve the project because of an existing agreement to use all-union labor for construction.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Opponents in the neighborhood insisted that the provision of new market-rate construction would only further drive out the area’s poor minority residents. Scott Feeney, a Mission resident who supported the project, countered this concern: “Where are those rich people going to live if they don’t have a new apartment to move into?” he asked. “The obvious answer is…they’re going to have to look at older housing stock. By doing that, they drive up prices of old apartments that were once relatively affordable to the middle class.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;photo-with-caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../news/at-planning-commission-debates-over-diversity-and-affordability/missionimby.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;news_photo&quot;/&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;photo-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Don't call it market-rate.&quot; (source: SF GovTV)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;“I’m not going to have anything in common with the rich people living right down the street, one speaker insisted. (Another speaker supporting the project offered to meet with her afterwards to find things they had in common.) In bemoaning the changing demographics of the area, the speaker summed up the ongoing economic debate: “Don’t call it market-rate. In San Francisco, market-rate is luxury housing.”&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Members of Calle 24 insisted that the project had the potential to disrupt the newly designated Latino Cultural District, intended to preserve legacy Latino businesses. “We believe it can be better,” Arguello noted in asking for a continuance.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;Despite these demands, the planning commission unanimously approved both projects.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-francisco-2088-the-last-olympic-city-in-the-us/">
    <title type="text">San Francisco 2088: The Last Olympic City in the US?</title>
    <id>urn:uuid:99a6d968-c236-3100-a42e-9848d79c919f</id>
    <updated>2016-08-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://sfbamo.com/news/san-francisco-2088-the-last-olympic-city-in-the-us/" />
    <author>
      <name>Diego Aguilar Canabal</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;div class=&quot;text-block&quot;&gt;
	
	
	

  
    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;On warm summer days in the Bay Area, one can often hear an onlooker remark, while gazing at the shimmering clear sky, “this is what we pay exorbitant rents for—this perfect weather.” In 2088, another major industry may be making the same overtures toward San Francisco: the Olympics.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;UK medical journal The Lancet’s recently published &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0140673616313356&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, “The last Summer Olympics? Climate change, health, and work outdoors” seeks to evaluate which major cities around the globe could withstand global warming enough to host the 2088 Olympics. Researchers Kirk Smith of UC Berkeley, Alistair Woodard, and other global health scientists paint a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fastcodesign.com/3062819/the-list-of-cities-that-could-host-the-2086-olympics-is-very-very-short&quot;&gt;grim picture&lt;/a&gt;. In the United States, San Francisco is the only city whose climate could support outdoor athletic competitions during the daytime.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The paper assumes that the International Olympic Committee would not want to host the events where there would be a 10% or higher chance that games must be cancelled to avoid heat stroke or death. (The research limits itself to the Northern Hemisphere due to its greater concentration of the world's population.) Only Calgary, Vancouver, and San Francisco would qualify in North America. Asia would only have two worth the risk: the capital cities of Bishkek, Kyrgyzstan, and Ulanbataar, Mongolia. By the 2100s, the only suitable cities left would be Belfast, Dublin, Edinburgh, and Glasgow.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;The paper also points to the so-called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.runnersworld.com/races/2007-chicago-marathon-melt-down&quot;&gt;“meltdown”&lt;/a&gt; of the aborted 2007 Chicago Marathon, in which 185 runners were raced to hospitals, and one contestant died. Kirk, Woodart et al insist this is evidence the patterns they predict are already well underway.&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
    
				&lt;p&gt;More alarming is what researchers call the “pernicious impact” of climate change: overwhelming detriments for labor and the world’s poorest populations. Half of the world’s population works outside during the daytime, and Smith predicts that necessary changes in daytime behavior will be met with strong resistance from bosses trying to streamline productivity. “Increasingly,” the researchers write, “people will face a choice between doing what they have done for millions of years—work hard outdoors essentially any time they wish—and being safe.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

    
  
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- END text-block --&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
